<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC0791    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2026    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2119    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2132    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2132.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2860    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2860.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2929    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2929.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2939    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2939.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3228    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3228.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3232    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3232.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3552    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3575    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3575.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3692    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3692.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3748    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3942    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3942.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3968    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3968.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4005    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4005.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4025    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4025.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4044    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4044.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4124    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4124.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4169    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4169.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4271    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4283    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4283.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4288    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4288.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4301    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4301.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4340    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4340.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4395    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4395.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4422    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4422.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4446    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4446.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4520    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4520.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4589    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4589.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4727    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4727.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5246    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5378    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5742    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5742.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5771    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5771.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5795    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5795.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6195    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6195.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6275    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6275.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6709    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6709.xml'>

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>  
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc
  category="bcp"
  seriesNo="26"
  obsoletes="5226"
  submissionType="IETF"
  ipr="trust200902"
  docName="draft-leiba-cotton-iana-5226bis-02">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IANA Considerations Section in RFCs">
    Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs
    </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Cotton" fullname="Michelle Cotton, Manager, IANA Services">
      <organization abbrev="ICANN">
        Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>
          <city>Los Angeles</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90094-2536</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 310 301 5812</phone>
        <email>michelle.cotton@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='B.' surname="Leiba" fullname='Barry Leiba'>
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 646 827 0648</phone>
        <email>barryleiba@computer.org</email>
        <uri>http://internetmessagingtechnology.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='T.' surname="Narten" fullname='Thomas Narten'>
      <organization>IBM Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3039 Cornwallis Ave., PO Box 12195 - BRQA/502</street>
          <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
          <region>NC</region>
          <code>27709-2195</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 919 254 7798</phone>
        <email>narten@us.ibm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup></workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
   Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of constants and
   other well-known values.  Even after a protocol has been defined and
   deployment has begun, new values may need to be assigned (such as for a
   new option type in DHCP, or a new encryption or authentication
   transform for IPsec).  To ensure that such quantities have consistent
   values and interpretations across all implementations, their
   assignment must be administered by a central authority.  For IETF
   protocols, that role is provided by the Internet Assigned Numbers
   Authority (IANA).
      </t>
      <t>
   In order for IANA to manage a given namespace prudently, it needs
   guidelines describing the conditions under which new values can be
   assigned or when modifications to existing values can be made.  If
   IANA is expected to play a role in the management of a namespace,
   IANA must be given clear and concise instructions describing that
   role.  This document discusses issues that should be considered in
   formulating a policy for assigning values to a namespace and provides
   guidelines for authors on the specific text that must be included in
   documents that place demands on IANA.
      </t>
      <t>
   This document obsoletes RFC 5226.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
   Many protocols make use of fields that contain constants and other
   well-known values (such as the Protocol field in the IP header <xref target="RFC0791"/> and
   MIME media types <xref target="RFC4288"/>).  Even after a protocol has been defined
   and deployment has begun, new values may need to be assigned (such as a
   new option type in DHCP <xref target="RFC2132"/> or a new encryption or
   authentication transform for IPsec <xref target="RFC4301"/>).  To ensure that such
   fields have consistent values and interpretations in different
   implementations, their assignment must be administered by a central
   authority.  For IETF protocols, that role is provided by the Internet
   Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) <xref target="RFC2860"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
   In this document, we call the range of possible values for such a field
   a "namespace"; its actual value may be a text string, a number, or
   another kind of value.  The binding or association of a specific
   value with a particular purpose within a namespace is called an
   assigned number (or assigned value, or sometimes a "code point",
   "protocol constant", or "protocol parameter").  Each assignment of a
   value in a namespace is called a registration.
      </t>
      <t>
   In order for IANA to manage a given namespace prudently, it needs
   guidelines describing the conditions under which new values should be
   assigned or when (and how) modifications to existing values can be
   made.  This document provides guidelines to authors on what sort of
   text should be added to their documents in order to provide IANA
   clear guidelines, and it reviews issues that should be considered in
   formulating an appropriate policy for assigning numbers to name
   spaces.
      </t>
      <t>
   Not all namespaces require centralized administration.  In some
   cases, it is possible to delegate a namespace in such a way that
   further assignments can be made independently and with no further
   (central) coordination.  In the Domain Name System, for example, IANA
   only deals with assignments at the higher levels, while subdomains
   are administered by the organization to which the space has been
   delegated.  As another example, Object Identifiers (OIDs) as defined
   by the ITU are also delegated <xref target="RFC3232"/>; IANA manages the subtree
   rooted at "iso.org.dod.internet" (1.3.6.1) .  When a namespace is
   delegated, the scope of IANA is limited to the parts of the namespace
   where IANA has authority.
      </t>

      <section title="Terminology Used In This Document">
        <t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
   For this document, "the specification" as used by RFC 2119 refers to
   the processing of protocol documents within the IETF standards
   process.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="why" title="Why Management of a Namespace May Be Necessary">
      <t>
   One issue to consider in managing a namespace is its size.  If the
   space is small and limited in size, assignments must be made
   carefully to prevent exhaustion of the space.  If the space is
   essentially unlimited, on the other hand, potential exhaustion will
   probably not be a practical concern at all.  Even when the space is
   essentially unlimited, however, it is usually desirable to have at
   least a minimal review prior to assignment in order to:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
        prevent the hoarding of or unnecessary wasting of values.  For
        example, if the space consists of text strings, it may be
        desirable to prevent entities from obtaining large sets of
        strings that correspond to desirable names (existing
        company names, for example).
          </t>
          <t>
        provide a sanity check that the request actually makes sense and
        is necessary.  Experience has shown that some level of minimal
        review from a subject matter expert is useful to prevent
        assignments in cases where the request is malformed or not
        actually needed (for example, an existing assignment for an essentially
        equivalent service already exists).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
   A second consideration is whether it makes sense to delegate the
   namespace in some manner.  This route should be pursued when
   appropriate, as it lessens the burden on IANA for dealing with
   assignments.
      </t>
      <t>
   A third, and perhaps most important, consideration concerns potential
   impact on the interoperability of unreviewed extensions.  Proposed
   protocol extensions generally benefit from community review; indeed,
   review is often essential to avoid future interoperability problems
   <xref target='RFC6709' />.
      </t>
      <t>
   When the namespace is essentially unlimited and there are no
   potential interoperability issues, assigned numbers can safely be
   given out to anyone without any subjective review.  In such cases,
   IANA can make assignments directly, provided that IANA is given
   specific instructions on what types of requests it should grant, and
   what information must be provided as part of a well-formed request
   for an assigned number.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="experts" title="Designated Experts">
      <section anchor="experts-motivation" title="The Motivation for Designated Experts">
        <t>
   IANA does not create or define registry assignment policy itself; rather,
   it carries out policies that have been defined by others and published in
   RFCs. IANA must be given a set of guidelines that allow it to make
   allocation decisions with minimal subjectivity and without requiring any
   technical expertise with respect to the protocols that make use of a
   registry.
        </t>
        <t>
   In many cases, some review of prospective allocations is appropriate,
   and the question becomes who should perform the review and what is
   the purpose of the review.  One might think that an IETF working
   group familiar with the namespace at hand should be consulted.
   In practice, however, working groups eventually disband, so they cannot be
   considered a permanent evaluator.  It is also possible for namespaces
   to be created through individual submission documents, for which no
   working group is ever formed.
        </t>
        <t>
   One way to ensure community review of prospective assignments is to
   have the requester submit a document for publication as an RFC.  Such
   an action helps ensure that the specification is publicly and
   permanently available, and it allows some review of the specification
   prior to publication and assignment of the requested code points.
   This is the preferred way of ensuring review, and is particularly
   important if any potential interoperability issues can arise.  For
   example, some assignments are not just assignments, but also involve
   an element of protocol specification.  A new option may define fields
   that need to be parsed and acted on, which (if specified poorly) may
   not fit cleanly with the architecture of other options or the base
   protocols on which they are built.
        </t>
        <t>
   In some cases, however, the burden of publishing an RFC in order to
   get an assignment is excessive.  However, it is generally still
   useful (and sometimes necessary) to discuss proposed additions on a
   mailing list dedicated to the purpose (such as the media-types@iana.org
   for media types) or on a more general mailing list (such as that of a
   current or former IETF working group).  Such a mailing list provides a way for
   new registrations to be publicly reviewed prior to getting assigned,
   or gives advice to persons wanting help in understanding what a
   proper registration should contain.
        </t>
        <t>
   While discussion on a mailing list can provide valuable technical
   feedback, opinions may vary and discussions may continue for some
   time without clear resolution.  In addition, IANA cannot participate
   in all of these mailing lists and cannot determine if or when such
   discussions reach consensus.  Therefore, IANA relies on a "designated
   expert" for advice regarding the specific question of whether an
   assignment should be made.  The designated expert is an individual
   who is responsible for carrying out an appropriate evaluation and
   returning a recommendation to IANA.
        </t>
        <t>
   It should be noted that a key motivation for having designated
   experts is for the IETF to provide IANA with a subject matter expert
   to whom the evaluation process can be delegated.  IANA forwards
   requests for an assignment to the expert for evaluation, and the
   expert (after performing the evaluation) informs IANA as to whether
   or not to make the assignment or registration.
        </t>
        <t>
          It will often be useful to use a designated expert only some of the time,
          as a supplement to other processes.  For more discussion of that topic,
          see <xref target="multiple-policies"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="experts-role" title="The Role of the Designated Expert">
        <t>
   The designated expert is responsible for initiating and coordinating
   the appropriate review of an assignment request.  The review may be
   wide or narrow, depending on the situation and the judgment of the
   designated expert.  This may involve consultation with a set of
   technology experts, discussion on a public mailing list, consultation
   with a working group (or its mailing list if the working group has
   disbanded), etc.  Ideally, the designated expert follows specific
   review criteria as documented with the protocol that creates or uses
   the namespace.  See the IANA Considerations sections of <xref target="RFC3748"/>
   and <xref target="RFC3575"/> for examples that have been done for specific
   namespaces.
        </t>
        <t>
   Designated experts are expected to be able to defend their decisions
   to the IETF community, and the evaluation process is not intended to
   be secretive or bestow unquestioned power on the expert.  Experts are
   expected to apply applicable documented review or vetting procedures,
   or in the absence of documented criteria, follow generally accepted
   norms such as those in <xref target="expert-reviews"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
   <xref target="updating-registrations"/> discusses disputes and appeals in more detail.
        </t>
        <t>
   Designated experts are appointed by the IESG (normally upon
   recommendation by the relevant Area Director).  They are typically
   named at the time a document creating or updating a namespace is
   approved by the IESG, but as experts originally appointed may later
   become unavailable, the IESG will appoint replacements if necessary.
        </t>
        <t>
   For some registries, it has proven useful to have multiple designated
   experts.  Sometimes those experts work together in evaluating a
   request, while in other cases additional experts serve as backups.
   In cases of disagreement among those experts, it is the
   responsibility of those experts to make a single clear recommendation
   to IANA.  It is not appropriate for IANA to resolve disputes among
   experts.  In extreme situations, such as deadlock, the IESG may need
   to step in to resolve the problem.
        </t>
        <t>
   In registries where a pool of experts evaluates requests, the pool
   should have a single chair responsible for defining how requests are
   to be assigned to and reviewed by experts.  In some cases, the expert
   pool may consist of a primary and backups, with the backups involved
   only when the primary expert is unavailable.  In other cases, IANA
   might assign requests to individual members in sequential or
   approximate random order.  In the event that IANA finds itself having
   received conflicting advice from its experts, it is the
   responsibility of the pool's chair to resolve the issue and provide
   IANA with clear instructions.
        </t>
        <t>
   Since the designated experts are appointed by the IESG, they may be
   removed by the IESG.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="expert-reviews" title="Designated Expert Reviews">
        <t>
   In the years since RFC 2434 was published and has been put to
   use, experience has led to the following observations:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
        A designated expert must respond in a timely fashion, normally
        within a week for simple requests to a few weeks for more
        complex ones.  Unreasonable delays can cause significant
        problems for those needing assignments, such as when products
        need code points to ship.  This is not to say that all reviews
        can be completed under a firm deadline, but they must be
        started, and the requester and IANA should have some
        transparency into the process if an answer cannot be given
        quickly.
            </t>
            <t>
        If a designated expert does not respond to IANA's requests
        within a reasonable period of time, either with a response or
        with a reasonable explanation for the delay (some requests
        may be particularly complex), and if this is a recurring event,
        IANA must raise the issue with the IESG.  Because of the
        problems caused by delayed evaluations and assignments, the IESG
        should take appropriate actions to ensure that the expert
        understands and accepts his or her responsibilities, or appoint
        a new expert.
            </t>
            <t>
        The designated expert is not required to personally bear the
        burden of evaluating and deciding all requests, but acts as a
        shepherd for the request, enlisting the help of others as
        appropriate.  In the case that a request is denied, and
        rejecting the request is likely to be controversial, the expert
        should have the support of other subject matter experts.  That
        is, the expert must be able to defend a decision to the
        community as a whole.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
   When a designated expert is used, the documentation should give
   clear guidance to the designated expert, laying out criteria for
   performing an evaluation and reasons for rejecting a request.
   In the case where there are no specific documented criteria, the
   presumption should be that a code point should be granted unless
   there is a compelling reason to the contrary.  Possible reasons to
   deny a request include these:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
        Scarcity of code points, where the finite remaining code points
        should be prudently managed, or when a request for a large
        number of code points is made, when a single code point is the
        norm.
            </t>
            <t>
        Documentation is not of sufficient clarity to evaluate or ensure
        interoperability.
            </t>
            <t>
        The code point is needed for a protocol extension, but the
        extension is not consistent with the documented (or generally
        understood) architecture of the base protocol being extended,
        and would be harmful to the protocol if widely deployed.  It is
        not the intent that "inconsistencies" refer to minor differences
        "of a personal preference nature".  Instead, they refer to
        significant differences such as inconsistencies with the
        underlying security model, implying a change to the semantics of
        an existing message type or operation, requiring unwarranted
        changes in deployed systems (compared with alternate ways of
        achieving a similar result), etc.
            </t>
            <t>
        The extension would cause problems with existing deployed
        systems.
            </t>
            <t>
        The extension would conflict with one under active development
        by the IETF, and having both would harm rather than foster
        interoperability.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="expert-lifecycle" title="Expert Reviews and the Document Lifecycle">
        <t>
          Review by the designated expert is necessarily done at a particular point in time,
          and represents review of a particular version of the document.
          Deciding when the review should take place is a question of good judgment.
          And while re-reviews might be done when it's acknowledged that the documentation
          of the registered item has changed substantially, making sure that re-review
          happens requires attention and care.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is possible, through carelessness, accident, inattentiveness, or even
          willful disregard, that changes might be made after the designated expert's
          review and approval that would, if the document were re-reviewed, cause the expert
          not to approve the registration.  It is up to the IESG, with the token held by
          the responsible Area Director, to be alert to such situations and to
          recognize that such changes need to be checked.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="creating" title="Creating a Registry">
      <t>
   Creating a registry involves describing the namespaces to be created,
   an initial set of assignments (if appropriate), and guidelines on how
   future assignments are to be made.
      </t>
      <t>
   Once a registry has been created, IANA records assignments that have
   been made.  The following labels describe the status of an individual
   (or range) of assignments:

        <list style="empty"><t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
          <t hangText="Private Use:">
            Private use only (not assigned), as described in <xref target="policy-private"/>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Experimental:">
            Available for general experimental use as described in
            <xref target="RFC3692"/>.  IANA does not record specific
            assignments for any particular use.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Unassigned:">
            Not currently assigned, and available for assignment via documented procedures.
            While it's generally clear that any values that are not registered are unassigned
            and available for assignment, it is sometimes useful to explicitly specify that
            situation.
            Note that this is distinctly different from "Reserved".            
          </t>
          <t hangText="Reserved:">
            Not assigned and not available for assignment.
            Reserved values are held for special uses,
            such as to extend the namespace when it becomes exhausted.
            Note that this is distinctly different from "Unassigned".
          </t>
        </list></t></list>
      </t>

      <section anchor="well-known" title="Well-Known IANA Policy Definitions">
        <t>
   The following are some defined policies, most of which are in use
   today.  These cover a range of typical policies that have been used
   to describe the procedure for assigning new values in a namespace.
   It is not strictly required that documents use these terms; the
   actual requirement is that the instructions to IANA be clear and
   unambiguous.  However, use of these terms is strongly RECOMMENDED,
   because their meanings are widely understood.
   The terms are fully explained in the following subsections.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
     <list style="empty"><t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Private Use</t>
            <t>Experimental Use</t>
            <t>Hierarchical Allocation</t>
            <t>First Come First Served</t>
            <t>Expert Review</t>
            <t>Specification Required</t>
            <t>RFC Required</t>
            <t>IETF Review</t>
            <t>Standards Action</t>
            <t>IESG Approval</t>
          </list>
     </t></list>  
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>
        <t>
   It should be noted that it often makes sense to partition a namespace
   into multiple categories, with assignments within each category
   handled differently.
   Many protocols now partition
   namespaces into two or more parts, with one range reserved
   for Private or Experimental Use while other ranges are reserved for
   globally unique assignments assigned following some review process.
   Dividing a namespace into ranges makes it possible to have different
   policies in place for different ranges and different use cases.
        </t>
        <t>
          Similarly, it will often be useful to specify multiple policies in parallel,
          with each policy being used under different circumstances.
          For more discussion of that topic, see <xref target="multiple-policies"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
   Examples:
   <list>
     <t>LDAP <xref target="RFC4520"/></t>
     <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers <xref target="RFC5246"/>
        (as detailed in the subsections below)</t>
     <t>Pseudowire Edge to Edge Emulation (PWE3) <xref target="RFC4446"/></t>
   </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
        </t>

        <section anchor="policy-private" title="Policy: Private Use">
          <t>
            For private or local use only, with the type and
            purpose defined by the local site.  No attempt is made to
            prevent multiple sites from using the same value in
            different (and incompatible) ways.  There is no need for
            IANA to review such assignments (since IANA does not record
            them) and assignments are not generally useful for broad
            interoperability.  It is the responsibility of the sites
            making use of the Private Use range to ensure that no
            conflicts occur (within the intended scope of use).
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>Site-specific options in DHCP <xref target="RFC2939"/></t>
              <t>Fibre Channel Port Type Registry <xref target="RFC4044"/></t>
              <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers 224-255 <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-experimental" title="Policy: Experimental Use">
          <t>
            Similar to private or local use only, with the
            purpose being to facilitate experimentation.  See
            <xref target="RFC3692"/> for details.
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Example:
            <list>
              <t>Experimental Values in IPv4, IPv6, ICMPv4, ICMPv6,
                 UDP, and TCP Headers <xref target="RFC4727"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-hierarchical" title="Policy: Hierarchical Allocation">
          <t>
            Delegated managers can assign values
            provided they have been given control over that part of the
            namespace.  IANA controls the higher levels of the namespace
            according to one of the other policies.
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>DNS names</t>
              <t>Object Identifiers</t>
              <t>IP addresses</t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-fcfs" title="Policy: First Come First Served">
          <t>
            Assignments are made to anyone on a
            first come, first served basis.  There is no substantive
            review of the request, other than to ensure that it is
            well-formed and doesn't duplicate an existing assignment.
            However, requests must include a minimal amount of clerical
            information, such as a point of contact (including an email
            address) and a brief description of how the value will be
            used.  Additional information specific to the type of value
            requested may also need to be provided, as defined by the
            namespace.  For numbers, the exact value is generally
            assigned by IANA; with names, specific text strings can
            usually be requested.
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>SASL mechanism names <xref target="RFC4422"/></t>
              <t>LDAP Protocol Mechanisms and LDAP Syntax <xref target="RFC4520"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-expert" title="Policy: Expert Review">
          <t>
            (Sometimes also called "Designated Expert" in earlier editions of this document.)
            Review and approval by a designated expert is required.
            The required documentation and review
            criteria for use by the designated expert should be provided
            when defining the registry.  For example, see Sections 6 and
            7.2 in <xref target="RFC3748"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            It is particularly important, when using a designated expert, to give
            clear guidance to the expert, laying out criteria for
            performing an evaluation and reasons for rejecting a request.
            When specifying a policy that involves a designated expert, the
            IANA Considerations SHOULD contain such guidance.
            It is also a good idea to include, when possible, a sense of whether
            many registrations are expected over time, or if the registry is
            expected to be updated infrequently or in exceptional circumstances only.
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>EAP Method Types <xref target="RFC3748"/></t>
              <t>HTTP Digest AKA algorithm versions <xref target="RFC4169"/></t>
              <t>URI schemes <xref target="RFC4395"/></t>
              <t>GEOPRIV Location Types <xref target="RFC4589"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-specification" title="Policy: Specification Required">
          <t>
            Review and approval by a Designated Expert is required,
            (as in <xref target="policy-expert"/>)
            and the values and their meanings must be
            documented in a permanent and readily available public
            specification, in sufficient detail so that interoperability
            between independent implementations is possible.
            The Designated Expert will review the public specification and
            evaluate whether it is sufficiently clear to allow
            interoperable implementations.  The intention behind
            "permanent and readily available" is that a document can
            reasonably be expected to be findable and retrievable long
            after IANA assignment of the requested value.  Publication
            of an RFC is an ideal means of achieving this requirement,
            but Specification Required is intended to also cover the
            case of a document published outside of the RFC path.  For
            RFC publication, the normal RFC review process is expected
            to provide the necessary review for interoperability, though
            the designated expert may be a particularly well-qualified
            person to perform such a review.
          </t>
          <t>
            When specifying this policy, just use the term "Specification Required".
            Some specifications have chosen to refer to it as "Expert Review with
            Specification Required", and that only causes confusion.
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>Diffserv-aware TE Bandwidth Constraints Model Identifiers <xref target="RFC4124"/></t>
              <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers 64-223 <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
              <t>ROHC Profile Identifiers <xref target="RFC5795"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-rfc" title="Policy: RFC Required">
          <t>
            RFC publication suffices, as an IETF submission or in any other stream
            (currently an RFC Editor Independent Submission <xref target="RFC5742"/>
            or an RFC in the IRTF or IAB Stream).
            Unless otherwise specified, any type of RFC is sufficient
            (currently Standards Track, BCP, Informational, Experimental, Historic).
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-ietf" title="Policy: IETF Review">
          <t>
            (Formerly called "IETF Consensus" in the first edition of this document.)
            New values are assigned only through RFCs in the IETF Stream --
            those that have been shepherded through the IESG as AD-Sponsored or
            IETF working group Documents <xref target="RFC2026"/> <xref target="RFC5378"/>.
            The intention is that the document and proposed assignment will
            be reviewed by the IESG and appropriate IETF working groups (or
            experts, if suitable working groups no longer exist) to
            ensure that the proposed assignment will not negatively
            impact interoperability or otherwise extend IETF protocols
            in an inappropriate or damaging manner.
          </t>
          <t>
            To ensure adequate community review, such documents are
            shepherded through the IESG as AD-sponsored or working group
            documents with an IETF Last Call.
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>IPSECKEY Algorithm Types <xref target="RFC4025"/></t>
              <t>Accounting-Auth-Method AVP values in DIAMETER <xref target="RFC4005"/></t>
              <t>TLS Extension Types <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-standards" title="Policy: Standards Action">
          <t>
            Values are assigned only for Standards Track RFCs approved by the IESG.
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>BGP message types <xref target="RFC4271"/></t>
              <t>Mobile Node Identifier option types <xref target="RFC4283"/></t>
              <t>TLS ClientCertificateType Identifiers 0-63 <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
              <t>DCCP Packet Types <xref target="RFC4340"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="policy-iesg" title="Policy: IESG Approval">
          <t>
            New assignments may be approved by the IESG.
            Although there is no requirement that the request be
            documented in an RFC, the IESG has discretion to request
            documents or other supporting materials on a case-by-case
            basis.
          </t>
          <t>
            IESG Approval is not intended to be used often or as a
            "common case"; indeed, it has seldom been used in practice
            during the period RFC 2434 was in effect.  Rather, it is
            intended to be available in conjunction with other policies
            as a fall-back mechanism in the case where one of the other
            allowable approval mechanisms cannot be employed in a timely
            fashion or for some other compelling reason.  IESG Approval
            is not intended to circumvent the public review processes
            implied by other policies that could have been employed for
            a particular assignment.  IESG Approval would be
            appropriate, however, in cases where expediency is desired
            and there is strong consensus (such as from a working group)
            for making the assignment.
          </t>
          <t>
            The following guidelines are suggested for any evaluation
            under IESG Approval:
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>
              The IESG can (and should) reject a request if another path
              for registration is available that is more appropriate and
              there is no compelling reason not to use that path.
                </t>
                <t>
              Before approving a request, the community should be
              consulted, via a "call for comments" that provides as much
              information as is reasonably possible about the request.
                </t>
              </list>
          </t>
          <t>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
            Examples:
            <list>
              <t>IPv4 Multicast address assignments <xref target="RFC5771"/></t>
              <t>IPv4 IGMP Type and Code values <xref target="RFC3228"/></t>
              <t>Mobile IPv6 Mobility Header Type and Option values <xref target="RFC6275"/></t>
            </list>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="selecting-policy" title="Best Practice for Selecting an Appropriate Policy">
        <t>
          The definitions above from "First Come First Served" to "Standards Action"
          specify a range of policies in increasing order of strictness:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
            <t hangText="4. ">First Come First Served:<vspace/>
              No review, minimal documentation.</t>
            <t hangText="5. ">Expert Review:<vspace/>
              Expert review, sufficient documentation for review.</t>
            <t hangText="6. ">Specification Required:<vspace/>
              Expert review, significant, stable public documentation.</t>
            <t hangText="7. ">RFC Required:<vspace/>
              Any RFC publication, IETF or a non-IETF Stream.</t>
            <t hangText="8. ">IETF Review:<vspace/>
              RFC publication, IETF Stream only, but need not be Standards Track.</t>
            <t hangText="9. ">Standards Action:<vspace/>
              RFC publication, IETF Stream, Standards Track only.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          In considering which of those policies to apply, it's important to get
          the right balance of review and ease of registration.  In many cases, those
          needing to register items will not be IETF participants; requests often come
          from other standards organizations, from organizations not directly involved
          in standards, from ad-hoc community work (from an open-source project, for example),
          and so on.  We must not make registration policies and procedures unnecessarily
          difficult to navigate, unnecessarily costly (in terms of time and other resources),
          nor unnecessarily subject to denial.
        </t>
        <t>
          While it is sometimes necessary to restrict what gets registered (for limited
          resources such as bits in a byte or numbers within a relatively small range,
          or for items for which unsupported values can be damaging to protocol operation),
          in many cases having items registered is more important than putting restrictions
          on the registration.  A pattern of denial through overly strict review criteria,
          or because of excessive cost in time and effort to get through the process,
          discourages people from even attempting to register their items.
          And failure to have in-use items registered adversely affects the protocols
          in use on the Internet.
        </t>
        <t>
          In particular, because policies 7 through 9 require involvement of working groups,
          directorates, and/or communities of former working-group participants to be actively
          involved and to support the effort, requests frequently run into concerns that
          "it's not worth doing a Standards-Track RFC for something this trivial," when,
          in fact, that requirement was created by the working group in the first place,
          with its selection of a Standards Action policy for the registry.
          Indeed, publishing any RFC is costly, and a Standards Track RFC is especially so,
          requiring a great deal of community time for review and discussion,
          IETF-wide last call, involvement of the entire IESG as well as concentrated time
          and review from the sponsoring AD, review and action by IANA,
          and RFC-Editor processing.
        </t>
        <t>
          Working groups and other document developers should use care in selecting
          appropriate registration policies when their documents create registries.
          They should select the least strict policy that suits a registry's needs,
          and look for specific justification for policies stricter than
          Specification Required.
          Examples of situations that might merit RFC Required, IETF Review, or Standards Action
          include the following.
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Registries of limited resources, such as bits in a byte (or in two bytes, or four),
              or numbers in a limited range.  In these cases, allowing registrations that
              haven't been carefully reviewed and agreed by community consensus could too
              quickly deplete the allowable values.
            </t>
            <t>
              Registries for which thorough community review is necessary to avoid
              extending or modifying the protocol in ways that could be damaging.
              One example is in defining new command codes, as opposed to options
              that use existing command codes: the former might require a strict
              policy, where a more relaxed policy could be adequate for the latter.
              Another example is in defining things that change the semantics of
              existing operations.
            </t>
          </list>
          There will be other cases, as well, of course; much assessment and judgment is needed.
          And it will sometimes be the case that using multiple policies in combination is
          appropriate (see <xref target="multiple-policies"/>).
          It's not the intent here to put limits on the applicability
          of particular registration policies, but to recommend laxity, rather than strictness,
          in general, and to encourage document developers to think carefully about each registry
          before deciding on policies.
        </t>
        <t>
          The description in <xref target="policy-iesg"/> of "IESG Approval"
          suggests that the IESG "can (and should) reject a request if another path
          for registration is available that is more appropriate
          and there is no compelling reason not to use that path."
          The IESG should give similar
          consideration to any registration policy more stringent than Specification Required,
          asking for justification and ensuring that more relaxed policies have been considered,
          and the strict policy is the right one.
          This is a situation that will -- and should -- involve a substantive discussion
          between the IESG and the working group, chairs, document editors,
          and/or document shepherd.
          The important point, again, is not to relax the registration policy just to get the
          document through quickly, but to carefully choose the right policy for each registry.
        </t>
        <t>
          Accordingly, document developers need to anticipate this and
          document their considerations for selecting the specified policy.
          Ideally, they should include that in the document.
          At the least, it should be included in the shepherd
          writeup for the document, and in any case the document shepherd
          should ensure that the selected policies have been justified before
          sending the document to the IESG.
        </t>
        <t>
          When specifications are revised, registration policies should be reviewed in light
          of experience since the policies were set.
          It is also possible to produce a small document at any time, which
          "updates" the original specification and changes registration policies.
          In either case, a policy can be relaxed or made more strict, as appropriate
          to the actual situation.
        </t>
        <t>
          Once again, it cannot be stressed enough that this must not be a mechanical process,
          but one to which the document developers apply thought, consideration, assessment,
          and judgment in choosing the right policy for each registry.
        </t>
        <t>
          The recommendations in this section apply whether the well-defined policy names
          defined herein are used, or whether the document contains other policy definitions.
          The point, again, is not to limit registration policies, but to ensure that the
          policies selected are appropriate, and that proper consideration has been given to
          the level of strictness required by them.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="multiple-policies" title="Using Multiple Policies in Combination">
        <t>
          It is often desirable to allow registrations through the normal IETF process,
          and to also provide a mechanism for registration outside the process.
          Thus, a particular registry might want to use a policy such as "RFC Required" or
          "IETF Review" sometimes, with a designated expert checking a "Specification Required"
          policy at other times.  Such combinations are frequently appropriate, and are encouraged.
        </t>
        <t>
          The alternative to using a combination requires either that all requests come through
          RFCs or that requests in RFCs go through review by the designated expert, despite the
          review and consensus that RFCs represent.
        </t>
        <t>
          For example, if it is felt that IETF consensus will provide good review for a
          particular registry, but we expect frequent registrations from other SDOs and
          we do not want those other organizations always to be required
          to go through the IETF RFC process, we might put the following in the
          IANA Considerations section when we create the registry:
          <list style="empty"><t>
            IANA is asked to create the registry "Fruit Access Flags" as a sub-registry of
            "Fruit Parameters".  New registrations will be permitted through either the
            IETF Review policy or the Specification Required policy [BCP26].
            </t></list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Such combinations will commonly use one of {Standards Action, IETF Review,
          RFC Required} in combination with one of {Specification Required, Expert Review}.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="what-to-put" title="What to Put in Documents That Create a Registry">
        <t>
   The previous sections presented some issues that should be considered
   in formulating a policy for assigning values in namespaces.  It is
   the working group and/or document author's job to formulate an
   appropriate policy and specify it in the appropriate document.  In
   almost all cases, having an explicit "IANA Considerations" section is
   appropriate.  The following and later sections define what is needed
   for the different types of IANA actions.
        </t>
        <t>
   Documents that create a new namespace (or modify the definition of an
   existing space) and that expect IANA to play a role in maintaining
   that space (serving as a repository for registered values) MUST
   provide clear instructions on details of the namespace.  In
   particular, instructions MUST include:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
         The name of the registry (or sub-registry) being created and/or
         maintained.
         <vspace/>
         The name will appear on the IANA web page and will
         be referred to in future documents that need to allocate a
         value from the new space.  The full name (and abbreviation, if
         appropriate) should be provided.  It is highly desirable that
         the chosen name not be easily confusable with the name of
         another registry.
         When creating a sub-registry, the registry that it is a part of
         must be clearly identified using its exact name (look it up, to be sure).
         Providing a URL to precisely identify the registry is helpful.
         Such URLs will be removed from the RFC prior to final publication,
         but help to ensure that IANA will understand exactly what is being requested.
         For example, a document could contain something like this:
         <list style="empty"><t>
         [TO BE REMOVED: This registration should be made in the Foobar Operational Parameters
         registry, located at http://www.iana.org/assignments/foobar-registry]
         </t></list>
            </t>
            <t>
         What information must be provided as part of a request in order
         to assign a new value.
         This information may include the need
         to document relevant security considerations, if any.
            </t>
            <t>
         The review process that will apply to all future requests for a
         value from the namespace.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
         Note: When a designated expert is used, documents MUST NOT name
         the designated expert in the document itself; instead, any suggested names
         should be relayed to the appropriate Area Director at the time
         the document is sent to the IESG for approval.
         This is usually done in the document shepherd writeup.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
         If the request should also be reviewed on a specific public
         mailing list (such as the media-types@iana.org for media types),
         that mailing address should be specified.  Note, however, that
         when mailing lists are specified, the requirement for a
         designated expert MUST also be specified (see <xref target="experts"/>).
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
         If IANA is expected to make assignments without requiring an
         outside review, sufficient guidance MUST be provided so that
         the requests can be evaluated with minimal subjectivity.
            </t>
            <t>
         The size, format, and syntax of registry entries.  When
         creating a new name/number space, authors must describe any
         technical requirements on registry (and sub-registry) values
         (valid ranges for integers, length limitations on
         strings, etc.) as well as the exact format in which registry
         values should be displayed.  For number assignments, one should
         specify whether values are to be recorded in decimal,
         hexadecimal, or some other format.  For strings, the encoding
         format should be specified (ASCII, UTF8, etc.).  Authors
         should also clearly specify what fields to record in the
         registry.
            </t>
            <t>
         Initial assignments and reservations.  Clear instructions
         should be provided to identify any initial assignments or
         registrations.  In addition, any ranges that are to be reserved
         for "Private Use", "Reserved", "Unassigned", etc. should be
         clearly indicated.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
   When specifying the process for making future assignments, it is
   quite acceptable to pick one (or more) of the example policies listed
   in <xref target="well-known"/> and refer to it by name.  Indeed, this is the
   preferred mechanism in those cases where the sample policies provide
   the desired level of review.  It is also acceptable to cite one of
   the above policies and include additional guidelines for what kind of
   considerations should be taken into account by the review process.
   For example, RADIUS <xref target="RFC3575"/> specifies the use of a Designated
   Expert, but includes specific additional criteria the Designated
   Expert should follow.
        </t>
        <t>
   For example, a document could say something like this:
          <figure>
            <artwork>
    ---------------------------------------------------------------
    This document defines a new DHCP option, entitled "FooBar" (see
    Section y), assigned a value of TBD1 from the DHCP Option space
    [to be removed upon publication:
    http://www.iana.org/assignments/bootp-dhcp-parameters]
    [RFC2132] [RFC2939]:
                                   Data
          Tag     Name            Length      Meaning
          ----    ----            ------      -------
          TBD1    FooBar          N           FooBar server

    The FooBar option also defines an 8-bit FooType field, for which
    IANA is to create and maintain a new sub-registry entitled
    "FooType values" under the FooBar option.  Initial values for the
    DHCP FooBar FooType registry are given below; future assignments
    are to be made through Expert Review [BCP26].
    Assignments consist of a DHCP FooBar FooType name and its
    associated value.

          Value    DHCP FooBar FooType Name        Definition
          ----     ------------------------        ----------
          0        Reserved
          1        Frobnitz                        See Section y.1
          2        NitzFrob                        See Section y.2
          3-254    Unassigned
          255      Reserved
    ---------------------------------------------------------------
            </artwork>
          </figure>          
        </t>
        <t>
   For examples of documents that provide detailed guidance to IANA
   on the issue of assigning numbers, consult <xref target="RFC6195"/>, <xref target="RFC3575"/>,
   <xref target="RFC3968"/>, and <xref target="RFC4520"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="updating-existing" title="Updating IANA Guidelines for Existing Registries">
        <t>
   Updating the registration process for an already existing
   (previously created) namespace (whether created explicitly or
   implicitly) follows a process similar to that used when creating a
   new namespace.  That is, a document is produced that makes reference
   to the existing namespace and then provides detailed guidelines for
   handling assignments in each individual namespace.  Such documents
   are normally processed as Best Current Practices (BCPs)
   <xref target="RFC2026"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
   Example documents that updated the guidelines for managing (then)
   pre-existing registries include: <xref target="RFC6195"/>, <xref target="RFC3228"/>, and <xref target="RFC3575"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="existing" title="Registering New Values in an Existing Registry">
      <section anchor="put-in-existing" title="What to Put in Documents When Registering Values">
        <t>
   Often, documents request an assignment from an already existing
   namespace (one created by a previously published document).  In such
   cases:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
        Documents should clearly identify the namespace in which each
        value is to be registered.  If the registration goes into a
        sub-registry, the author should clearly describe where the
        assignment or registration should go.  It is helpful to use the
        *exact* namespace name as listed on the IANA web page
        (please look it up, and don't guess),
        and cite the RFC where the namespace is defined.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        Note 1: There is no need to mention what the assignment policy
        for new assignments is, as that should be clear from the
        references.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        Note 2: When referring to an existing registry, providing a URL
        to precisely identify the registry is helpful.  Such URLs,
        however, should usually be removed from the RFC prior to final
        publication, since IANA URLs are not guaranteed to be stable in
        the future.  In cases where it is important to include a URL in
        the document, IANA should concur on its inclusion.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
         For example, a document could contain something like this:
         <list style="empty"><t>
         [TO BE REMOVED: This registration should be made in the Foobar Operational Parameters
         registry, located at http://www.iana.org/assignments/foobar-registry]
         </t></list>
            </t>
            <t>
        Each value requested should be given a unique reference.  When
        the value is numeric, use the notation: TBD1, TBD2, etc.
        Throughout the document where an actual IANA-assigned value
        should be filled in, use the "TBDx" notation.  This helps ensure
        that the final RFC has the correct assigned values inserted in
        all of the relevant places where the value is expected to appear
        in the final document.  For values that are text strings, a
        specific name can be suggested.  IANA will normally assign the
        name, unless it conflicts with a name already in use.
            </t>
            <t>
        Normally, the values to be used are chosen by IANA and documents
        should specify values of "TBD".  However, in some cases, a value
        may have been used for testing or in early implementations.  In
        such cases, it is acceptable to include text suggesting what
        specific value should be used (together with the reason for the
        choice).  For example, one might include the text "the value XXX
        is suggested as it is used in implementations".  However, it
        should be noted that suggested values are just that; IANA will
        attempt to assign them, but may find that impossible, if the
        proposed number has already been assigned for some other use.

        For some registries, IANA has a long-standing policy prohibiting
        assignment of names or codes on a vanity or organization-name
        basis.  For example, codes are always assigned sequentially unless there
        is a strong reason for making an exception.  Nothing in this
        document is intended to change those policies or prevent their
        future application.
            </t>
            <t>
        The IANA Considerations section should summarize all of the IANA
        actions, with pointers to the relevant sections elsewhere in the
        document as appropriate.  When multiple values are requested, it
        is generally helpful to include a summary table.  It is also
        helpful for this table to be in the same format as it appears or will
        appear on the IANA web site.  For example:
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
            Value     Description          Reference
            --------  -------------------  ---------
            TBD1      Foobar               [[this RFC]]
            </artwork>
          </figure>          
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        Note: In cases where authors feel that including the full table is
        too verbose or repetitive, authors should still include the table in the draft,
        but may include a note asking that the table be removed prior to
        publication of the final RFC.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
   As an example, the following text could be used to request assignment
   of a DHCPv6 option number:
          <list>
            <t>
      IANA has assigned an option code value of TBD1 to the DNS
      Recursive Name Server option and an option code value of TBD2 to
      the Domain Search List option from the DHCP option code space
      defined in Section 24.3 of RFC 3315.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="updating-registrations" title="Updating Registrations">
        <t>
   Registrations are a request to assign a new value, including the
   related information needed to evaluate and document the request.
   Even after a number has been assigned, some types of registrations
   contain additional information that may need to be updated over time.
   For example, MIME media types, character sets, and language tags,
   etc. typically include more information than just the registered
   value itself.  Example information can include point-of-contact
   information, security issues, pointers to updates, literature
   references, etc.  In such cases, the document defining the namespace
   must clearly state who is responsible for maintaining and updating a
   registration.  In different cases, it may be appropriate to specify
   one or more of the following:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
        Let the author update the registration, subject to the same
        constraints and review as with new registrations.
            </t>
            <t>
        Allow some mechanism to attach comments to the registration, for
        cases where others have significant objections to claims in a
        registration, but the author does not agree to change the
        registration.
            </t>
            <t>
        Designate the IESG, a designated expert, or another entity as
        having the right to change the registrant associated with a
        registration and any requirements or conditions on doing so.
        This is mainly to get around the problem when a registrant
        cannot be reached in order to make necessary updates.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="overriding-procedures" title="Overriding Registration Procedures">
        <t>
   Since RFC 2434 was published, experience has shown that the
   documented IANA considerations for individual protocols do not always
   adequately cover the reality after the protocol is deployed.  For
   example, many older routing protocols do not have documented,
   detailed IANA considerations.  In addition, documented IANA
   considerations are sometimes found to be too stringent to allow even
   working group documents (for which there is strong consensus) to
   obtain code points from IANA in advance of actual RFC publication.
   In other cases, the documented procedures are unclear or neglected to
   cover all the cases.  In order to allow assignments in individual
   cases where there is strong IETF consensus that an allocation should
   go forward, but the documented procedures do not support such an
   assignment, the IESG is granted authority to approve assignments in
   such cases.  The intention is not to overrule properly documented
   procedures, or to obviate the need for protocols to properly document
   their IANA considerations.  Instead, the intention is to permit
   assignments in individual cases where it is obvious that the
   assignment should just be made, but updating the IANA process just to
   assign a particular code point is viewed as too heavy a burden.
        </t>
        <t>
   In general, the IETF would like to see deficient IANA registration
   procedures for a namespace revised through the IETF standards
   process, but not at the cost of unreasonable delay for needed
   assignments.  If the IESG has had to take the action in this section,
   it is a strong indicator that the IANA registration procedures should
   be updated, possibly in parallel with ongoing protocol work.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="referring" title="Documentation References in IANA Registries">
      <t>
        Usually, registries and registry entries include references to documentation (RFCs
        or other documents).  The purpose of these references is to provide pointers for
        implementors to find details necessary for implementation, NOT to simply note what
        document created the registry or entry.  Therefore:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            If a document registers an item that is defined and explained elsewhere, the
            registered reference should be to that document, and not to the document that
            is merely performing the registration.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the registered item is defined and explained in the current document,
            it is important to include sufficient information to enable implementors to
            understand the item and to create a proper implementation.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the registered item is explained primarily in a specific section of the
            reference document, it is useful to include a section reference.
            For example, "[RFC9876], Section 3.2", rather than just "[RFC9876]".
          </t>
          <t>
            For documentation of a new registry, the reference should provide information
            about the registry itself, not just a pointer to the creation of it.
            Useful information includes the purpose of the registry, a rationale for its
            creation, documentation of the process and policy for new registrations,
            guidelines for new registrants or designated experts, and other such
            related information.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="bis-docs" title='What to Do in "bis" Documents'>
      <t>
        We often produce a new edition of an RFC, which obsoletes the previous edition
        (we sometimes call these "bis" documents, such as when RFC 9876 is updated by
        draft-ietf-foo-rfc9876bis).  When the original document created registries and/or
        registered entries, there is a question of how to handle the IANA Considerations
        section in the "bis" document.
      </t>
      <t>
        If the registrations specify the original document as a reference, those registrations
        should be updated to point to the current (not obsolete) documentation for those
        items.  Usually, that will mean changing the reference to be the "bis" document.
      </t>
      <t>
        For example, suppose RFC 9876 registered the "BANANA" flag in the "Fruit Access Flags"
        registry, and the documentation for that flag is in Section 3.2.
        The current registry might look, in part, like this:
        <figure>
          <artwork>
   Name      Description          Reference
   --------  -------------------  ---------
   BANANA    Flag for bananas     [RFC9876], Section 3.2
          </artwork>
        </figure>          
        If draft-ietf-foo-rfc9876bis obsoletes RFC 9876 and, because of some rearrangement,
        now documents the flag in Section 4.1.2, the IANA Considerations of the bis document
        might contain text such as this:
        <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        <list style="empty"><t>
        IANA is asked to change the registration information for the BANANA flag
        in the "Fruit Access Flags" registry to the following:
        <figure>
          <artwork>
   Name      Description          Reference
   --------  -------------------  ---------
   BANANA    Flag for bananas     [[this RFC]], Section 4.2.1
          </artwork>
        </figure>          
        </t></list>
      </t>
      <t>
        In many cases, if there are a number of registered references to the original
        RFC and the document organization has not changed the registered section numbering much,
        it may simply be reasonable to do this:
        <list style="empty"><t>
        Because this document obsoletes RFC 9876,
        IANA is asked to change all registration information that references
        [RFC9876] to instead reference [[this RFC]].
        </t></list>
      </t>
      <t>
        If information for registered items has been or is being moved to other documents,
        then, of course, the registration information should be changed to point to those
        other documents.  In no case is it reasonable to leave documentation pointers
        to the obsoleted document for any registries or registered items that are still
        in current use.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="misc" title="Miscellaneous Issues">
      <section anchor="misc-no-actions" title="When There Are No IANA Actions">
        <t>
   Before an Internet-Draft can be published as an RFC, IANA needs to
   know what actions (if any) it needs to perform.  Experience has shown
   that it is not always immediately obvious whether a document has no
   IANA actions, without reviewing the document in some detail.  In
   order to make it clear to IANA that it has no actions to perform (and
   that the author has consciously made such a determination), such
   documents should include an IANA Considerations section that states:
          <list>
            <t>
      This document has no IANA actions.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
   This statement, or an equivalent, must only be inserted after the working group
   or individual submitter has carefully verified it to be true.  Using
   such wording as a matter of "boilerplate" or without careful
   consideration can lead to incomplete or incorrect IANA actions being
   performed.
        </t>
        <t>
   If a specification makes use of values from a namespace that is not
   managed by IANA, it may be useful to note this fact, with
   wording such as this:
          <list>
            <t>
      The values of the Foobar parameter are assigned by the Barfoo
      registry on behalf of the Rabfoo Forum.  Therefore, this document
      has no IANA actions.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
   In some cases, the absence of IANA-assigned values may be considered
   valuable information for future readers; in other cases, it may be
   considered of no value once the document has been approved, and may
   be removed before archival publication.  This choice should be made
   clear in the draft, for example, by including a sentence such as
          <list>
            <t>
      [RFC Editor: please remove this section prior to publication.]
            </t>
          </list>
   or
          <list>
            <t>
      [RFC Editor: please do not remove this section.]
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="lacking-guidance" title="Namespaces Lacking Documented Guidance">
        <t>
   For all existing RFCs that either explicitly or implicitly rely on
   IANA to evaluate assignments without specifying a precise evaluation
   policy, IANA (in consultation with the IESG) will continue to decide
   what policy is appropriate.  Changes to existing policies can always
   be initiated through the normal IETF consensus process.
        </t>
        <t>
   All future RFCs that either explicitly or implicitly rely on IANA to
   register or otherwise manage namespace assignments MUST provide
   guidelines for managing the namespace.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="after-fact" title="After-the-Fact Registrations">
        <t>
   Occasionally, IANA becomes aware that an unassigned value from a
   managed namespace is in use on the Internet or that an assigned value
   is being used for a different purpose than originally registered.
   IANA will not condone such misuse; procedures of the type
   described in this document MUST be applied to such cases.
   In the absence of specifications to the contrary, values may only be
   reassigned for a different purpose with the consent of the original
   assignee (when possible) and with due consideration of the impact of
   such a reassignment.  In cases of likely controversy, consultation
   with the IESG is advised.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="reclaiming" title="Reclaiming Assigned Values">
        <t>
   Reclaiming previously assigned values for reuse is tricky, because
   doing so can lead to interoperability problems with deployed systems
   still using the assigned values.  Moreover, it can be extremely
   difficult to determine the extent of deployment of systems making use
   of a particular value.  However, in cases where the namespace is
   running out of unassigned values and additional ones are needed, it
   may be desirable to attempt to reclaim unused values.  When
   reclaiming unused values, the following (at a minimum) should be
   considered:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
        Attempts should be made to contact the original party to which a
        value is assigned, to determine if the value was ever used, and
        if so, the extent of deployment.  (In some cases, products were
        never shipped or have long ceased being used.  In other cases,
        it may be known that a value was never actually used at all.)
            </t>
            <t>
        Reassignments should not normally be made without the
        concurrence of the original requester.  Reclamation under such
        conditions should only take place where there is strong evidence
        that a value is not widely used, and the need to reclaim the
        value outweighs the cost of a hostile reclamation.  In any case,
        IESG Approval is needed in this case.
            </t>
            <t>
        It may be appropriate to write up the proposed action and
        solicit comments from relevant user communities.  In some cases,
        it may be appropriate to write an RFC that goes through a formal
        IETF process (including IETF Last Call) as was done when DHCP
        reclaimed some of its "Private Use" options <xref target="RFC3942"/>.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="assignee" title="Contact Person vs Assignee or Owner">
        <t>
          Many registries include designation of a technical or administrative contact
          associated with each entry.  Often, this is recorded as contact information for
          an individual.  It is unclear, though, what role the individual has with respect
          to the registration: is this item registered on behalf of the individual,
          the company the individual worked for, or perhaps another organization the
          individual was acting for?
        </t>
        <t>
          This matters because some time later, when the individual has changed jobs or roles,
          and perhaps can no longer be contacted, someone might want to update the registration.
          IANA has no way to know what company, organization, or individual should be allowed
          to take the registration over.  For registrations rooted in RFCs, the stream owner
          (such as the IESG or the IAB) can make an overriding decision.  But in other cases,
          there is no recourse.
        </t>
        <t>
          Registries can include, in addition to a "Contact" field, an "Assignee"
          or "Owner" field that can be used to address this situation,
          giving IANA clear guidance as to the actual owner of the registration.
          Alternatively, organizations can put an organizational role into the "Contact"
          field in order to make their ownership clear.
        </t>
        <t>
        </t>
        <t>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="closing-obsoleting" title="Closing or Obsoleting a Registry">
        <t>
          <cref>This section needs to be resolved before publication.</cref>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="bcp78-79" title="BCP 78/79 Issues in Registries">
        <t>
          <cref>
            This section needs to be resolved before publication,
            but I'm not sure anything's needed here after all.
          </cref>
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="appeals" title="Appeals">
      <t>
   Appeals of registration decisions made by IANA can be made using the
   normal IETF appeals process as described in Section 6.5 of
   <xref target="RFC2026"/>.  Specifically, appeals should be directed to the
   IESG, followed (if necessary) by an appeal to the IAB, etc.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mailing-lists" title="Mailing Lists">
      <t>
   All IETF mailing lists associated with evaluating or discussing
   assignment requests as described in this document are subject to
   whatever rules of conduct and methods of list management are
   currently defined by Best Current Practices or by IESG decision.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
   Information that creates or updates a registration needs to be
   authenticated and authorized.  IANA updates registries according to
   instructions in published RFCs and from the IESG.  It also may accept
   clarifications from document authors, relevant working group chairs, Designated
   Experts, and mail list participants, too.
      </t>
      <t>
   Information concerning possible security vulnerabilities of a
   protocol may change over time.  Likewise, security vulnerabilities
   related to how an assigned number is used may change as well.
   As new vulnerabilities are discovered,
   information about such vulnerabilities may need to be attached to
   existing registrations, so that users are not misled as to the true
   security issues surrounding the use of a registered number.
      </t>
      <t>
   An analysis of security issues is generally required for all
   protocols that make use of parameters (data types, operation codes,
   keywords, etc.) used in IETF protocols or registered by IANA.  Such
   security considerations are usually included in the protocol document
   <xref target="RFC3552"/>.  It is the responsibility of the IANA considerations
   associated with a particular registry to specify what (if any)
   security considerations must be provided when assigning new values,
   and the process for reviewing such claims.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="to-do" title="To-Do List; resolve and remove before requesting publication">
      <t>
Just was speaking with someone at the IANA office hours.
I was looking through the 5226bis draft and there is nothing in there about how to deprecate values in registries.
Might be something good to add.
      </t>
      <t>
        
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="changes" title="Changes Relative to Earlier Editions of BCP 26">

      <section title="2012: Changes in This Document Relative to RFC 5226">
        <t>Significant additions:
          <list style="symbols">
        
            <t>Added <xref target="expert-lifecycle"/>, Expert Reviews and the Document Lifecycle</t>

            <t>Moved well-known policies into a separate section for each, subsections of <xref target="well-known"/>.</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="selecting-policy"/>, Best Practice for Selecting an Appropriate Policy.</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="multiple-policies"/>, Using Multiple Policies in Combination.</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="referring"/>, Documentation References in IANA Registries</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="bis-docs"/>, What to Do in "bis" Documents</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="assignee"/>, Contact Person vs Assignee or Owner</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="closing-obsoleting"/>, Closing or Obsoleting a Registry</t>

            <t>Added <xref target="bcp78-79"/>, BCP 78/79 Issues in Registries</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Clarifications and such:
          <list style="symbols">
          
            <t>Made clarifications about identification of IANA registries and use of URLs for them.</t>

            <t>Clarified the distinction between "Unassigned" and "Reserved".</t>

            <t>Made some clarifications in "Expert Review" about instructions to the designated expert.</t>

            <t>Made some clarifications in "Specification Required" about how to declare this policy.</t>
            
            <t>Assorted minor clarifications and editorial changes throughout.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="2008: Changes in RFC 5226 Relative to RFC 2434">
      <t>
   Changes include:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
        Major reordering of text to expand descriptions and to better
        group topics such as "updating registries" vs. "creating new
        registries", in order to make it easier for authors to find the
        text most applicable to their needs.
          </t>
          <t>
        Numerous editorial changes to improve readability.
          </t>
          <t>
        Changed the term "IETF Consensus" to "IETF Review" and added
        more clarifications.  History has shown that people see the
        words "IETF Consensus" (without consulting the actual
        definition) and are quick to make incorrect assumptions about
        what the term means in the context of IANA Considerations.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added "RFC Required" to list of defined policies.
          </t>
          <t>
        Much more explicit directions and examples of "what to put in
        RFCs".
          </t>
          <t>
        "Specification Required" now implies use of a Designated Expert
        to evaluate specs for sufficient clarity.
          </t>
          <t>
        Significantly changed the wording in the Designated Experts section.
        Main purpose is to make clear that Expert Reviewers are accountable to the
        community, and to provide some guidance for review criteria in
        the default case.
          </t>
          <t>
        Changed wording to remove any special appeals path.  The normal
        RFC 2026 appeals path is used.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added a section about reclaiming unused value.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added a section on after-the-fact registrations.
          </t>
          <t>
        Added a section indicating that mailing lists used to evaluate
        possible assignments (such as by a Designated Expert) are subject
        to normal IETF rules.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <section title="Acknowledgments for This Document (2012)">
        <t>
          Thomas Narten and Harald Tveit Alvestrand edited the two earlier editions
          of this document (RFCs 2434 and 5226), and Thomas continues his role in
          this third edition.  Most of the text from RFC 5226 remains in this edition.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgments from the second edition (2008)">
        <t>
   The original acknowledgments section in RFC 5226 was:
        </t>
        <t>
   This document has benefited from specific feedback from Jari Arkko,
   Marcelo Bagnulo Braun, Brian Carpenter, Michelle Cotton, Spencer
   Dawkins, Barbara Denny, Miguel Garcia, Paul Hoffman, Russ Housley,
   John Klensin, Allison Mankin, Blake Ramsdell, Mark Townsley, Magnus
   Westerlund, and Bert Wijnen.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgments from the first edition (1998)">
        <t>
   The original acknowledgments section in RFC 2434 was:
        </t>
        <t>
   Jon Postel and Joyce Reynolds provided a detailed explanation on what
   IANA needs in order to manage assignments efficiently, and patiently
   provided comments on multiple versions of this document.  Brian
   Carpenter provided helpful comments on earlier versions of the
   document.  One paragraph in the Security Considerations section was
   borrowed from <xref target="RFC4288"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119; <!-- keywords -->
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC0791;
      &RFC2026;
      &RFC2132;
      &RFC2860;
      &RFC2939;
      &RFC3228;
      &RFC3232;
      &RFC3552;
      &RFC3575;
      &RFC3692;
      &RFC3748;
      &RFC3942;
      &RFC3968;
      &RFC4005;
      &RFC4025;
      &RFC4044;
      &RFC4124;
      &RFC4169;
      &RFC4271;
      &RFC4283;
      &RFC4288;
      &RFC4301;
      &RFC4340;
      &RFC4395;
      &RFC4422;
      &RFC4446;
      &RFC4520;
      &RFC4589;
      &RFC4727;
      &RFC5246;
      &RFC5378;
      &RFC5742;
      &RFC5771;
      &RFC5795;
      &RFC6195;
      &RFC6275;
      &RFC6709;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
