<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-web-proxy-desc-00" category="std">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Web Proxy Description">The Web Proxy Description Format</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2014"/>

    <area>General</area>
    
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This specification defines a simple means of configuring Web proxies, and places additional
requirements upon them in order to promote improved interoperability, security, and error handling.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>Web proxies are configured in a variety of ways today, but existing approaches suffer from
security, usability and interoperability issues.</t>

<t>This specification defines:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>A simple format for describing a Web proxy (“WPD”; see <xref target="wpd"/>) to facilitate configuration, and
so that it can be represented to users in a consistent way, and</t>
  <t>A way to discover the proxy description using a well-known URL (<xref target="discover"/>), so that direct
configuration of a proxy is as simple as entering a hostname, and</t>
  <t>A set of additional requirements for proxies described in this fashion, as well as requirements
for User Agents connecting to them, designed to improve security, usability and interoperability.
See <xref target="wpd-proxy"/>.</t>
</list></t>

<t>It can be used in a variety of ways, but is designed to meet the following goals:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Users should always be aware of a configured proxy and be able to confidently identify it, and</t>
  <t>Configuring a proxy should be a deliberate act, but simple to do for non-technical users, and</t>
  <t>Proxies should always respect the wishes of the end user and Web site, and</t>
  <t>Proxies should never reduce or compromise the security of connections, and improve it where
possible, and</t>
  <t>The proxy should be able to reliably communicate with the end user regarding its policies and
problems that are encountered.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Furthermore, it is designed to be useful in the following cases:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>An end user wants to use a proxy network that provides improved performance, by re-compressing
responses to http:// resources.</t>
  <t>An end user wants to use a proxy network that provides improved privacy, by routing requests
through any number of intermediaries.</t>
  <t>An end user is required to use a proxy to access Internet resources by their network (e.g., a
school, workplace or prison).</t>
  <t>A network wants to offer enhanced access to selected Web sites, through interposition of a proxy.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Importantly, this specification does not address the automatic discovery of proxy configuration for
a given network, because proxy configuration is a security-sensitive action, and ought never be
done automatically.</t>

<t>It is expected that the mechanisms described could be implemented by a single program (e.g., a Web
browser), or through an Operating System facility.</t>

<section anchor="notational-conventions" title="Notational Conventions">

<t>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”, “SHOULD NOT”,
“RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and “OPTIONAL” in this document are to be interpreted as described in
<xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="wpd-proxy" title="WPD Proxies">

<t>This specification defines a particular kind of HTTP proxy (as per <xref target="RFC7230"/> Section 2.3) known
as a “WPD proxy” that has additional requirements placed upon it, as well as upon those using it.</t>

<t>WPD Proxies MUST support HTTP/2 <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2"/> over TLS for connections from clients.
Clients that cannot establish a HTTP/2 connection to a WPD proxy MUST consider that proxy “failed.”</t>

<t>WPD Proxies MUST support forwarding requests with the “http” scheme <xref target="RFC7230"/>, and SHOULD support
the CONNECT method, as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2"/> Section 8.3.</t>

<t><xref target="RFC7230"/> Section 5.7.2 requires proxies to honour the semantic of the “no-transform”
cache-control directive, and append the 214 (Transformation Applied) warn-code to other messages
that have been transformed; WPD proxies MUST honour these requirements.</t>

<t>When connecting to a WPD proxy, clients MUST use TLS and MUST validate the proxy hostname as per
<xref target="RFC2818"/> Section 3.1. If the proxy presents an invalid certificate, that proxy MUST be
considered “failed” and not used (until a valid certificate is presented).</t>

<t>User agents MUST use a CONNECT tunnel when retrieving URLs with the “https” scheme through WPD
proxies.</t>

<t>When user agents encounter 5xx responses to a CONNECT request from a WPD proxy, they MUST present
the response to the end user, but MUST NOT present or process it as a response to the eventual
request to be made through the tunnel (i.e., it has an unidentified payload, as per <xref target="RFC7231"/>
Section 3.1.4.1).</t>

<t>NOTE: Many user agents refuse to show an error response to a CONNECT to the user, in order to deal
with the issues brought to light by <xref target="bad-proxy"/>. While effective in dealing with those attacks,
doing so effectively disallows communication between the proxy and the end user; this requirement
is designed to force clients to re-open that channel.</t>

<t>If a WPD proxy becomes unresponsive, clients SHOULD consider it failed and attempt to use another
proxy (if available) or inform the end user (if not available). Clients SHOULD regularly attempt to
re-establish contact with failed WPD proxies (e.g., every minute).</t>

</section>
<section anchor="wpd" title="The Web Proxy Description (WPD) Format">

<t>WPD is a JSON <xref target="RFC7159"/> format that describes a Web proxy to its clients. Its root is an object
containing WPD-specific object members. For example:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
{
    "name": "ExampleCorp Web Proxy",
    "desc": "ExampleCorp's Proxy Gateway for Web access. Note that
             all traffic through this proxy is logged, and may be
             filtered for content."
    "moreInfo": "https://inside.example.com/proxy/",
    "proxies": [
        {
            "host": "proxy.example.com",
            "port": 8080,
            "clientNetworks": ["192.0.2.0/24"]
            },
        {
            "host": "proxy1.example.com",
            "port": 8080,
            "clientNetworks": ["192.0.2.0/24"]
        }
    ],
    "alwaysDirect": ["example.com", "192.0.2.0/24"],
	"failDirect": False
}
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>When configuring a proxy through WPD, the User agent SHOULD present the relevant information
contained within (i.e., the ‘name’, ‘desc’ and ‘moreInfo’ members, the latter as a link) to the end
user. User agents SHOULD also make this information available to the end user whenever the WPD is
in use.</t>

<t>The remainder of this section defines the content of these members. Unrecognized members SHOULD
be ignored.</t>

<section anchor="name" title="name">

<t>A string containing a short, memorable name for the proxy; typically 64 characters or less. This
member MUST be present.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="desc" title="desc">

<t>A string containing a textual description of the proxy’s function(s); typically 256 characters or
less. This member MUST be present.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="moreinfo" title="moreInfo">

<t>A string containing a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/> that leads to more information about the proxy, its
operation, who operates it, etc. The URI MUST have a scheme of “https” <xref target="RFC7230"/>, and MUST be
able to respond with an HTML <xref target="W3C.CR-html5-20140731"/> representation. This member MUST be present.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="proxies" title="proxies">

<t>An array containing one or more proxy objects; each proxy object represents a proxy endpoint that
can be used when this WPD is configured. See <xref target="wpd-proxy"/> for requirements specific to these
proxies, as well as those clients connecting to them.</t>

<t>Proxy objects’ members are defined by the following subsections; unrecognized members SHOULD be
ignored.</t>

<t>The ordering of proxy objects within the proxies array is not significant; clients MAY choose any
proxy they wish (keeping in mind the requirements of clientNetworks), and MAY use more than one at a
time.</t>

<t>NOTE: the array of proxy objects is functionally similar to, but not as expressive as, the
commonly-used “proxy.pac” format. While it would be expedient for WPD to just reference a
proxy.pac, feedback so far is that proxy.pac has a number of deficiencies, and interoperability
over it is poor. Therefore, this document specifies the proxy object instead, in order to gather
feedback on an alternative approach.</t>

<section anchor="host" title="host">

<t>A string containing the host (as per <xref target="RFC3986"/>, section 3.2.2) of the proxy. This member MUST be
present.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="port" title="port">

<t>A number representing the port that the proxy is listening on. This member MUST be present, and
MUST be an integer.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="clientnetworks" title="clientNetworks">

<t>An array containing strings; each string contains a classless prefix <xref target="RFC4632"/> which the proxy
can be used within. Clients MUST NOT attempt to use the proxy if their IP address is not within one
of the stated ranges.</t>

<t>This member is optional.</t>

<t>For example, if the value of clientNetworks is</t>

<t>[ “192.168.1.0/32”, “192.168.2.0/24” ]</t>

<t>then the only clients that could use the proxy would have IP addresses in the ranges 192.168.1.0 to
192.168.1.3 and 192.168.2.0 to 192.168.2.255.</t>

<t>Note that by their nature <xref target="RFC1918"/> private networks are not unique, and therefore there may be
false positives. As such, clients SHOULD NOT automatically configure a WPD based upon clientNetworks
when the IP address is in these ranges, although they MAY notify the user of a WPD’s possible
applicability, and MAY use additional information to correlate a WPD to its proper network.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="forreferers" title="forReferers">

<t>An array containing strings; each string is a host (as per <xref target="RFC3986"/> Section 3.2.2).</t>

<t>When forReferers is present, Clients MUST use the WPD’s proxies to access these hosts, hostnames
that have the host as a root, and for traffic generated by that content. They MUST NOT be used for
other traffic.</t>

<t>This member is optional.</t>

<t>For example, if the value of forReferers is</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
[ "friendface.example.com" ]
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>then requests to “friendface.example.com”, “www.friendface.example.com”,
“app.friendface.example.com” etc. would use the associated proxies; likewise, if processing a
response from one of these hosts generated further requests to “images.example.net” and
“scripts.example.org”, they would also use the proxies.</t>

<t>Note that alwaysDirect takes precedence over forReferers.</t>

<t>TODO: tighten up what “processing” means here; the intent is to omit a href</t>

</section>
<section anchor="alwaysdirect" title="alwaysDirect">

<t>An array containing strings; each string is one of:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>a host (as per <xref target="RFC3986"/> Section 3.2.2), </t>
  <t>a classless prefix <xref target="RFC4632"/>. </t>
  <t>the string “CONNECT”.</t>
</list></t>

<t>Clients MUST NOT use the WPD’s proxies to access nominated hosts and hostnames that have the a
nominated host as its root. Likewise, clients MUST NOT use the WPD’s proxies to access bare IP
addresses that fall within the classless prefix.</t>

<t>If the string “CONNECT” appears in alwaysDirect, it indicates that requests that require
establishment of a tunnel (e.g., for “https” URLs) MUST NOT use the WPD’s proxies, but instead
ought to be made directly to the origin (i.e., without a tunnel).</t>

<t>Note that when a “bare” IP address or classless prefix is used in alwaysDirect, clients are not
required to perform a reverse lookup on hostnames; these forms are only intended for accessing URLs
that use the IP-literal or IPv4address forms.</t>

<t>This member is optional.</t>

<t>For example, if the value of alwaysDirect is:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
[ "example.com", "192.168.5/24" ]
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>then requests to “example.com”, “www.example.com”, “foo.example.com” etc would not use any proxy.
Likewise, requests whose URL authority were bare IP addresses in the range 192.168.5.0 to
192.168.5.255 would not use any proxy.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="failDirect" title="failDirect">

<t>A boolean indicating whether the client should attempt to directly access the origin server if
all applicable proxies are unavailable.</t>

<t>When False, clients MUST NOT attempt to directly access the origin server when no proxy is
available, but instead SHOULD inform the user that the proxy is unavailable.</t>

<t>When True, clients MAY do so. If failDirect is not present, clients MAY default to this behavior.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="discover" title="Discovering WPD Files">

<t>To facilitate easy configuration of Web proxies, this specification defines a well-known URI
<xref target="RFC5785"/>. Doing so allows a proxy’s description to be found with a simple hostname; e.g.,
“proxy.example.net” or even just “example.net”.</t>

<t>Clients MUST NOT use the DHCP “WPAD” mechanism to discover WPDs.</t>

<section anchor="well-known" title="The web-proxy-desc well-known URI">

<t>The “web-proxy-desc” well-known URI allows discovery of a Web Proxy Description (<xref target="wpd"/>).</t>

<t>This well-known URI is only valid when used with the “https” URI Scheme <xref target="RFC7230"/>; it MUST NOT be
used with “http” URIs. In other words, WPD discovery is always protected by TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/>.</t>

<t>The description found at this location is considered valid for its freshness lifetime, as defined
in <xref target="RFC7234"/> Section 4.2. Once stale, clients SHOULD refresh it and apply any changes.</t>

<t>If the WPD is not retrievable (e.g., a 404 response status), invalid (as per JSON <xref target="RFC7159"/> or
the requirements in <xref target="wpd"/>), or its certificate is not valid for the host (as per <xref target="RFC2818"/>
Section 3.1), the client MUST NOT use the WPD, and if a user agent, SHOULD inform the end user.</t>

<t>The well-known URI MAY use proactive content negotiation (<xref target="RFC7231"/> Section 3.4.1) to select an
appropriate language for the response representation. Therefore, clients SHOULD send an
Accept-Language request header field (<xref target="RFC7231"/> Section 5.3.5) when they wish to advertise their
configured language.</t>

<t>The registration template is:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>URI suffix: web-proxy-desc</t>
  <t>Change controller: IETF</t>
  <t>Specification document(s): [this document]</t>
  <t>Related information: only to be used with ‘https’ scheme</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This specification registers a new well-known URI, as per <xref target="RFC5785"/>. See <xref target="well-known"/> for the
template.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>If a user can be convinced to configure a WPD hostname as their proxy, that host can observe all
unencrypted traffic by the client. As such, WPD configuration interfaces ought only allow
configuration of proxies once their identity is validate (as required), and the user ought to be
given access to all relevant information about the WPD proxy (i.e., ‘name’, ‘desc’ and ‘moreInfo’,
the latter as a link). Furthermore, WPD proxies ought only be configured as the result of an
intentional act, not as a side effect of normal Web browsing.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>Thanks to Patrick McManus for his feedback and suggestions.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>





<reference anchor='RFC1918'>

<front>
<title>Address Allocation for Private Internets</title>
<author initials='Y.' surname='Rekhter' fullname='Yakov Rekhter'>
<organization>Cisco systems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95134-1706</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 914 528 0090</phone>
<facsimile>+1 408 526 4952</facsimile>
<email>yakov@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Moskowitz' fullname='Robert G. Moskowitz'>
<organization>Chrysler Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>25999 Lawrence Ave</street>
<city>Center Line</city>
<region>MI</region>
<code>48015</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 810 758 8212</phone>
<facsimile>+1 810 758 8173</facsimile>
<email>rgm3@is.chrysler.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Karrenberg' fullname='Daniel Karrenberg'>
<organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Kruislaan 409</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<region />
<code>1098 SJ</code>
<country>NL</country></postal>
<phone>+31 20 5925065</phone>
<facsimile>+31 20 5925090</facsimile>
<email>Daniel.Karrenberg@ripe.net</email></address></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Groot' fullname='Geert Jan de Groot'>
<organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Kruislaan 409</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<region />
<code>1098 SJ</code>
<country>NL</country></postal>
<phone>+31 20 5925065</phone>
<facsimile>+31 20 5925090</facsimile>
<email>GeertJan.deGroot@ripe.net</email></address></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Lear' fullname='Eliot Lear'>
<organization>Silicon Graphics, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2011 N. Shoreline Blvd.</street>
<street>Mail Stop 15-730</street>
<city>Mountain View</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94043-1389</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 415 960 1980</phone>
<facsimile>+1 415 961 9584</facsimile>
<email>lear@sgi.com</email></address></author>
<date year='1996' month='February' /></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='5' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1918' />
<format type='TXT' octets='22270' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1918.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC2119'>

<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17970' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC2818'>

<front>
<title>HTTP Over TLS</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2000' month='May' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo describes how to use Transport Layer Security (TLS) to secure Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) connections over the Internet.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2818' />
<format type='TXT' octets='15170' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2818.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC3986'>

<front>
<title abbrev='URI Generic Syntax'>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
<organization abbrev='W3C/MIT'>World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
<street>77 Massachusetts Avenue</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02139</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-617-253-5702</phone>
<facsimile>+1-617-258-5999</facsimile>
<email>timbl@w3.org</email>
<uri>http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/</uri></address></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
<organization abbrev='Day Software'>Day Software</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>5251 California Ave., Suite 110</street>
<city>Irvine</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>92617</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-949-679-2960</phone>
<facsimile>+1-949-679-2972</facsimile>
<email>fielding@gbiv.com</email>
<uri>http://roy.gbiv.com/</uri></address></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
<organization abbrev='Adobe Systems'>Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>345 Park Ave</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95110</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-408-536-3024</phone>
<email>LMM@acm.org</email>
<uri>http://larry.masinter.net/</uri></address></author>
<date year='2005' month='January' />
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>uniform resource identifier</keyword>
<keyword>URI</keyword>
<keyword>URL</keyword>
<keyword>URN</keyword>
<keyword>WWW</keyword>
<keyword>resource</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters
that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification
defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references
that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security
considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.
The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs,
allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI
reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every
possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative
grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual
specifications of each URI scheme.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='66' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986' />
<format type='TXT' octets='141811' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3986.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='214067' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='163534' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc3986.xml' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC4632'>

<front>
<title>Classless Inter-domain Routing (CIDR): The Internet Address Assignment and Aggregation Plan</title>
<author initials='V.' surname='Fuller' fullname='V. Fuller'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Li' fullname='T. Li'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='August' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo discusses the strategy for address assignment of the existing 32-bit IPv4 address space with a view toward conserving the address space and limiting the growth rate of global routing state.  This document obsoletes the original Classless Inter-domain Routing (CIDR) spec in RFC 1519, with changes made both to clarify the concepts it introduced and, after more than twelve years, to update the Internet community on the results of deploying the technology described.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='122' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4632' />
<format type='TXT' octets='66944' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4632.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC7159'>

<front>
<title>The JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) Data Interchange Format</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Bray' fullname='T. Bray'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='March' />
<abstract>
<t>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) is a lightweight, text-based, language-independent data interchange format. It was derived from the ECMAScript Programming Language Standard. JSON defines a small set of formatting rules for the portable representation of structured data.&lt;/t>&lt;t> This document removes inconsistencies with other specifications of JSON, repairs specification errors, and offers experience-based interoperability guidance.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7159' />
<format type='TXT' octets='27451' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7159.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC7230'>

<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Message Syntax and Routing</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Reschke' fullname='J. Reschke'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='June' />
<abstract>
<t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless application-level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems.  This document provides an overview of HTTP architecture and its associated terminology, defines the "http" and "https" Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes, defines the HTTP/1.1 message syntax and parsing requirements, and describes related security concerns for implementations.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7230' />
<format type='TXT' octets='205947' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7230.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC7234'>

<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Caching</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Nottingham' fullname='M. Nottingham'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Reschke' fullname='J. Reschke'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='June' />
<abstract>
<t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless \%application- level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems.  This document defines HTTP caches and the associated header fields that control cache behavior or indicate cacheable response messages.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7234' />
<format type='TXT' octets='90647' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7234.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-httpbis-http2'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol version 2</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Belshe' fullname='Mike Belshe'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='R' surname='Peon' fullname='Roberto Peon'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Thomson' fullname='Martin Thomson'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='30' year='2014' />

<abstract><t>This specification describes an optimized expression of the syntax of the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP).  HTTP/2 enables a more efficient use of network resources and a reduced perception of latency by introducing header field compression and allowing multiple concurrent messages on the same connection.  It also introduces unsolicited push of representations from servers to clients.  This specification is an alternative to, but does not obsolete, the HTTP/1.1 message syntax.  HTTP's existing semantics remain unchanged.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-14' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-httpbis-http2-14.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='W3C.CR-html5-20140731'
           target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2014/CR-html5-20140731'>
<front>
<title>HTML5</title>

<author initials='R.' surname='Berjon' fullname='Robin Berjon'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S.' surname='Faulkner' fullname='Steve Faulkner'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='T.' surname='Leithead' fullname='Travis Leithead'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='E.' surname='Navara' fullname='Erika Doyle Navara'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='E.' surname='O&amp;#039;Connor' fullname='Edward O&amp;#039;Connor'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='S.' surname='Pfeiffer' fullname='Silvia Pfeiffer'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='31' year='2014' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium CR' value='CR-html5-20140731' />
<format type='HTML' target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2014/CR-html5-20140731' />
</reference>




    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>





<reference anchor='RFC5246'>

<front>
<title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Dierks' fullname='T. Dierks'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='August' />
<abstract>
<t>This document specifies Version 1.2 of the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol.  The TLS protocol provides communications security over the Internet.  The protocol allows client/server applications to communicate in a way that is designed to prevent eavesdropping, tampering, or message forgery. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5246' />
<format type='TXT' octets='222395' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5246.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC5785'>

<front>
<title>Defining Well-Known Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs)</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Nottingham' fullname='M. Nottingham'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Hammer-Lahav' fullname='E. Hammer-Lahav'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='April' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo defines a path prefix for "well-known locations", "/.well-known/", in selected Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5785' />
<format type='TXT' octets='13779' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5785.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC7231'>

<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Semantics and Content</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Reschke' fullname='J. Reschke'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='June' />
<abstract>
<t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless \%application- level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypertext information systems.  This document defines the semantics of HTTP/1.1 messages, as expressed by request methods, request header fields, response status codes, and response header fields, along with the payload of messages (metadata and body content) and mechanisms for content negotiation.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7231' />
<format type='TXT' octets='235053' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc7231.txt' />
</reference>


<reference anchor="bad-proxy" target="research.microsoft.com/jump/79323">
  <front>
    <title>Pretty-Bad-Proxy: An Overlooked Adversary in Browsers’ HTTPS Deployments</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Chen" fullname="Shuo Chen">
      <organization>Microsoft Research</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="Z." surname="Mao" fullname="Ziqing Mao">
      <organization>Purdue University</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Wang" fullname="Yi-Min Wang">
      <organization>Microsoft Research</organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Zhang" fullname="Ming Zhang">
      <organization>Microsoft Research</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2009" month="January"/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>


<section anchor="user-experience-for-wpds" title="User Experience for WPDs">

<t>There are a variety of ways to present proxy configuration to users and administrators, so this
specification does not constrain how this is done. That said, guidance for the common case (visual
Web browsers) can be helpful in assuring consistent user experience.</t>

<t>One of the core principles of this specification is that WPDs need to be explicitly configured,
either by the end user or an administrator on their behalf. This is because using a proxy is a
security-sensitive operation; if an attacker can automatically configure a proxy, or convince a
user to do so as part of accessing a site, they can gain access to the user’s traffic, even when
the user leaves the attacking network.</t>

<t>Likewise, only a single WPD ought be configured at a time; combining WPDs leads both to ambiguity
(which has precedence?) and user confusion.</t>

<t>When a WPD is active, its ought be visible to the end user, to remind them of its presence, and to
offer more information about the configured proxy.</t>

</section>


  </back>
</rfc>

