<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.30 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../Tools/rfcbootstrap/rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-5785bis-00" category="std">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Defining Well-Known URIs">Defining Well-Known Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs)</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>
        <uri>https://www.mnot.net/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017"/>

    <area>General</area>
    
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This memo defines a path prefix for “well-known locations”, “/.well-known/”, in selected Uniform
Resource Identifier (URI) schemes.</t>



    </abstract>


    <note title="Note to Readers">


<t><spanx style="emph">RFC EDITOR: please remove this section before publication</spanx></t>

<t>The issues list for this draft can be found at <eref target="https://github.com/mnot/I-D/labels/5785bis">https://github.com/mnot/I-D/labels/5785bis</eref>.</t>

<t>The most recent (often, unpublished) draft is at <eref target="https://mnot.github.io/I-D/5785bis/">https://mnot.github.io/I-D/5785bis/</eref>.</t>

<t>Recent changes are listed at <eref target="https://github.com/mnot/I-D/commits/gh-pages/5785bis">https://github.com/mnot/I-D/commits/gh-pages/5785bis</eref>.</t>

<t>See also the draft’s current status in the IETF datatracker, at
<eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-nottingham-5785bis/">https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-nottingham-5785bis/</eref>.</t>


    </note>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>It is increasingly common for Web-based protocols to require the discovery of policy or other
information about a host (“site-wide metadata”) before making a request. For example, the Robots
Exclusion Protocol <eref target="http://www.robotstxt.org/">http://www.robotstxt.org/</eref> specifies a way for automated processes to obtain
permission to access resources; likewise, the Platform for Privacy Preferences
<xref target="W3C.REC-P3P-20020416"/> tells user-agents how to discover privacy policy beforehand.</t>

<t>While there are several ways to access per-resource metadata (e.g., HTTP headers, WebDAV’s PROPFIND
<xref target="RFC4918"/>), the perceived overhead (either in terms of client-perceived latency and/or
deployment difficulties) associated with them often precludes their use in these scenarios.</t>

<t>When this happens, it is common to designate a “well-known location” for such data, so that it can
be easily located. However, this approach has the drawback of risking collisions, both with other
such designated “well-known locations” and with pre-existing resources.</t>

<t>To address this, this memo defines a path prefix in HTTP(S) URIs for these “well-known locations”,
“/.well-known/”. Future specifications that need to define a resource for such site-wide metadata
can register their use to avoid collisions and minimise impingement upon sites’ URI space.</t>

<section anchor="appropriate-use-of-well-known-uris" title="Appropriate Use of Well-Known URIs">

<t>There are a number of possible ways that applications could use Well- known URIs. However, in
keeping with the Architecture of the World- Wide Web [W3C.REC-webarch-20041215], well-known URIs
are not intended for general information retrieval or establishment of large URI namespaces on the
Web. Rather, they are designed to facilitate discovery of information on a site when it isn’t
practical to use other mechanisms; for example, when discovering policy that needs to be evaluated
before a resource is accessed, or when using multiple round-trips is judged detrimental to
performance.</t>

<t>As such, the well-known URI space was created with the expectation that it will be used to make
site-wide policy information and other metadata available directly (if sufficiently concise), or
provide references to other URIs that provide such metadata.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="notational-conventions" title="Notational Conventions">

<t>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”, “SHOULD NOT”,
“RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and “OPTIONAL” in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC
2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="well-known-uris" title="Well-Known URIs">

<t>A well-known URI is a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/> whose path component begins with the characters
“/.well-known/”, and whose scheme is “HTTP”, “HTTPS”, or another scheme that has explicitly been
specified to use well- known URIs.</t>

<t>Applications that wish to mint new well-known URIs MUST register them, following the procedures in
Section 5.1.</t>

<t>For example, if an application registers the name ‘example’, the corresponding well-known URI on
‘http://www.example.com/’ would be ‘http://www.example.com/.well-known/example’.</t>

<t>Registered names MUST conform to the segment-nz production in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

<t>Note that this specification defines neither how to determine the authority to use for a particular
context, nor the scope of the metadata discovered by dereferencing the well-known URI; both should
be defined by the application itself.</t>

<t>Typically, a registration will reference a specification that defines the format and associated
media type to be obtained by dereferencing the well-known URI.</t>

<t>It MAY also contain additional information, such as the syntax of additional path components, query
strings and/or fragment identifiers to be appended to the well-known URI, or protocol-specific
details (e.g., HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/> method handling).</t>

<t>Note that this specification does not define a format or media-type for the resource located at
“/.well-known/” and clients should not expect a resource to exist at that location.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>This memo does not specify the scope of applicability of metadata or policy obtained from a
well-known URI, and does not specify how to discover a well-known URI for a particular application.
Individual applications using this mechanism must define both aspects.</t>

<t>Applications minting new well-known URIs, as well as administrators deploying them, will need to
consider several security-related issues, including (but not limited to) exposure of sensitive
data, denial-of-service attacks (in addition to normal load issues), server and client
authentication, vulnerability to DNS rebinding attacks, and attacks where limited access to a
server grants the ability to affect how well-known URIs are served.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<section anchor="the-well-known-uri-registry" title="The Well-Known URI Registry">

<t>This document establishes the well-known URI registry.</t>

<t>Well-known URIs are registered on the advice of one or more Designated Experts (appointed by the
IESG or their delegate), with a Specification Required (using terminology from <xref target="RFC5226"/>).
However, to allow for the allocation of values prior to publication, the Designated Expert(s) may
approve registration once they are satisfied that such a specification will be published.</t>

<t>Registration requests should be sent to the wellknown-uri-review@ietf.org mailing list for review
and comment, with an appropriate subject (e.g., “Request for well-known URI: example”).</t>

<t>Before a period of 14 days has passed, the Designated Expert(s) will either approve or deny the
registration request, communicating this decision both to the review list and to IANA. Denials
should include an explanation and, if applicable, suggestions as to how to make the</t>

<t>request successful. Registration requests that are undetermined for a period longer than 21 days
can be brought to the IESG’s attention (using the iesg@iesg.org mailing list) for resolution.</t>

<section anchor="registration-template" title="Registration Template">

<t>URI suffix:  The name requested for the well-known URI, relative to
      “/.well-known/”; e.g., “example”.</t>

<t>Change controller:  For Standards-Track RFCs, state “IETF”.  For
      others, give the name of the responsible party.  Other details
      (e.g., postal address, e-mail address, home page URI) may also be
      included.</t>

<t>Specification document(s):  Reference to the document that specifies
      the field, preferably including a URI that can be used to retrieve
      a copy of the document.  An indication of the relevant sections
      may also be included, but is not required.</t>

<t>Related information:  Optionally, citations to additional documents
      containing further relevant information.</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>





<reference  anchor='RFC2119' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119'>
<front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'><organization /></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<abstract><t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2119'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC3986' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3986'>
<front>
<title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='T. Berners-Lee'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'><organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='L. Masinter'><organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='January' />
<abstract><t>A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.  The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='66'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3986'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC5226' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5226'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'><organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='H. Alvestrand'><organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='May' />
<abstract><t>Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of constants and other well-known values.  Even after a protocol has been defined and deployment has begun, new values may need to be assigned (e.g., for a new option type in DHCP, or a new encryption or authentication transform for IPsec).  To ensure that such quantities have consistent values and interpretations across all implementations, their assignment must be administered by a central authority.  For IETF protocols, that role is provided by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).</t><t>In order for IANA to manage a given namespace prudently, it needs guidelines describing the conditions under which new values can be assigned or when modifications to existing values can be made.  If IANA is expected to play a role in the management of a namespace, IANA must be given clear and concise instructions describing that role.  This document discusses issues that should be considered in formulating a policy for assigning values to a namespace and provides guidelines for authors on the specific text that must be included in documents that place demands on IANA.</t><t>This document obsoletes RFC 2434.  This document specifies an Internet Best  Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and  suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5226'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5226'/>
</reference>




    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>





<reference anchor='W3C.REC-P3P-20020416'
           target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/REC-P3P-20020416'>
<front>
<title>The Platform for Privacy Preferences 1.0 (P3P1.0) Specification</title>

<author initials='M.' surname='Marchiori' fullname='Massimo Marchiori'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='16' year='2002' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation' value='REC-P3P-20020416' />
<format type='HTML' target='http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/REC-P3P-20020416' />
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC4918' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4918'>
<front>
<title>HTTP Extensions for Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WebDAV)</title>
<author initials='L.' surname='Dusseault' fullname='L. Dusseault' role='editor'><organization /></author>
<date year='2007' month='June' />
<abstract><t>Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WebDAV) consists of a set of methods, headers, and content-types ancillary to HTTP/1.1 for the management of resource properties, creation and management of resource collections, URL namespace manipulation, and resource locking (collision avoidance).</t><t>RFC 2518 was published in February 1999, and this specification obsoletes RFC 2518 with minor revisions mostly due to interoperability experience.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4918'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC4918'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC2616' target='https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2616'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Gettys' fullname='J. Gettys'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Mogul' fullname='J. Mogul'><organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Frystyk' fullname='H. Frystyk'><organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='L. Masinter'><organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Leach' fullname='P. Leach'><organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='T. Berners-Lee'><organization /></author>
<date year='1999' month='June' />
<abstract><t>HTTP has been in use by the World-Wide Web global information initiative since 1990. This specification defines the protocol referred to as &quot;HTTP/1.1&quot;, and is an update to RFC 2068.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2616'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC2616'/>
</reference>




    </references>


<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>We would like to acknowledge the contributions of everyone who provided feedback and use cases for
this document; in particular, Phil Archer, Dirk Balfanz, Adam Barth, Tim Bray, Brian Eaton, Brad
Fitzpatrick, Joe Gregorio, Paul Hoffman, Barry Leiba, Ashok Malhotra, Breno de Medeiros, John
Panzer, and Drummond Reed. However, they are not responsible for errors and omissions.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="frequently-asked-questions" title="Frequently Asked Questions">

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>Aren’t well-known locations bad for the Web?</t>
</list></t>

<t>They are, but for various reasons – both technical and social – they are commonly used and
  their use is increasing. This memo defines a “sandbox” for them, to reduce the risks of collision
  and to minimise the impact upon pre-existing URIs on sites.</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>Why /.well-known?</t>
</list></t>

<t>It’s short, descriptive, and according to search indices, not widely used.</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>What impact does this have on existing mechanisms, such as P3P and
  robots.txt?</t>
</list></t>

<t>None, until they choose to use this mechanism.</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>Why aren’t per-directory well-known locations defined?</t>
</list></t>

<t>Allowing every URI path segment to have a well-known location (e.g., “/images/.well-known/”)
  would increase the risks of colliding with a pre-existing URI on a site, and generally these
  solutions are found not to scale well, because they’re too “chatty”.</t>

</section>


  </back>
</rfc>

