<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
   <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc2616 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc3986 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc4288 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4288.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc4627 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4627.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5789 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5789.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5988 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc6570 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6570.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY httpbis-semenatics SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-httpbis-p2-semantics-19.xml'>
   <!ENTITY httpbis-conditional SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-httpbis-p4-conditional-19.xml'>
   <!ENTITY httpbis-range SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-httpbis-p5-range-19.xml'>
   <!ENTITY prefer SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-snell-http-prefer-12.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-json-home-01" category="info">

	<front>
		<title>Home Documents for HTTP APIs</title>
		<author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
			<organization>Rackspace</organization>
			<address>       
				<email>mnot@mnot.net</email> 
				<uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date year="2012"/>
		<abstract>

			<t>This document proposes a "home document" format for non-browser
         HTTP clients.</t>

		</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>

		<section title="Introduction">

         <t>There is an emerging preference for non-browser Web applications
         (colloquially, "HTTP APIs") to use a link-driven approach to their
         interactions to assure loose coupling, thereby enabling extensibility
         and API evolution.</t>

         <t>This is based upon experience with previous APIs that specified
         static URI paths (such as
         "http://api.example.com/v1.0/widgets/abc123/properties") have
         resulted in brittle, tight coupling between clients and servers. </t>

         <t>Sometimes, these APIs were documented by a document format like
         <eref target="http://www.w3.org/Submission/wadl/">WADL</eref> that is
         used as a design time description; i.e., the URIs and other
         information they describe are "baked into" client
         implementations.</t>

         <t>In contrast, a "follow your nose" API advertises the resources
         available to clients using link relations <xref target="RFC5988"/>
         and the formats they support using internet media types <xref
         target="RFC4288"/>. A client can then decide – at run time – which
         resources to interact with based upon its capabilities (as described
         by link relations), and the server can safely add new resources and
         formats without disturbing clients that are not yet aware of
         them.</t>

         <t>As such, the client needs to be able to discover this information
         quickly and efficiently use it to interact with the server. Just as
         with a human-targeted home page for a site, we can create a "home
         document" for a HTTP API that describes it to non-browser
         clients.</t>

         <t>Of course, an HTTP API might use any format to do so; however,
         there are advantages to having a standard home document format. This
         specification suggests one for consideration, using the JSON
         format <xref target="RFC4627"/>.</t>

		</section>

		<section title="Requirements">
		   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
		   NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
		   this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
		   target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
		</section>


      <section anchor="json-home-documents" title="JSON Home Documents">

         <t>A JSON Home Document uses the format described in <xref
         target="RFC4627"/> and has the media type
         "application/json-home".</t>

         <t>Its content consists of a root object with a "resources" property,
         whose names are link relation types (as defined by <xref
         target="RFC5988"/>), and values are Resource Objects, defined
         below.</t>

         <t>For example:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
GET / HTTP/1.1
Host: example.org
Accept: application/json-home

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/json-home
Cache-Control: max-age=3600
Connection: close

{
  "resources": {
    "http://example.org/rel/widgets": {
      "href": "/widgets/"
    },
    "http://example.org/rel/widget": {
      "href-template": "/widgets/{widget_id}",
      "href-vars": {
        "widget_id": "http://example.org/param/widget"
      },
      "hints": {
        "allow": ["GET", "PUT", "DELETE", "PATCH"],
        "representations": ["application/json"],
        "accept-patch": ["application/json-patch"],
        "accept-post": ["application/xml"],
        "accept-ranges": ["bytes"]
      }
    }      
  }
}
]]></artwork></figure>

         <t>Here, we have a home document that links to a resource,
         "/widgets/" with the relation "http://example.org/rel/widgets". It
         also links to an undefined number of resources with the relation type
         "http://example.org/rel/widget" using a URI Template <xref
         target="RFC6570"/>, along with a mapping of several identifiers to
         specific variables for use in that template.</t>
         
         <t>It also gives several hints about interacting with the latter
         "widget" resources, including the HTTP methods usable with them, the
         patch formats they accept, and the fact that they support partial
         requests <xref target="RFC2616"/> using the "bytes"
         range-specifier.</t>
         
         <t>It gives no such hints about the "widgets" resource. This does
         not mean that it (for example) doesn’t support any HTTP methods; it
         means that the client will need to discover this by interacting with
         the resource, and/or examining the documentation for its link
         relation type.</t>

      </section>
      <section anchor="resource-objects" title="Resource Objects">

         <t>A Resource Object links to resources of the defined type using one
         of two mechanisms; either a direct link (in which case there is
         exactly one resource of that relation type associated with the API),
         or a templated link, in which case there are zero to many such
         resources.</t>

         <t>Resource Objects MUST have only and exactly one of the "href" and
         "href-template" properties.</t>
      
         <t>Direct links are indicated with an "href" property, whose value is
         a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

         <t>Templated links are indicated with an "href-template" property,
         whose value is a URI Template <xref target="RFC6570"/>. When
         "href-template" is present, the Resource Object MUST have a
         "href-vars" property; see "Resolving Templated Links".</t>

         <t>In both forms, the links that "href" and "href-template" refer to
         are URI-references <xref target="RFC3986"/> whose base URI is that
         of the JSON Home Document itself.</t>

         <t>Resource Objects MAY also have a "hints" property, whose value is
         an object that uses named Resource Hints as its properties.</t>

         <section anchor="resolving-templates" title="Resolving Templated Links">

            <t>A URI can be derived from a Templated Link by treating the
            "href-template" value as a Level 3 URI Template <xref
            target="RFC6570"/>, using the "href-vars" property to fill the
            template.</t>
            
             <t>The "href-vars" property, in turn, is an object that acts as a
            mapping between variable names available to the template and
            absolute URIs that are used as global identifiers for the
            semantics and syntax of those variables.</t>
            
             <t>For example, given the following Resource Object:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
"http://example.org/rel/widget": {
  "href-template": "/widgets/{widget_id}",
  "href-vars": {
    "widget_id": "http://example.org/param/widget"
  },
  "hints": {
    "allow": ["GET", "PUT", "DELETE", "PATCH"],
    "representations": ["application/json"],
    "accept-patch": ["application/json-patch"],
    "accept-post": ["application/xml"],
    "accept-ranges": ["bytes"]
  }
}      
]]></artwork></figure>

            <t>If you understand that "http://example.org/param/widget" is an
            numeric identifier for a widget (perhaps by dereferencing that URL
            and reading the documentation), you can then find the resource
            corresponding to widget number 12345 at
            "http://example.org/widgets/12345" (assuming that the Home
            Document is located at "http://example.org/").</t>

         </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="resource-hints" title="Resource Hints">

         <t>Resource hints allow clients to find relevant information about
         interacting with a resource beforehand, as a means of optimising
         communications, as well as advertising available behaviours (e.g., to
         aid in laying out a user interface for consuming the API).</t>
         
         <t>Hints are just that – they are not a "contract", and are to only
         be taken as advisory. The runtime behaviour of the resource always
         overrides hinted information.</t>
         
         <t>For example, a resource might hint that the PUT method is allowed
         on all "widget" resources. This means that generally, the user has
         the ability to PUT to a particular resource, but a specific resource
         could reject a PUT based upon access control or other considerations.
         More fine-grained information might be gathered by interacting with
         the resource (e.g., via a GET), or by another resource "containing"
         it (such as a "widgets" collection).</t>
         
         <t>This specification defines a set of common hints, based upon
         information that’s discoverable by directly interacting with
         resources. A future draft will explain how to define new hints.</t>

         <section anchor="allow" title="allow">

            <t>Hints the HTTP methods that the current client will be able to
            use to interact with the resource; equivalent to the Allow HTTP
            response header.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, containing HTTP
            methods.</t>

         </section>
         <section anchor="representations" title="representations">

            <t>Hints the representation types that the resource produces and
            consumes, using the GET and PUT methods respectively, subject to
            the ‘allow’ hint.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, containing media
            types.</t>

         </section>
         <section anchor="accept-patch" title="accept-patch">

            <t>Hints the PATCH request formats <xref target="RFC5789"/>
            accepted by the resource for this client; equivalent to the
            Accept-Patch HTTP response header.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, containing media
            types.</t>

         </section>
         <section anchor="accept-post" title="accept-post">

            <t>Hints the POST request formats accepted by the resource for
            this client.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, containing media
            types.</t>

         </section>
         <section anchor="accept-put" title="accept-put">

            <t>Hints the PUT request formats accepted by the resource for
            this client.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, containing media
            types. If absent, a client MAY assume that any format indicated
            by the 'representations' hint is acceptable in a PUT.</t>

         </section>
         <section anchor="accept-ranges" title="accept-ranges">

            <t>Hints the range-specifiers available to the client for this
            resource; equivalent to the Accept-Ranges HTTP response
            header <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-p5-range"/>.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, containing HTTP
            range-specifiers.</t>

         </section>
         
         <section anchor="accept-prefer" title="prefer">
            
            <t>Hints the preferences <xref target="I-D.snell-http-prefer"/>
            supported by the resource. Note that, as per that specifications,
            a preference can be ignored by the server.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, contain preferences.</t>
            
         </section>
         
         <section anchor="precondition-req" title="precondition-req">
            
            <t>Hints that the resource requires state-changing requests (e.g.,
            PUT, PATCH) to include a precondition, as per <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-p4-conditional"/>, to avoid conflicts due
            to concurrent updates.</t>
            
            <t>Content MUST be an array of strings, with possible values
            "etag" and "last-modified" indicating type type of precondition
            expected.</t>
            
         </section>
         
      </section>

      <section anchor="creating" title="Creating and Serving Home Documents">

         <t>When making a home document available, there are a few things to
         keep in mind:</t>

         <t><list style='symbols'>

           <t>A home document is best located at a memorable URI, because its
           URI will effectively become the URI for the API itself to
           clients.</t>
           <t>Home documents can be personalised, just as "normal" home pages
           can. For example, you might advertise different URIs, and/or
           different kinds of link relations, depending on the client’s
           identity.</t>
           <t>Home documents SHOULD be assigned a freshness lifetime (e.g.,
           "Cache-Control: max-age=3600") so that clients can cache them, to
           avoid having to fetch it every time the client interacts with the
           service.</t>
           <t>Custom link relation types, as well as the URIs for variables,
           should lead to documentation for those constructs.</t>
         </list></t>

         <section anchor="managing-change-in-home-documents" title="Managing Change in Home Documents">

            <t>The URIs used in home documents MAY change over time. However,
            changing them can cause issues for clients that are relying on
            cached home documents containing old links.</t>

            <t>To mitigate these risks, servers changing links SHOULD
            consider:</t>

            <t><list style='symbols'>
              <t>Reducing the freshness lifetime of home documents before a
              link change, so that clients are less likely to refer to an
              "old" document</t>
              <t>Assure that they handle requests for the "old" URIs
              appropriately; e.g., with a 404 Not Found, or by redirecting the
              client to the new URI.</t>
              <t>Alternatively, considering the "old" and "new" URIs as
              equally valid references for an "overlap" period.</t>
            </list></t>

            <t>Generally, servers ought not to change URIs without good
            cause.</t>

         </section>

         <section anchor="evolving-and-mixing-apis-with-home-documents" title="Evolving and Mixing APIs with Home Documents">

            <t>Using home documents affords the opportunity to change the
            "shape" of the API over time, without breaking old clients. </t>
            
             <t>This includes introducing new functions alongside the old ones
            – by adding new link relation types with corresponding resource
            objects – as well as adding new template variables, media types,
            and so on.</t>
            
             <t>It’s important to realise that a home document can serve more
            than one "API" at a time; by listing all relevant relation types,
            it can effectively "mix" different APIs, allowing clients to work
            with different resources as they see fit.</t>

         </section>

         <section anchor="documenting-apis-that-use-home-documents" title="Documenting APIs that use Home Documents">

            <t>Another use case for "static" API description formats like WSDL
            and WADL is to generate documentation for the API from them.</t>
            
             <t>An API that uses the home document format correctly won’t have
            a need to do so, provided that the link relation types and media
            types it uses are well-documented already.</t>

         </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="consuming-home-documents" title="Consuming Home Documents">

         <t>Clients might use home documents in a variety of ways. </t>

         <t>In the most common case – actually consuming the API – the client
         will scan the Resources Object for the link relation(s) that it is
         interested in, and then to interact with the resource(s) referred to.
         Resource Hints can be used to optimise communication with the client,
         as well as to inform as to the permissible actions (e.g., whether PUT
         is likely to be supported).</t>

         <t>Note that the home document is a "living" document; it does not
         represent a "contract", but rather is expected to be inspected before
         each interaction. In particular, links from the home document MUST
         NOT be assumed to be valid beyond the freshness lifetime of the home
         document, as per HTTP’s caching model <xref target="RFC2616"/>.</t>
         
          <t>As a result, clients SHOULD cache the home document (as per <xref
          target="RFC2616"/>, to avoid fetching it before every interaction
          (which would otherwise be required).</t>
         
          <t>Likewise, a client encountering a 404 Not Found on a link SHOULD
         obtain a fresh copy of the home document, to assure that it is
         up-to-date.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

         <t>TBD</t>

      </section>
      <section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

         <t>TBD</t>

      </section>
      
	</middle>

	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			&rfc2119;
			&rfc2616;
			&rfc3986;
			&rfc4627;
			&rfc5988;
			&rfc6570;
		</references>

		<references title="Informative References">
			&rfc4288;
			&rfc5789;
			&httpbis-conditional;
			&httpbis-range;
			&prefer;
		</references>

		<section title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>Thanks to 
               Mike Amundsen,
               Bill Burke,
               Graham Klyne,
               Leif Hedstrom, and
               Jeni Tennison
			  for their suggestions and feedback.           
			 </t>
		</section>

      <section anchor="frequently-asked-questions" title="Frequently Asked Questions">

         <section anchor="why-not-microformats" title="Why not Microformats?">

            <t>Browser-centric Web applications use HTML as their
            representation format of choice. While it is possible to augment
            HTML for non-browser clients (using techniques like <eref
            target="http://microformats.org/">Microformats</eref> ), a few
            issues become evident when doing so:</t>

            <t><list style='symbols'>
              <t>HTML has a very forgiving syntax. While this is appropriate
              for browsers (especially considering that there are many million
              HTML authors in the world), it makes for a less-than-precise
              language for machines, resulting in both overhead (parsing and
              transmission) as well as lack of precision.</t>
              <t>HTML is presentation-centric, making it tempting to reformat
              it from time to time, to improve the "look and feel" of a page.
              However, doing so can cause comparatively brittle non-browser
              clients to lose their understanding of the content’s semantics,
              unless very careful controls are in place.</t>
            </list></t>

            <t>Because of this, it’s most practical to define a separate
            format, and JSON is easily machine-readable, precise, and has a
            better chance of being managed for stability.</t>

         </section>
         <section anchor="what-about-authentication" title="What about authentication?">

            <t>In HTTP, authentication is discoverable by interacting with the
            resource (usually, by getting a 401 Unauthorized response status
            code, along with one or more challenges). While the home document
            could hint it, this isn’t yet done, to avoid possible security
            complications.</t>

         </section>
         <section anchor="what-about-faults-ie-errors" title="What about "Faults" (i.e., errors)?">

            <t>In HTTP, errors are conveyed by HTTP status codes. While this
            specification could (and even may) allow enumeration of possible
            error conditions, there’s a concern that this will encourage
            applications to define many such "faults", leading to tight
            coupling between the application and its clients.</t>
            
             <t>So, this is an area of possible future development; if any
            such mechanism appears here, it’s likely to be quite
            restricted.</t>

         </section>
         <section title="How Do I find the XML Schema / JSON Schema / etc. for a particular media type?">

            <t>That isn’t addressed by home documents. Ultimately, it’s up to
            the media type accepted and generated by resources to define and
            constrain (or not) their syntax. </t>

         </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="open-issues" title="Open Issues">

      <t>The following is a list of placeholders for open issues.</t>

      <t><list style='symbols'>
        <t>Refining and extending representation formats - "application/xml",
        for example, isn't enough. While a media type for every representation
        is one answer, something like 'profile' might be good too.</t>
        <t>Object for contact details - do we need an object that describes
        who's running the API, etc?</t>
        <t>Defining new hints - guidance is needed on minting new hints.
        Possibly a registry.</t>
        <t>Defining new top-level properties - how new ones are minted,
        registry, etc.</t>
        <t>Defining new Resource Object properties - how new ones are minted,
        registry, etc.</t>
      </list></t>
      </section>

	</back>
</rfc>
