<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc1591 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1591.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2048 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2048.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2396 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2396.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3023 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3023.xml'>
]>

<?rfc toc="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

<!--

Other stuff to add ...

- mention shortcomings of Don Eastlake's work?
- examples and example representations from dereferenced URIs

-->


<rfc category="std" ipr="full2026" docName="draft-nottingham-uri-media-tree-00.xml">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="The 'uri' Media Type Tree">The 'uri' Media Type Registration Tree</title>
        <author initials='M' surname="Nottingham" fullname='Mark Nottingham'>
            <organization>BEA Systems</organization>
        </author>
        <author initials='M' surname="Baker" fullname='Mark Baker'>
        	<organization/>
        </author>
        <date month="November" year="2003"/>
        <abstract><t>This document specifies the 'uri' media subtype registration tree,
    which is intended to ease the deployment of new Internet applications
    with associated media types without being constrained by the 
    necessity of a specialized central registry.  By using URIs, this tree also provides
    the (optional) added benefit of permitting the decentralized lookup of information
    associated with the media type.</t></abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Requirements notation">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Introduction">
        <t>The <xref target="RFC2048">registration procedures for Internet media types</xref> allow for the
        specification of media type trees, which allow for faceted names to be described in order to increase 
        the efficiency and flexibility of the registration process. They also allow for the creation of new 
        registration trees, with the advice and consent of the IESG.</t>    
        <t>This specification proposes one such tree for consideration.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Motivations">
            <section title="Decentralization">
            <t><xref target="RFC2048"><!-- connoly-baker -->A Registry of Assignments using Ubiquitous Technologies and Careful Policies"</xref>
               was also an important motivation for the 'uri' tree.  It describes
               some of the shortcomings of registries which don't assign authoritative dereferenceable
               URIs for their assignments.
            </t>

            <t>It is an objective of the 'uri' subtree to achieve as many of the benefits of
               this approach as possible, while still fitting into the existing deployed media type
               based application dispatch framework.
            </t>
            </section>

            <section title="XML">
            
            <t>The Internet media type system was designed to encourage certain properties, and
                arguably has been quite successful because of its approach. In particular, IANA acts as a central 
                registry to bring coordination and convenience, and various levels of community review are 
                required before a media type may be registered, to assure some level of quality in and appropriate 
                application of media types.</t>

            <t>However, the advent of the Web and in particular XML has changed the conditions in which
                formats are created and used. XML allows the creation of business-specific document
                and protocol formats by end users, rather than standards organisations. Often, these end
                users are unfamiliar with IETF and IANA process for registration of media types, and do not
                have a requirement for recognition by a centralized registry. As such, the cost of media type
                registration for these users is not justified.</t>

            <t>As a result, many formats are created without corresponding media types (often under the umbrella 
                of 'text/xml' or 'application/xml'). Such formats are not first-class citizens on the Internet or
                the Web; one cannot content negotiate for them, for example, and one cannot use existing software
                dispatch mechanisms in MIME software to accommodate them.</t> 
            
            <t>It should be noted that these undesirable effects disproportionately affect those who wish to use 
                the format in ways that may not have been forseen by its creators. As such, the registration 
                system indirectly discourages the use of those mechanisms that leverage media types.</t>

            <t>Current registration proceedures do allow for some flexibility to accommodate vendor-specific
                formats (the .vnd tree), "vanity" formats (the .prs tree) and ad hoc, experimental formats 
                (the x. tree and its predecessor, the 'x-' convention). Unfortunately, these mechanisms do not address
                the problems described here; the .vnd and .prs trees are still based on a centralized registry, and
                the x- convention is too brittle for most uses (and indeed its use has been discouraged for some time).
            </t>

<!--
            <t>As a result of all of these factors, there is a need to register media types for ad hoc, experimental, limited 
                deployment, or otherwise specialized formats that is not addressed by the 'x', 'prs' or 'vnd' trees. In the
                case of the 'x' tree, this is caused by the lack of coordination, and, paradoxically, in the case of the 'prs'
                and 'vnd' trees, problems arise because the burden of coordination is too great.</t>
-->
            <t>This specification proposes that the widely deployed DNS infrastructure be leveraged to act as a distributed
                registry, to avoid the possibility of collision, whilst removing the need for an additional centralized 
                registry. In this manner, it is similar to URIs, in that they also leverage the DNS to provide locally-managed
                name spaces.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="The 'uri' Tree">
            <t>The 'uri' tree follows the conventions of faceted name trees as specified by <xref target="RFC2048"/>, and is
                distinguished by the leading facet 'uri.'. This facet MUST be followed by an absolute URI reference
                per <xref target="RFC2396"/>, with the additional syntactic constraint that the URI cannot include
                an unescaped semi-colon (";"), as this would be interpreted by MIME agents as a delimiter between
                the media type and its attributes.
            </t>
            <t>Media types using this tree MUST be minted with the knowledge and permission of the authority identified
                by the authority component of the URI, if any.
            </t>
            <section title="Format-Specific Attributes">
                <t>Formats using this tree MAY designate their own attributes, which SHOULD
                    be documented at or referenced from the URI facet of the type.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>Implementation of the uri tree does not require IANA coordination.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <section title="Change of Ownership">
                <t>Over time, the authority for the URI in a uri tree media type may change ownership. Without proper
                    care, media types created by the previous owner might collide with those created by the new owner.
                    As a result, when domains which have been used in the registration of media
                    types in the uri tree change hands, the previous owner SHOULD take care to 
                    communicate existing media types to the new owner, and the new owner SHOULD
                    take care to avoid collisions. Previous owners MAY publish a transition plan
                    to a new domain, if doing so is judged to cause minimal disruption.</t>
            </section>
<!--
I disagree with this for the URI tree, so suggest we exclude it.  Being the person who
determines what a GET returns is enough of a demonstration of ownership IMO.
            <section title="Unauthorized Registration">

                <t>Media types using the dns tree have no enforced relationship to the domain
                    names that they are based upon; the use of domain names is only a convention
                    to assure proper name spacing. Implementations SHOULD NOT make any assumptions
                    about this relationship, especially regarding security issues.</t>
            </section>
-->
        </section>
    </middle>

<!--
Do you want to check with these folks?  Some might be surprised to learn that what they reviewed
is now the uri tree - they may not even agree with the idea.
-->
    <back>
        <references>&rfc1591; &rfc2119; &rfc2048; &rfc2396; &rfc3023;</references>
        <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>The following people gave input and feedback during the creation of this document; Graham Klyne, Don Box, 
            David Orchard, John Kemp and Ted Hardie. All errors are the responsibility of the authors.</t>
        </section>    </back>

</rfc>
