<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3023 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3023.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="full3978" docName="draft-nottingham-rss-media-type-01">
    <front>
        <title>The "application/rss+xml" media type</title>
        <author initials='D.' surname="Winer" fullname='Dave Winer'>
            <organization></organization>
            <address>
			<email>mailto:dwiner@cyber.law.harvard.edu</email>
		   </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="J." surname="Palfrey" fullname="John Palfrey">
           <organization abbrev="Berkman">The Berkman Center for Internet and Society at Harvard Law School</organization>
           <address>
           <email>mailto:jpalfrey@law.harvard.edu</email>
           </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham" role="editor">
            <organization></organization>
            <address>
			<email>mailto:mnot@pobox.com</email>
		   </address>
        </author>
        <date month="May" year="2006"/>
        <abstract><t>This document defines the "application/rss+xml" media type.</t></abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Notational Conventions">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>

<section title="Introduction">

   <t> RSS is a lightweight, multipurpose, extensible metadata description
   and syndication format. It is currently used for a number of applications, 
   including news and other headline syndication, weblog syndication, and the
   propogation of software update lists. </t>

   <t>There are a number of revisions of the RSS format in use. This memo 
   defines a media type, application/rss+xml, that is intended for use
   with RSS 2.0, but may be used with other versions of RSS.</t>

</section>

<section title="Registration">

<t>
<list style="hanging">
  <t hangText="MIME media type name:">
	application</t>

     <t hangText="MIME subtype name:">
	rss+xml</t>

     <t hangText="Required parameters:">
	none</t>

     <t hangText="Optional parameters:">
	<list style="hanging">
	<t hangText='"charset":'>
	This parameter has identical semantics to the charset parameter
	of the "application/xml" media type as specified in RFC 3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.
	</t>

	<t hangText='"revision":'>
	This optional parameter indicates the version of RSS used;
	the value is specified by the target RSS version. It MAY be an XML
	namespace (e.g., "http://purl.org/rss/1.0/" for RSS 1.0), or a
	revision number (e.g., "2.0").</t>
	<t>Note that it is a hint only.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
     <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">
	Identical to those of "application/xml" as described in RFC 3023
	<xref target="RFC3023"/>, section 3.2.</t>

     <t hangText="Security considerations:">
     Shares the security considerations as described in RFC 3023
          <xref target="RFC3023"/>, section 10.</t>

     <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">
	There are no known interoperability issues.</t>

     <t hangText="Published specification:">
	See <xref target="rss2"/>.</t>

     <t hangText="Applications that use this media type:">
	Some RSS applications (e.g., aggregators and content producers) use this media type.</t>
     </list>

     <t>Additional information:</t>

    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Magic number:">
    There is no one series of bytes that can be used to identify the beginning of an RSS file.</t>

     <t hangText="File extension:">
	.rss</t>

     <t hangText="Macintosh File Type code:">
	TEXT</t>

     <t hangText="Fragment identifiers:">
	Identical to that of "application/xml" as described in RFC 3023
	<xref target="RFC3023"/>, section 5.</t>

     <t hangText="Base URI:">
	As specified in RFC 3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>, section 6.</t>


     <t hangText="Person and email address to contact for further information:">
	The author of this memo.</t>

     <t hangText="Intended usage:">
	COMMON</t>

     <t hangText="Author/Change controller:">
	The author of this memo.</t>
	</list>
   </t>
</section>

    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">&rfc2119; &rfc3023;</references>
        <section title="RSS Specification (non-normative)" anchor="rss2">
        <figure>
        <preamble>This appendix incorporates a copy of the RSS 2.0 specification for
        reference only; it does not supercede it.</preamble>

<artwork> <![CDATA[
RSS 2.0 Specification

    Contents

  * What is RSS?
  * Sample files
  * About this document
  * Required channel elements
  * Optional channel elements
  * Elements of <item>
  * Comments
  * Extending RSS
  * Roadmap
  * License and authorship

What is RSS?

RSS is a Web content syndication format.

Its name is an acronym for Really Simple Syndication.

RSS is a dialect of XML. All RSS files must conform to the XML
1.0 specification, as published on the World Wide Web Consortium
(W3C) website.

A summary of RSS version history.

At the top level, a RSS document is a <rss> element, with a
mandatory attribute called version, that specifies the version of
RSS that the document conforms to. If it conforms to this
specification, the version attribute must be 2.0.

Subordinate to the <rss> element is a single <channel> element,
which contains information about the channel (metadata) and its
contents.

Sample files

Here are sample files for: RSS 0.91, 0.92 and 2.0.

Note that the sample files may point to documents and services
that no longer exist. The 0.91 sample was created when the 0.91
docs were written. Maintaining a trail of samples seems like a
good idea.

About this document

This document represents the status of RSS as of the Fall of
2002, version 2.0.1.

It incorporates all changes and additions, starting with the
basic spec for RSS 0.91 (June 2000) and includes new features
introduced in RSS 0.92 (December 2000) and RSS 0.94 (August
2002).

Change notes are here.

First we document the required and optional sub-elements of
<channel>; and then document the sub-elements of <item>. The
final sections answer frequently asked questions, and provide a
roadmap for future evolution, and guidelines for extending RSS.

Required channel elements

Here's a list of the required channel elements, each with a brief
description, an example, and where available, a pointer to a more
complete description.

Element    Description                              Example

title      The name of the channel. It's how   GoUpstate.com
           people refer to your service. If    News Headlines
           you have an HTML website that 
           contains the same information as
           your RSS file, the title of your
           channel should be the same as
           the title of your website.

link       The URL to the HTML website         http://www.
           corresponding to the channel.       goupstate.com/

description  Phrase or sentence describing     The latest news from
             the channel.                      from GoUpstate.com, a
                                               Spartanburg Herald-
                                               Journal Web site.

Optional channel elements

Here's a list of optional channel elements.

Element        Description                         Example
language       The language the channel is written en-us
               in. This allows aggregators to
               group all Italian language sites,
               for example, on a single page. A
               list of allowable values for this
               element, as provided by Netscape,
               is here. You may also use values
               defined by the W3C.

copyright      Copyright notice for content in the Copyright 2002,
               channel.                            Spartanburg
                                                   Herald-Journal

managingEditor Email address for person            geo@herald.com
               responsible for editorial content.  (George Matesky)

webMaster      Email address for person            betty@herald.com
               responsible for technical issues    (Betty Guernsey)
               relating to channel.

pubDate        The publication date for the        Sat, 07 Sep 2002
               content in the channel. For         00:00:01 GMT
               example, the New York Times
               publishes on a daily basis, the
               publication date flips once every
               24 hours. That's when the pubDate
               of the channel changes. All
               date-times in RSS conform to the
               Date and Time Specification of RFC
               822, with the exception that the
               year may be expressed with two
               characters or four characters (four
               preferred).

lastBuildDate  The last time the content of the    Sat, 07 Sep 2002
               channel changed.                    09:42:31 GMT

category    Specify one or more categories that <category>
            the channel belongs to. Follows the Newspapers
            same rules as the <item>-level      </category>
            category element. More info.

generator   A string indicating the program     MightyInHouse
            used to generate the channel.       Content System v2.3

docs        A URL that points to the            http://
            documentation for the format used   blogs.law.harvard.edu
            in the RSS file. It's probably a    /tech/rss
            pointer to this page. It's for
            people who might stumble across an
            RSS file on a Web server 25 years
            from now and wonder what it is.

cloud       Allows processes to register with a <cloud
            cloud to be notified of updates to  domain="rpc.sys.com"
            the channel, implementing a         port="80"
            lightweight publish-subscribe       path="/RPC2"
            protocol for RSS feeds. More info   registerProcedure=
            here.                               "pingMe" 
                                                protocol="soap"/>

ttl         ttl stands for time to live. It's a <ttl>60</ttl>
            number of minutes that indicates
            how long a channel can be cached
            before refreshing from the source.
            More info here.

image       Specifies a GIF, JPEG or PNG image
            that can be displayed with the
            channel. More info here.

rating      The PICS rating for the channel.

textInput   Specifies a text input box that can
            be displayed with the channel. More
            info here.

skipHours   A hint for aggregators telling them
            which hours they can skip. More
            info here.

skipDays    A hint for aggregators telling them
            which days they can skip. More info
            here.

<image> sub-element of <channel>

<image> is an optional sub-element of <channel>, which contains
three required and three optional sub-elements.

<url> is the URL of a GIF, JPEG or PNG image that represents the
channel.

<title> describes the image, it's used in the ALT attribute of
the HTML <img> tag when the channel is rendered in HTML.

<link> is the URL of the site, when the channel is rendered, the
image is a link to the site. (Note, in practice the image <title>
and <link> should have the same value as the channel's <title>
and <link>.

Optional elements include <width> and <height>, numbers,
indicating the width and height of the image in pixels.
<description> contains text that is included in the TITLE
attribute of the link formed around the image in the HTML
rendering.

Maximum value for width is 144, default value is 88.

Maximum value for height is 400, default value is 31.

<cloud> sub-element of <channel>

<cloud> is an optional sub-element of <channel>.

It specifies a web service that supports the rssCloud interface
which can be implemented in HTTP-POST, XML-RPC or SOAP 1.1.

Its purpose is to allow processes to register with a cloud to be
notified of updates to the channel, implementing a lightweight
publish-subscribe protocol for RSS feeds.

<cloud domain="rpc.sys.com" port="80" path="/RPC2"
registerProcedure="myCloud.rssPleaseNotify" protocol="xml-rpc" />

In this example, to request notification on the channel it
appears in, you would send an XML-RPC message to rpc.sys.com on
port 80, with a path of /RPC2. The procedure to call is
myCloud.rssPleaseNotify.

A full explanation of this element and the rssCloud interface is
here.

<ttl> sub-element of <channel>

<ttl> is an optional sub-element of <channel>.

ttl stands for time to live. It's a number of minutes that
indicates how long a channel can be cached before refreshing from
the source. This makes it possible for RSS sources to be managed
by a file-sharing network such as Gnutella.

Example: <ttl>60</ttl>

<textInput> sub-element of <channel>

A channel may optionally contain a <textInput> sub-element, which
contains four required sub-elements.

<title> -- The label of the Submit button in the text input area.

<description> -- Explains the text input area.

<name> -- The name of the text object in the text input area.

<link> -- The URL of the CGI script that processes text input
requests.

The purpose of the <textInput> element is something of a mystery.
You can use it to specify a search engine box. Or to allow a
reader to provide feedback. Most aggregators ignore it.

  ----------------------------------------------------------------

Elements of <item>

A channel may contain any number of <item>s. An item may
represent a "story" -- much like a story in a newspaper or
magazine; if so its description is a synopsis of the story, and
the link points to the full story. An item may also be complete
in itself, if so, the description contains the text
(entity-encoded HTML is allowed; see examples), and the link and
title may be omitted. All elements of an item are optional,
however at least one of title or description must be present.

Element          Description              Example
title            The title of the item.   Venice Film Festival
                                          Tries to Quit Sinking

link             The URL of the item.     http://nytimes.com/2004/
                                          12/07FEST.html

description      The item synopsis.       Some of the most heated
                                          chatter at the Venice
                                          Film Festival this week
                                          was about the way that
                                          the arrival of the stars
                                          at the Palazzo del Cinema
                                          was being staged.

author           Email address of the author of
                 the item. More.

category         Includes the item in one or more
                 categories. More.

comments         URL of a page for comments
                 relating to the item. More.

enclosure        Describes a media object that is
                 attached to the item. More.

guid             A string that uniquely
                 identifies the item. More.

pubDate          Indicates when the item was
                 published. More.

source           The RSS channel that the item
                 came from. More.

<source> sub-element of <item>

<source> is an optional sub-element of <item>.

Its value is the name of the RSS channel that the item came from,
derived from its <title>. It has one required attribute, url,
which links to the XMLization of the source.

<source url="http://www.tomalak.org/links2.xml">Tomalak's
Realm</source>

The purpose of this element is to propagate credit for links, to
publicize the sources of news items. It can be used in the Post
command of an aggregator. It should be generated automatically
when forwarding an item from an aggregator to a weblog authoring
tool.

<enclosure> sub-element of <item>

<enclosure> is an optional sub-element of <item>.

It has three required attributes. url says where the enclosure is
located, length says how big it is in bytes, and type says what
its type is, a standard MIME type.

The url must be an http url.

<enclosure
url="http://www.scripting.com/mp3s/weatherReportSuite.mp3"
length="12216320" type="audio/mpeg" />

A use-case narrative for this element is here.

<category> sub-element of <item>

<category> is an optional sub-element of <item>.

It has one optional attribute, domain, a string that identifies a
categorization taxonomy.

The value of the element is a forward-slash-separated string that
identifies a hierarchic location in the indicated taxonomy.
Processors may establish conventions for the interpretation of
categories. Two examples are provided below:

<category>Grateful Dead</category>

<category domain="http://www.fool.com/cusips">MSFT</category>

You may include as many category elements as you need to, for
different domains, and to have an item cross-referenced in
different parts of the same domain.

<pubDate> sub-element of <item>

<pubDate> is an optional sub-element of <item>.

Its value is a date, indicating when the item was published. If
it's a date in the future, aggregators may choose to not display
the item until that date.

<pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2002 15:21:36 GMT</pubDate>

<guid> sub-element of <item>

<guid> is an optional sub-element of <item>.

guid stands for globally unique identifier. It's a string that
uniquely identifies the item. When present, an aggregator may
choose to use this string to determine if an item is new.

<guid>http://some.server.com/weblogItem3207</guid>

There are no rules for the syntax of a guid. Aggregators must
view them as a string. It's up to the source of the feed to
establish the uniqueness of the string.

If the guid element has an attribute named "isPermaLink" with a
value of true, the reader may assume that it is a permalink to
the item, that is, a url that can be opened in a Web browser,
that points to the full item described by the <item> element. An
example:

<guid
isPermaLink="true">http://inessential.com/2002/09/01.php#a2
</guid>

isPermaLink is optional, its default value is true. If its value
is false, the guid may not be assumed to be a url, or a url to
anything in particular.

<comments> sub-element of <item>

<comments> is an optional sub-element of <item>.

If present, it is the url of the comments page for the item.

<comments>http://ekzemplo.com/entry/4403/comments</comments>

More about comments here.

<author> sub-element of <item>

<author> is an optional sub-element of <item>.

It's the email address of the author of the item. For newspapers
and magazines syndicating via RSS, the author is the person who
wrote the article that the <item> describes. For collaborative
weblogs, the author of the item might be different from the
managing editor or webmaster. For a weblog authored by a single
individual it would make sense to omit the <author> element.

<author>lawyer@boyer.net (Lawyer Boyer)</author>

Comments

RSS places restrictions on the first non-whitespace characters of
the data in <link> and <url> elements. The data in these elements
must begin with an IANA-registered URI scheme, such as http://,
https://, news://, mailto: and ftp://. Prior to RSS 2.0, the
specification only allowed http:// and ftp://, however, in
practice other URI schemes were in use by content developers and
supported by aggregators. Aggregators may have limits on the URI
schemes they support. Content developers should not assume that
all aggregators support all schemes.

In RSS 0.91, various elements are restricted to 500 or 100
characters. There can be no more than 15 <items> in a 0.91
<channel>. There are no string-length or XML-level limits in RSS
0.92 and greater. Processors may impose their own limits, and
generators may have preferences that say no more than a certain
number of <item>s can appear in a channel, or that strings are
limited in length.

In RSS 2.0, a provision is made for linking a channel to its
identifier in a cataloging system, using the channel-level
category feature, described above. For example, to link a channel
to its Syndic8 identifier, include a category element as a
sub-element of <channel>, with domain "Syndic8", and value the
identifier for your channel in the Syndic8 database. The
appropriate category element for Scripting News would be
<category domain="Syndic8">1765</category>.

A frequently asked question about <guid>s is how do they compare
to <link>s. Aren't they the same thing? Yes, in some content
systems, and no in others. In some systems, <link> is a permalink
to a weblog item. However, in other systems, each <item> is a
synopsis of a longer article, <link> points to the article, and
<guid> is the permalink to the weblog entry. In all cases, it's
recommended that you provide the guid, and if possible make it a
permalink. This enables aggregators to not repeat items, even if
there have been editing changes.

If you have questions about the RSS 2.0 format, please post them
on the RSS2-Support mail list, hosted by Sjoerd Visscher. This is
not a debating list, but serves as a support resource for users,
authors and developers who are creating and using content in RSS
2.0 format.

Extending RSS

RSS originated in 1999, and has strived to be a simple, easy to
understand format, with relatively modest goals. After it became
a popular format, developers wanted to extend it using modules
defined in namespaces, as specified by the W3C.

RSS 2.0 adds that capability, following a simple rule. A RSS feed
may contain elements not described on this page, only if those
elements are defined in a namespace.

The elements defined in this document are not themselves members
of a namespace, so that RSS 2.0 can remain compatible with
previous versions in the following sense -- a version 0.91 or
0.92 file is also a valid 2.0 file. If the elements of RSS 2.0
were in a namespace, this constraint would break, a version 0.9x
file would not be a valid 2.0 file.

Roadmap

RSS is by no means a perfect format, but it is very popular and
widely supported. Having a settled spec is something RSS has
needed for a long time. The purpose of this work is to help it
become a unchanging thing, to foster growth in the market that is
developing around it, and to clear the path for innovation in new
syndication formats. Therefore, the RSS spec is, for all
practical purposes, frozen at version 2.0.1. We anticipate
possible 2.0.2 or 2.0.3 versions, etc. only for the purpose of
clarifying the specification, not for adding new features to the
format. Subsequent work should happen in modules, using
namespaces, and in completely new syndication formats, with new
names.

Last update: Sunday, January 30, 2005 at 6:14:58 PM.
]]></artwork>
</figure>

        </section>
    </back>

</rfc>
