<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc1591 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1591.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2048 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2048.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2396 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2396.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3023 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3023.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="full2026" docName="draft-nottingham-dns-media-tree-00">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="The 'dns' Media Type Tree">The 'dns' Media Type Registration Tree</title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
            <organization/>
            <address>
			<email>mailto:mnot@pobox.com</email>
		   </address>
        </author>
        <date month="January" year="2003"/>
        <abstract>
          <t>This document specifies the 'dns' media subtype registration tree,
          which is intended to ease the deployment of new Internet applications
          and their associated media types without the need for coordination with
          a central registry.</t>
	   </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Requirements notation">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
            NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL"
            in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
            target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>

		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>The <xref target="RFC2048">registration proceedures for Internet
			media types</xref> allow for the specification of media type trees,
			which allow for faceted names to be described in order to increase the
			efficiency and flexibility of the registration process. They also
			allows for the creation of new registration trees, with the advice and
			consent of the IESG.</t> 
			
			<t>This specification describes one such tree.</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Motivation">
			<t>The Internet media type system was designed to encourage certain
			properties, and arguably has been quite successful because of its
			approach. In particular, IANA acts as a central registry to bring
			coordination and convenience, and various levels of community
			review are required before a media type may be registered, to
			assure some level of quality in and appropriate application of
			media types.</t>

			<t>However, the arrival of the Web, and in particular XML, has
			changed the conditions under which formats are created and used.
			XML allows the creation of business-specific document and protocol
			formats by end users. Often, these parties are unfamiliar with IETF
			and IANA process for registration of media types, and do not have a
			requirement for recognition by a centralized registry. As such, the
			cost of media type registration is not justified in the view of 
			some parties that are minting new formats.</t>

			<t>As a result, many formats are created without corresponding
			media types (often under the umbrella of 'text/xml' or
			'application/xml'). Such formats are not first-class citizens on
			the Internet or the Web; one cannot content negotiate for them, for
			example, and one cannot use existing software dispatch mechanisms
			in MIME software to accommodate them.</t>

			<t>It should be noted that these undesirable effects
			disproportionately affect those who wish to use a format in ways
			that may not have been forseen by its creators. As such, the
			registration system indirectly discourages the wide use of those
			mechanisms that leverage media types.</t>

			<t>Current registration proceedures do allow for some flexibility
			to accommodate vendor-specific formats (the .vnd tree), "vanity"
			formats (the .prs tree) and ad hoc, experimental formats (the x.
			tree and its predecessor, the 'x-' convention). Unfortunately,
			these mechanisms do not address the problems described here; the x-
			convention is too brittle for most uses (and indeed its use has
			been discouraged for some time), and the .vnd and .prs trees are
			still based on a centralized registry.</t> 
				
			<t>This specification proposes that the widely recognized DNS
			infrastructure be leveraged to act as a distributed registry, to
			avoid the possibility of collision, whilst removing the need for an
			additional centralized registry. The approach is similar to URI
			schemes that also leverage the DNS to provide locally-managed name
			spaces.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="The 'dns' Tree">
			<t>The 'dns' media subtype tree is intended to be used to identify
			proprietary, ad hoc, experimental, or limited deployment
			formats.</t>

			<t>It follows the conventions of faceted name trees as specified by
			<xref target="RFC2048"/>, and is distinguished by the leading facet
			'dns.'. This facet MUST be followed by one or more dot-delimited
			facets that are derived from a domain name, in reverse order.
			Finally, those facets MUST be followed by on or more facets that
			indicate the format's identity within that name space.</t>

			<t>Media types using this tree MUST be minted with the knowledge
			and permission of the authority responsible for the corresponding
			Internet domain name. The domain name used MUST be registered in
			the Internet Registry, as delegated by IANA (see <xref
			target="RFC1591"/>).</t>

			<t>For example, if the entity responsible for example.com wished to
			register a textual media type with the name 'foo' in this fashion,
			its media type might be:</t>

			<t>text/dns.com.example.foo</t>

			<t>XML-based formats SHOULD be conformant with <xref
			target="RFC3023"/>, e.g.:</t>

			<t>application/dns.com.example.foo+xml</t>

			<t>If example.com were a multinational concern, it may wish to
			delegate authority for minting new types to regional departments.
			It could do so by mandating an additional facet; an application
			media type minted by the Australian division might be:</t>

			<t>application/dns.com.example.au.bar</t>

			<t>whilst a completely separate application format, also identified
			as 'bar' and minted by the U.S. division might be distinguished
			as:</t>

			<t>application/dns.com.example.us.bar</t>

			<section title="The 'doc' Attribute">
				<t>Media types in the dns tree MAY use the 'doc' attribute,
				which indicates a <xref target="RFC2396">URL</xref> that can be
				used to locate documentation of the identified format.</t>

				<t>For example:</t>

				<t>application/dns.com.example.foo;
				doc="http://www.example.com/formats/foo.html"</t>

				<t>The 'doc' attribute is only informative, and MUST NOT be
				interpreted to alter the nature of the format identified; i.e.,
				a media type with a 'doc' attribute of "foo" MUST be
				considered equivalent to the same media type with a 'doc'
				attribute of "bar", or one without a 'doc' attribute. </t>
			</section>
			<section title="Format-Specific Attributes">
				<t>Formats using this dns tree MAY designate their own
				attributes, which SHOULD be documented at or referenced from
				the URL specified in the 'doc' attribute, if present.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>Implementation of the dns tree does not require IANA coordination.
			Any media type conformant with this specification is considered 
			to be registered with IANA.</t>
		</section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
			<section title="Change of Ownership"></section>
				<t>Over time, domain names may change ownership. Without proper
				care, media types created by a domain name's previous owner 
				might collide with those created by the new owner.</t>

				<t>As a result, when domains which have been used in the
				registration of media types in the dns tree change hands, the
				previous owner SHOULD take care to communicate existing media
				types to the new owner, and the new owner SHOULD take care to
				avoid collisions. Previous owners MAY publish a transition plan
				to a new domain, if doing so is judged to cause minimal
				disruption.</t>
			<section title="Unauthorized Registration">
				<t>Media types using the dns tree have no enforced relationship
				to the domain names that they are based upon; the use of domain
				names is only a convention to assure proper name spacing.
				Implementations SHOULD NOT make any assumptions about this
				relationship, especially regarding security issues.</t>
			</section>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references>&rfc1591; &rfc2119; &rfc2048; &rfc2396; &rfc3023;</references>
    	<section title="Acknowledgements">
    		<t>The following people gave input and feedback during the creation
    		of this document; Mark Baker, Don Box, Yaron Goland, Ted Hardie, 
    		John Kemp, Graham Klyne, and David Orchard. All errors are the 
    		responsibility of the author.</t>
    	</section>    
    	</back>
</rfc>
