<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3986 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2068 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2068.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2616 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3864 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3864.xml'>
<!ENTITY html SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.W3C.REC-html401-19991224.xml'>  
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="1" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="full3978" docName="draft-nottingham-http-link-header-00">
    <front>        
      <title>HTTP Header Linking</title>		
      <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
	<organization></organization>
	<address>		
	  <email>mnot@pobox.com</email>	
	  <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>		
	</address>	
      </author>		      
     <date year="2006"/>

      <abstract>
<t>This specification clarifies the status of the Link HTTP header and introduces
the complimentary Profile and Link-Template HTTP headers.</t>
      </abstract>    
	  
  </front>    

  <middle>
  
<section title="Introduction">

<t>A means of indicating the relationships between documents on the Web has been
available for some time in HTML, and was considered as a HTTP 
header in <xref target="RFC2068"/>, but removed from <xref target="RFC2616"/>, 
due to a lack of implementation experience.</t>

<t>There have since surfaced many cases where a means of including this
information in HTTP headers has proved useful. However, because it was removed, 
the status of the Link header is unclear, leading some to consider
minting new application-specific HTTP headers instead of reusing it.</t>

<t>Additionally, the complementary "profile" mechanism -- which is often 
used to disambiguate link relationship types -- is not available as a 
HTTP header.</t>

<t>This specification seeks to address these shortcomings. It also introduces
a new header, Link-Template, that allows the structure of links to be 
described.</t>
</section>

<section title="Notational Conventions">

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, <xref target="RFC2119"/>, as
scoped to those conformance targets.</t>

<t>This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)
   notation of <xref target="RFC2616"/>, and explicitly includes the following 
   rules from it: quoted-string, token, SP (space), ALPHA (letters), 
   DIGIT (decimal digit). Additionally, the following rules are included from
   <xref target="RFC3986"/>: URI-Reference, reserved, unreserved.</t>
   
</section>

<section title="The Link Header Field">

<t>The Link entity-header field provides a means for describing a
relationship between two resources, generally between the requested
resource and some other resource. An entity MAY include multiple Link
values. Links at the metainformation level typically indicate
relationships like hierarchical structure and navigation paths. The
Link field is semantically equivalent to the &lt;LINK&gt; element in
HTML.</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Link           = "Link" ":" #("<" URI-Reference ">" 
                   *( ";" link-param ) )
    
    link-param     = ( ( "rel" "=" relationship )
                   | ( "rev" "=" relationship )
                   | ( "title" "=" quoted-string )
                   | ( "anchor" "=" <"> URI-Reference <"> )
                   | ( link-extension ) )
    
    link-extension = token [ "=" ( token | quoted-string ) ]
    
    relationship   = sgml-name
                   | ( <"> sgml-name *( SP sgml-name) <"> )
    
    sgml-name      = ALPHA *( ALPHA | DIGIT | "." | "-" )
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Relationship values are case-insensitive and MAY be extended within
the constraints of the sgml-name syntax. The title parameter MAY be
used to label the destination of a link such that it can be used as
identification within a human-readable menu. The anchor parameter MAY
be used to indicate a source anchor other than the entire current
resource, such as a fragment of this resource or a third resource.</t>

<t>Examples of usage include:</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Link: <http://www.cern.ch/TheBook/chapter2>; rel="Previous"
    Link: <mailto:timbl@w3.org>; rev="Made"; title="Tim Berners-Lee"
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>The first example indicates that chapter2 is previous to this
resource in a logical navigation path. The second indicates that the
person responsible for making the resource available is identified by
the given e-mail address.</t>

</section>

<section title="The Profile Header Field">

<t>The Profile entity-header field provides a means to indicate the meta 
data profile of the entity. Commonly, it is used to disambiguate the meaning
of relationships in links.</t>

<t>Note that this URI MAY be used as either an identifier (e.g., to uniquely
identify links, without dereferencing the URI), or as a link that is intended
to be dereferenced.</t>

<t>The Profile field is semantically equivalent to the profile attribute of the 
HEAD element in HTML <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/>. Note, however,
that its use is not limited to HTML entities.</t>
    
<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Profile       = "Profile" ":" #("<" URI-Reference ">")
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>For example:</t>
     
<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Profile: <http://www.acme.com/profiles/core>
    Profile: <http://example.com/p1>, </profiles/other-profile>
]]></artwork>
</figure>

</section>


<section title="The Link-Template Header Field">

<t>The Link-Template entity-header field provides a means for describing 
the structure of a link between two resources, so that new links can be 
generated.</t>

<t>It does so through by allowing brace ("{}") -delimited strings
to be interposed throughout a URI reference. These correspond to variables
which, after being replaced with content in a relation-specified manner, are
semantically equivalent to the corresponding Link header.</t>

<t>For example,</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Link-Template: <http://example.com/home/{userid}>; rel="home"
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>This link indicates that the "home" link relation can be constructed if the
userid variable is known; if it were known to be "bob", this header would be
considered equivalent to</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Link: <http://example.com/home/bob>; rel="home"
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>This specification does not define when or how template variables are
interposed into link templates. Link relations that wish to allow templating
SHOULD specify such details.</t>

<t>This specification does not define the correct behaviour in the face of a
conflict between a Link-Template header and a Link header with the same 
relation. Link relations allowing templating SHOULD specify their relative
precedence.</t>

<t>Applications SHOULD NOT use link relations that do not explicitly allow
such templating in the Link-Template header.</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Link-Template  = "Link-Template" ":" #("<" template ">" 
                   *( ";" link-param ) )

    template       = *( uri-char | template-var )
    
    template-var   = "{" 1*( uri-char ) "}"

    uri-char       = ( reserved | unreserved )   
]]></artwork>
</figure>

</section>
      
<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This specification requires registration of two Message Header Fields for HTTP
<xref target="RFC3864"/>. Note that "Link" is already present in the registry; this registration only 
updates its specification document.</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve">
Header field: Link
Applicable protocol: http
Status: standard
Author/change controller:
    IETF  (iesg@ietf.org)
    Internet Engineering Task Force
Specification document(s):
   [ this document ]
</artwork>
</figure>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve">
Header field: Profile
Applicable protocol: http
Status: standard
Author/change controller:
    IETF  (iesg@ietf.org)
    Internet Engineering Task Force
Specification document(s):
   [ this document ]
</artwork>
</figure>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve">
Header field: Link-Template
Applicable protocol: http
Status: standard
Author/change controller:
    IETF  (iesg@ietf.org)
    Internet Engineering Task Force
Specification document(s):
   [ this document ]
</artwork>
</figure>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">

<t>The content of both the Link and Profile headers are not secure, private
or integrity-guaranteed, and due caution should be excercised when using them.
</t>

<t>Applications that take advantage of these mechanisms should consider the 
attack vectors opened by automatically following, trusting, or otherwise using
links gathered from HTTP headers.</t>

</section>


	</middle> 

	<back> 
	  
	  <references title="Normative References">
	   &rfc2119;
	   &rfc3986;
	   &rfc2616;
	   &rfc3864;
       &html;
	  </references>
	  <references title="Informative References">
	   &rfc2068;
	  </references>
	  
<section title="Acknowledgements">

<t>This specification lifts the definition of the Link header
from RFC2068; credit for it belongs entirely to the authors of and contributors
to that document.</t>

<t>The semantics and much of the syntax of the Profile header was defined by
HTML 4.01; credit for them belongs to the authors of and contributors to that
document.</t>

<t>Joe Gregorio, Marc Hadley and David Orchard contributed to the design of
the Link-Template mechanism.</t>

</section>
	  
     </back>
</rfc>


