<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2068 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2068.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2434 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2434.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2616 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3864 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3864.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3986 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4287 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4287.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4288 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4288.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4685 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4685.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4946 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4946.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5005 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.5005.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5023 SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.RFC.5023.xml'>
<!ENTITY html SYSTEM 'bibxml/reference.W3C.REC-html401-19991224.xml'>  
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="1" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="full3978" docName="draft-nottingham-http-link-header-02" category="std" updates="4287">
    <front>        
      <title>HTTP Header Linking</title>		
      <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
	<organization></organization>
	<address>		
	  <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>	
	  <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>		
	</address>	
      </author>		      
     <date year="2008"/>

      <abstract>
<t>This document clarifies the status of the Link HTTP header and attempts to consolidate
link relations in a single registry.</t>
      </abstract>    
	  
  </front>    

  <middle>
  
<section title="Introduction">

<t>A means of indicating the relationships between documents on the Web has been
available for some time in HTML <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/>, and was considered as a HTTP 
header in <xref target="RFC2068"/>, but removed from <xref target="RFC2616"/>, 
due to a lack of implementation experience.</t>

<t>There have since surfaced many cases where a means of including this
information in HTTP headers has proved useful. However, because it was removed, 
the status of the Link header is unclear, leading some to consider
minting new application-specific HTTP headers instead of reusing it.</t>

<t>This document seeks to address these shortcomings.</t>

<t>Additionally, formats other than HTML -- namely, Atom <xref target="RFC4287"/> -- 
have also defined generic linking mechanisms that are similar to those in HTML, 
but not identical. This document aims to reconcile these differences when
such links are expressed as headers.</t>

<t>[[ NOTE: This is a straw-man draft that is intended to give a ROUGH idea of what it would take
to align and consolidate the HTML and Atom link relations into a single registry with reasonable
extensibility rules. In particular; a) it changes the registry for Atom link relations, and the 
process for registration; b) it assigns more generic semantics to several existing link relations, both
Atom and HTML; c) it changes the syntax of the Link header (in the case where extensions are present). 
Feedback is welcome on the ietf-http-wg@w3.org mailing list, although this is NOT a work item of the
HTTPBIS WG.
]]</t>

</section>

<section title="Notational Conventions">

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, <xref target="RFC2119"/>, as
scoped to those conformance targets.</t>

<t>This document uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)
   notation of <xref target="RFC2616"/>, and explicitly includes the following 
   rules from it: quoted-string, token, SP (space). Additionally, the following rules are included from
   <xref target="RFC3986"/>: URI-Reference, and from <xref target="RFC4288"/>: type-name.</t>
   
</section>

<section title="The Link Header Field">

<t>The Link entity-header field provides a means for describing a
relationship between two resources, generally between that of the entity
associated with the header and some other resource. An entity MAY include 
multiple Link values.</t>

<t>The Link header field is semantically equivalent to the &lt;LINK&gt; element in
HTML, as well as the atom:link element in Atom <xref target="RFC4287"/>. </t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Link           = "Link" ":" #("<" URI-Reference ">"  
                   *( ";" link-param ) )
    
    link-param     = ( ( "rel" "=" relationship )
                   | ( "type" "=" type-name )
                   | ( "title" "=" quoted-string )
                   | ( link-extension ) )
    
    link-extension = token [ "=" ( token | quoted-string ) ]
    
    relationship   = URI-Reference |
                   <"> URI-Reference *( SP URI-Reference) <"> )
    ]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Relationship values that include a semicolon (";") or comma (",") MUST
	be quoted.</t>

<t>The title parameter MAY be used to label the destination of a link 
such that it can be used as identification within a human-readable menu.</t>

<t>For example:</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
    Link: <http://www.cern.ch/TheBook/chapter2>; rel="previous";
          title="previous chapter"
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>This indicates that chapter2 is previous to this
resource in a logical navigation path.</t>

<section title="Link Relationships">

<t>Relationship values are URIs that identify the type of link. If the 
relationship is a relative URI, its base URI MUST be considered to be
"http://www.iana.org/assignments/relation/", and the value MUST 
be present in the link relation registry.</t>

</section>

</section>
      
<section title="IANA Considerations">

<section title="Link Header Registration">

<t>This specification requires that the Message Header Registry entry for "Link" in HTTP
<xref target="RFC3864"/> be updated to refer to this document, and located at
"http://www.iana.org/assignments/relation/".</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve">
Header field: Link
Applicable protocol: http
Status: standard
Author/change controller:
    IETF  (iesg@ietf.org)
    Internet Engineering Task Force
Specification document(s):
   [ this document ]
</artwork>
</figure>

</section>

<section title="Link Relation Registry">

<t>This specification is intended to update Atom to become the 
reference for the Link Relation registry, and clarifies its nature and use.</t>

<t>A Link relation is a way of indicating the semantics of a link.
Link relations are not format-specific, and MUST NOT specify a particular
format or media type that they are to be used with.</t>

<t>The security considerations of following a particular link are not determined by the link's 
relation type; they are determined by the specific context of the use and the media type of the response.</t>

<t>Likewise, a link relation SHOULD NOT specify what the context of its use is, although
the media type of the dereferenced link may constrain how it is applied.</t>

<t>Link relations that differ only in case (e.g., "Foo" and "foo") MUST NOT be registered.</t>

<t>New relations MAY be registered, subject to IESG Approval, as outlined in <xref target="RFC2434"/>.
Requests should be made by email to IANA, which will then forward the
request to the IESG, requesting approval.  The request should use the
following template:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: </t>
  <t> Description:</t>
  <t> Reference: </t>
</list></t>

<t>The Link Relation registry replaces the Atom Link Relation registry, using
the same address with the following
contents:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: alternate</t>
  <t> Description: Designates a substitute for the link's context.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: appendix</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to an appendix.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: bookmark</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a bookmark or entry point. </t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: chapter</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a chapter in a collection of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: contents</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a table of contents.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: copyright</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a copyright statement.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: current</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a resource containing the most recent item(s) in a collection of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC5005"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: edit</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a resource that can be used to edit the link's context.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC5023"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: edit-media</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a resource that can be used to edit media associated with the link's context.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC5023"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: enclosure</t>
  <t> Description: Identifies a related resource that is potentially large and might require special handling.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC4287"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: first</t>
  <t> Description: A URI that refers to the furthest preceding resource in a series of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/link-relations/first"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: glossary</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a glossary of terms.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: help</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a resource offering help (more information, links to other sources information, etc.)</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: index</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to an index.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: last</t>
  <t> Description: A URI that refers to the furthest following resource in a series of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/link-relations/last"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: license</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a license associated with the link's context.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC4946"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: next</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to the next resource in a ordered series of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: next-archive</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to the immediately following archive resource.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC5005"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: payment</t>
  <t> Description: indicates a resource where payment is accepted.</t>
  <t> Reference: <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/link-relations/payment"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: prev</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to the previous resource in an ordered series of resources. Synonym for "previous".</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: previous</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to the previous resource in an ordered series of resources. Synonym for "prev".</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: prev-archive</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to the immediately preceding archive resource.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC5005"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: related</t>
  <t> Description: Identifies a related resource.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC4287"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: replies</t>
  <t> Description: Identifies a resource that is a reply to the context of the link.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC4685"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: section</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a section in a collection of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: self</t>
  <t> Description: Conveys an identifier for the link's context.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC4287"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: start</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to the first resource in a collection of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: stylesheet</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to an external style sheet.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: subsection</t>
  <t> Description: Refers to a resource serving as a subsection in a collection of resources.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/></t>
</list></t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t> Relation Name: via</t>
  <t> Description: Identifies a resource that is the source of the information in the link's context.</t>
  <t> Reference: <xref target="RFC4287"/></t>
</list></t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">

<t>The content the Link headers is not secure, private
or integrity-guaranteed, and due caution should be excercised when using it.
</t>

<t>Applications that take advantage of these mechanisms should consider the 
attack vectors opened by automatically following, trusting, or otherwise using
links gathered from HTTP headers.</t>

</section>


	</middle> 

	<back> 
	  
	  <references title="Normative References">
	   &rfc2119;
	   &rfc2434;
	   &rfc3986;
	   &rfc2616;
	   &rfc3864;
	   &rfc4288;
	  </references>
	  <references title="Informative References">
	   &rfc2068;
	   &rfc4287;
	   &rfc4685;
	   &rfc4946;
	   &rfc5005;
	   &rfc5023;
       &html;
	  </references>

<section title="Notes on HTML Links">

<t>HTML motivated the original syntax of the Link header, and many of the design decisions
in this document are driven by a desire to stay compatible with these uses.</t>

<t>All of the link relations defined by HTML4 have been included in the link relation registry,
so they can be used without modification. However, extension link relations work differently in HTML4
and the Link header; the former uses a document-wide "profile" URI to scope the relations, while the latter
allows the use of full URIs on individual relations.</t>

<t>Therefore, when using the profile mechanism in HTML4, it is necessary to map the profiled link relations
to URIs when expressed in Link headers. For example, in HTML:</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve">
<![CDATA[
<html>
  <head profile="http://example.com/profile1/">
    <link rel="foo" href="/foo">
  </head>
  [...]
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>

<t>could be represented as a header like this;</t>

<figure>
<artwork xml:space="preserve">
Link: &lt;/foo&gt;; rel="http://example.com/profile1/foo"
</artwork>
</figure>

<t>Profile authors should note this when creating profile URIs; it may be desirable to 
	use URIs that end in a delimiter (e.g., "/" or "#"), to make extracting the specific
	relation in use easier.</t>

<t>HTML defines link relation values as case-insensitive, while the Link header's syntax does not. Therefore,
it is important to case-normalise relation values in HTML before comparing or converting them to Link
headers.</t>

<t>HTML also defines several attributes on links that are not explicitly defined by the Link header.
Although most of these are believed to be defunct, they can be used as link-extensions.</t>

</section>

<section title="Notes on Atom Links">

<t>Atom conveys links in the atom:link element. When serialising an atom:link into a Link header, 
it is necessary to convert IRIs (if used) to URIs.</t>

<t>Additionally, since the base URI for link relations in Link headers is fixed, extension links
(i.e,. those not in the registry) MUST be represented as absolute URIs.</t>

<t>Note also that while the Link header allows multiple relations to be associated with a single
link, atom:link does not. In this case, a single Link header may map to several atom:link elements.
</t>

<t>As with HTML, atom:link defines some attributes that are not explicitly mirrored in the Link header
syntax, but they may also be used as link-extensions.</t>

</section>

	  
<section title="Acknowledgements">

<t>This specification lifts the definition of the Link header
from RFC2068; credit for it belongs entirely to the authors of and contributors
to that document. The link relation registrations themselves are sourced from several documents;
see the applicable references.</t>

<t>The author would like to thank the many people who commented upon, encouraged and gave feedback
	to this draft, especially including Frank Ellermann and Julian Reschke.</t>

</section>

<section title="Document history">

<t>-02</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
	<t>Dropped XLink language.</t>
	<t>Removed 'made' example.</t>
	<t>Removed 'rev'. Can still be used as an extension.</t>
	<t>Added HTML reference to introduction.</t>
	<t>Required relationship values that have a ; or , to be quoted.</t>
	<t>Changed base URI for relation values.</t>
	<t>Noted registry location.</t>
	<t>Added advisory text about HTML profile URIs.</t>
	<t>Disallowed registration of relations that only differ in case.</t>
	<t>Clarified language about IRIs in Atom.</t>
	<t>Added descriptions for 'first', 'last', and 'payment', referring to
		current IANA registry entries, as these were sourced from e-mail. Will
		this cause self-referential implosion?</t>
	<t>Explicitly updates RFC4287.</t>
	<t>Added 'type' parameter.</t>
	<t>Removed unnecessary advice about non-HTML relations in HTML section.</t>
</list></t>

<t>-01</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
 <t>Changed syntax of link-relation to one or more URI; dropped Profile.</t>
 <t>Dropped anchor parameter; can still be an extension.</t>
 <t>Removed Link-Template header; can be specified by templates spec or elsewhere.</t>
 <t>Straw-man for link relation registry.</t>
</list></t>

<t>-00</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>Initial draft; normative text lifted from RFC2068.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
	  
     </back>
</rfc>


