<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
   <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc7303 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7303.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc3986 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc4918 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4918.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc7159 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7159.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5234 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5987 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5987.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5988 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc6694 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6694.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rfc6838 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6838.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rfc7230 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc7231 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7231.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY xml SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xml-20081126.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY html SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-html5-20141028.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rdfa SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-rdfa-core-20130822.xml'>
   <!ENTITY problem-schema SYSTEM 'http-problem-07.rnc'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-appsawg-http-problem-02" category="std">

	<front>
		<title abbrev="Problem Details">Problem Details for HTTP APIs</title>
		<author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
			<organization>Akamai</organization>
			<address>       
				<email>mnot@mnot.net</email> 
				<uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
    <author initials="E." surname="Wilde" fullname="Erik Wilde">
	    <organization>UC Berkeley</organization>
	    <address>
        <email>dret@berkeley.edu</email>
        <uri>http://dret.net/netdret/</uri>
      </address>
	  </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
		<keyword>status</keyword>
		<keyword>HTTP</keyword>
		<keyword>error</keyword>
		<keyword>problem</keyword>
		<keyword>API</keyword>
		<keyword>JSON</keyword>
		<keyword>XML</keyword>
		<abstract>

			<t>This document defines a "problem detail" as a way to carry
      machine-readable details of errors in a HTTP response, to avoid the need
      to define new error response formats for HTTP APIs.</t>

		</abstract>

      <note title="Note to Readers">
  			<t>This draft should be discussed on the <eref        target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/apps-discuss">apps-discuss
         mailing list</eref>.</t>

         <t>This section is to be removed before publication.</t>
      </note>
      
      <note title="Note to RFC Editor">
        <t>Please replace all occurrences of "XXXX" with the final RFC number
        chosen for this draft.</t>
        
        <t>This section is to be removed before publication.</t>
      </note>

	</front>

	<middle>

		<section title="Introduction">
		  
      <t>HTTP <xref target="RFC7230"/> status codes are sometimes not
      sufficient to convey enough information about an error to be helpful.
      While humans behind Web browsers can be informed about the nature of the
      problem with an HTML <xref target="W3C.REC-html5-20141028"/> response
      body, non-human consumers of so-called "HTTP APIs" are usually not.</t>

      <t>This specification defines simple JSON <xref target="RFC7159"/> and
      XML <xref target="W3C.REC-xml-20081126"/> document formats to suit this
      purpose. They are designed to be reused by HTTP APIs, which can identify
      distinct "problem types" specific to their needs.</t>
      
      <t>Thus, API clients can be informed of both the high-level error
      class (using the status code) and the finer-grained details of the
      problem (using one of these formats).</t>

      <t>For example, consider a response that indicates that the client's
      account doesn't have enough credit. The 403 Forbidden status code might
      be deemed most appropriate to use, as it will inform HTTP-generic
      software (such as client libraries, caches and proxies) of the general
      semantics of the response.</t>
      
      <t>However, that doesn't give the API client enough information about
      why the request was forbidden, the applicable account balance, or how to
      correct the problem. If these details are included in the response body
      in a machine-readable format, the client can treat it appropriately; 
      for example, triggering a transfer of more credit into the account.</t>
      
      <t>This specification does this by identifying a specific type of
      problem (e.g., "out of credit") with a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/>;
      HTTP APIs can do this by nominating new URIs under their control, or by
      reusing existing ones.</t>

      <t>Additionally, problems can contain other information, such as a URI
      that identifies the specific occurrence of the problem (effectively
      giving an identifier to the concept "The time Joe didn't have enough
      credit last Thursday"), which can be useful for support or forensic
      purposes.</t>
      
      <t>The data model for problem details is a JSON <xref target="RFC7159"/>
      object; when formatted as a JSON document, it uses the
      "application/problem+json" media type. <xref target="xml-syntax"/>
      defines how to express them in an equivalent XML format, which uses
      the "application/problem+xml" media type.</t>
      
      <t>Note that problem details are (naturally) not the only way to convey
      the details of a problem in HTTP; if the response is still a
      representation of a resource, for example, it's often preferable to
      accommodate describing the relevant details in that application's
      format. Likewise, in many situations, there is an appropriate HTTP
      status code that does not require extra detail to be conveyed.</t>
      
      <t>Instead, the aim of this specification is to define common error
      formats for those applications that need one, so that they aren't
      required to define their own, or worse, tempted to re-define the
      semantics of existing HTTP status codes. Even if an application chooses
      not to use it to convey errors, reviewing its design can help guide
      the design decisions faced when conveying errors in an existing format.</t>

		</section>

		<section title="Requirements">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
		</section>


    <section title="The Problem Details JSON Object" anchor="problem-json">

      <t>The canonical model for problem details is a JSON <xref
      target="RFC7159"/> object.</t>

      <t>When serialised as a JSON document, that format is identified with
      the "application/problem+json" media type.</t>
      
      <t>For example, a HTTP response carrying JSON problem details:</t>

     <figure><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 403 Forbidden
Content-Type: application/problem+json
Content-Language: en

{
 "type": "https://example.com/probs/out-of-credit",
 "title": "You do not have enough credit.",
 "detail": "Your current balance is 30, but that costs 50.",
 "instance": "/account/12345/msgs/abc",
 "balance": 30,
 "accounts": ["/account/12345",
              "/account/67890"]
}]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>Here, the out-of-credit problem (identified by its type URI)
      indicates the reason for the 403 in "title", gives a reference for the
      specific problem occurrence with "instance", gives
      occurrence-specific details in "detail", and adds two extensions;
      "balance" conveys the account's balance, and "accounts" gives links
      where the account can be topped up.</t>

      <t>The ability to convey problem-specific extensions allows more than 
        one problem to be conveyed. For example:</t>
        
      <figure><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 400 Bad Request
Content-Type: application/problem+json
Content-Language: en

{
"type": "https://example.net/validation-error",
"title": "Your request parameters didn't validate.",
"invalid-params": [ { 
                      "name": "age", 
                      "reason": "must be a positive integer"
                    },
                    { 
                      "name": "color",
                      "reason": "must be 'green', 'red' or 'blue'"}
                  ]
}]]></artwork></figure>

     <t>Note that this requires each of the sub-problems to be similar enough
     to use the same HTTP status code. If they do not, the 207 (Multi-Status)
     <xref target="RFC4918"/> code could be used to encapsulate multiple status
     messages.</t>
          
        <section title="Problem Details Object Members" anchor="members">

        <t>A problem details object can have the following members:</t>

        <t><list style='symbols'>

          <t>"type" (string) - A URI reference <xref target="RFC3986"/> that
          identifies the problem type. When dereferenced, it is encouraged to
          provide human-readable documentation for the problem type (e.g.,
          using HTML <xref target="W3C.REC-html5-20141028"/>). When this
          member is not present, its value is assumed to be "about:blank".</t>

          <t>"title" (string) - A short, human-readable summary of the problem
          type. It SHOULD NOT change from occurrence to occurrence of the
          problem, except for purposes of localisation (e.g., using proactive
          content negotiation; see <xref target="RFC7231"/>, Section 3.4).</t>
        
          <t>"status" (number) - The HTTP status code (<xref
          target="RFC7231"/>, Section 6) generated by the origin server for this
          occurrence of the problem.</t>
          
           <t>"detail" (string) - An human readable explanation specific to
          this occurrence of the problem.</t>
          
           <t>"instance" (string) - A URI reference that identifies the
          specific occurrence of the problem. It may or may not yield
          further information if dereferenced.</t>
        
         </list></t>

        <t>Consumers MUST use the type string as the primary
        identifier for the problem type; the title string is advisory, and
        included only for users who are not aware of the semantics of the
        URI, and don't have the ability to discover them (e.g., offline log
        analysis). Consumers SHOULD NOT automatically dereference the
        type URI.</t>

        <t>The status member, if present, is only advisory; it conveys the
        HTTP status code used for the convenience of the consumer. Generators
        MUST use the same status code in the actual HTTP response, to assure
        that generic HTTP software that does not understand this format still
        behaves correctly. See <xref target="security-considerations"/> for
        further caveats regarding its use.</t>

        <t>The detail member, if present, ought to focus on helping the
        client correct the problem, rather than giving debugging
        information.</t>
        
        <t>Consumers SHOULD NOT parse the detail member for information;
        extensions are more suitable and less error-prone ways to obtain
        such information.</t>

        <t>Note that both "type" and "instance" accept relative URIs; this means
          that they must be resolved relative to the document's base URI, as 
          per <xref target="RFC3986"/>, Section 5.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="Extension Members">
       
        <t>Problem type definitions MAY extend the problem details
        object with additional members.</t>
        
        <t>For example, our "out of credit" problem above defines two such
          extensions, "balance" and "accounts" to convey additional, 
          problem-specific information.</t>

        <t>Clients consuming problem details MUST ignore any such extensions
        that they don't recognise; this allows problem types to evolve and
        include additional information in the future.</t>
        
        <t>Note that because extensions are effectively name spaced by the
        problem type, it is not possible to define new "standard" members
        without defining a new media type.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="defining" title="Defining New Problem Types">

      <t>When an HTTP API needs to define a response that indicates an error
      condition, it might be appropriate to do so by defining a new problem 
      type.</t>

      <t>Before doing so, it's important to understand what they are good for,
      and what's better left to other mechanisms.</t>

      <t>Problem details are not a debugging tool for the underlying
      implementation; rather, they are a way to expose greater detail about
      the HTTP interface itself. New problem types need to carefully consider
      the Security Considerations (<xref target="security-considerations"/>);
      in particular the risk of exposing attack vectors by exposing
      implementation internals through error messages.</t>
      
      <t>Likewise, truly generic problems – i.e., conditions that could
      potentially apply to any resource on the Web – are usually better
      expressed as plain status codes. For example, a "write access
      disallowed" problem is probably unnecessary, since a 403 Forbidden
      status code in response to a PUT request is self-explanatory.</t>

      <t>Finally, an application might have a more appropriate way to carry
      an error in a format that it already defines. Problem details
      are intended to avoid the necessity of establishing new "fault" or
      "error" document formats, not to replace existing domain-specific
      formats.</t>

      <t>That said, it is possible to add support for problem details to
      existing HTTP APIs using HTTP content negotiation (e.g., using the Accept
      request header to indicate a preference for this format; see <xref
      target="RFC7231"/>, Section 5.3.2).</t>

      <t>New problem type definitions MUST document:

      <list style="numbers">
        <t>A type URI (typically, with the "http" scheme),</t>
        <t>A title that appropriately describes it (think short), and</t>
        <t>The HTTP status code for it to be used with.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>Problem type definitions MAY specify the use of the Retry-After
      response header (<xref target="RFC7231"/>, Section 7.1.3) in appropriate
      circumstances.</t>

      <t>A problem's type URI SHOULD resolve to HTML <xref
      target="W3C.REC-html5-20141028"/> documentation that explains how to
      resolve the problem.</t>

      <t>A problem type definition MAY specify additional members on the
      Problem Details object. For example, an extension might use
      typed links <xref target="RFC5988"/> to another resource that can be
      used by machines to resolve the problem.</t>

      <t>If such additional members are defined, their names SHOULD start with
      a letter (ALPHA, as per <xref target="RFC5234"/>, Appendix B.1) and
      SHOULD consist of characters from ALPHA, DIGIT (Ibid.), and "_" (so that
      it can be serialized in formats other than JSON), and SHOULD be three
      characters or longer.</t>

      <section title="Example">

        <t>For example, if you are publishing an HTTP API to your online
        shopping cart, you might need to indicate that the user is out of
        credit (our example from above), and therefore cannot make the
        purchase.</t>

        <t>If you already have an application-specific format that can
        accommodate this information, it's probably best to do that. However,
        if you don't, you might consider using one of the problem details
        formats; JSON if your API is JSON-based, or XML if it uses that
        format.</t>
          
        <t>To do so, you might look for an already-defined type URI that
        suits your purposes. If one is available, you can reuse that URI.</t>
        
        <t>If one isn't available, you could mint and document a new
        type URI (which ought to be under your control and stable over
        time), an appropriate title and the HTTP status code that it will be
        used with, along with what it means and how it should be handled.</t>

        <t>In summary: an instance URI will always identify a specific
        occurrence of a problem. On the other hand, type URIs can be
        reused if an appropriate description of a problem type is already
        available someplace else, or they can be created for new problem
        types.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Pre-Defined Problem Types">
        <t>This specification reserves the use of one URI as a problem type:</t>
        
        <t>The "about:blank" URI <xref target="RFC6694"/>, when used as a
        problem type, indicates that the problem has no additional semantics
        beyond that of the HTTP status code.</t>
        
        <t>When "about:blank" is used, the title SHOULD be the same as the
        recommended HTTP status phrase for that code (e.g., "Not Found" for
        404, and so on), although it MAY be localized to suit client
        preferences (expressed with the Accept-Language request header).</t>
        
        <t>Please note that according to how the "type" member is defined
        (<xref target="members"/>), the "about:blank" URI is the default
        value for that member. Consequently, any problem details object not
        carrying an explicit "type" member implicitly uses this URI.</t>
      </section>

    </section>
    
      
            
		<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

        <t>When defining a new problem type, the information included must be
        carefully vetted. Likewise, when actually generating a problem –
        however it is serialized – the details given must also be
        scrutinized.</t>
         
        <t>Risks include leaking information that can be exploited to
        compromise the system, access to the system, or the privacy of users
        of the system.</t>
		  
        <t>Generators providing links to occurrence information are encouraged
        to avoid making implementation details such as a stack dump available
        through the HTTP interface, since this can expose sensitive details of
        the server implementation, its data, and so on.</t>
            
        <t>The "status" member duplicates the information available in the
        HTTP status code itself, thereby bringing the possibility of
        disagreement between the two. Their relative precedence is not clear,
        since a disagreement might indicate that (for example) an intermediary
        has modified the HTTP status code in transit. As such, those defining
        problem types as well as generators and consumers of problems need to
        be aware that generic software (such as proxies, load balancers,
        firewalls, virus scanners) are unlikely to know of or respect the
        status code conveyed in this member.</t>

		</section>

		<section title="IANA Considerations">

		  <t>This specification defines two new Internet media types
		    <xref target="RFC6838"/>:</t>

      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Type name: application
   Subtype name: problem+json
   Required parameters: None
   Optional parameters: None; unrecognised parameters 
                        should be ignored
   Encoding considerations: Same as [RFC7159]
   Security considerations: see [this document]
   Interoperability considerations: None.
   Published specification: [this document]
   Applications that use this media type: HTTP
   Additional information:
     Magic number(s): n/a
     File extension(s): n/a
     Macintosh file type code(s): n/a
   Person & email address to contact for further information:
     Mark Nottingham <mnot@mnot.net>
   Intended usage: COMMON
   Restrictions on usage: None.
   Author: Mark Nottingham <mnot@mnot.net>
   Change controller: IESG
]]></artwork></figure>

      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Type name: application
   Subtype name: problem+xml
   Required parameters: None
   Optional parameters: None; unrecognized parameters 
                        should be ignored
   Encoding considerations: Same as [RFC7303]
   Security considerations: see [this document]
   Interoperability considerations: None.
   Published specification: [this document]
   Applications that use this media type: HTTP
   Additional information:
     Magic number(s): n/a
     File extension(s): n/a
     Macintosh file type code(s): n/a
   Person & email address to contact for further information:
     Mark Nottingham <mnot@mnot.net>
   Intended usage: COMMON
   Restrictions on usage: None.
   Author: Mark Nottingham <mnot@mnot.net>
   Change controller: IESG
]]></artwork></figure>

		</section>
      
		<section title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>The authors would like to thank 
        Jan Algermissen,
        Mike Amundsen,
        Subbu Allamaraju,
        Roy Fielding,
        Eran Hammer,
        Sam Johnston,
        Mike McCall,
        Julian Reschke, and
        James Snell
			for review of this specification.
			</t>
		</section>

	</middle>

	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			&rfc2119;
			&rfc7230;
      &rfc7231;
			&rfc3986;
			&rfc7159;
			&rfc5234;
      &xml;
		</references>

      <references title="Informative References">
        <reference anchor="ISO-19757-2">
          <front>
            <title>Information Technology --- Document Schema Definition Languages (DSDL) --- Part 2: Grammar-based Validation --- RELAX NG</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2003"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="19757-2"/>
        </reference>
        &rfc7303;
        &rfc5988;
        &rfc4918;
        &rfc6694;
        &rfc6838;
        &html;
        &rdfa;
      </references>

<section anchor="xml-syntax" title="HTTP Problems and XML">
   
   <t>Some HTTP-based APIs use XML <xref
   target="W3C.REC-xml-20081126"/> as their primary format convention. Such
   APIs can express problem details using the format defined in this
   appendix.</t>
      
   <t>The OPTIONAL RELAX NG schema <xref target="ISO-19757-2"/>
   for the XML format is:</t>
      
<figure><artwork type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax">&problem-schema;</artwork></figure>

   <t>The media type for this format is "application/problem+xml".</t>
   
   <t>Extension arrays and objects can be serialized into the XML format by
   considering an element containing a child or children to represent an
   object, except for elements that contain only child element(s) named 'i',
   which are considered arrays. For example, an alternate version of the
   example above would appear in XML as:</t>
      
     <figure><artwork type="message/http; msgtype=&#34;response&#34;"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 403 Forbidden
Content-Type: application/problem+xml
Content-Language: en

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<problem xmlns="urn:ietf:rfc:XXXX">
  <type>https://example.com/probs/out-of-credit</type>
  <title>You do not have enough credit.</title>
  <detail>Your current balance is 30, but that costs 50.</detail>
  <instance>
    https://example.net/account/12345/msgs/abc
  </instance>
  <balance>30</balance>
  <accounts>
    <i>https://example.net/account/12345</i>
    <i>https://example.net/account/67890</i>
  </accounts>
</problem>]]></artwork></figure>

  <t>Note that this format uses an XML Namespace. This is primarily to allow
    embedding it into other XML-based formats; it does not imply that it can or should be extended
    with elements or attributes in other namespaces. The RELAX NG schema explicitly only
    allows elements from the one namespace used in the XML format. Any
    extension arrays and objects MUST be serialized into XML markup using only that
    namespace.</t>

</section>

   <section title="Using Problem Details with Other Formats">
     
     <t>In some situations, it can be advantageous to embed Problem Details in
     formats other than those described here. For example, an API that uses
     HTML <xref target="W3C.REC-html5-20141028"/> might want to also use
     HTML for expressing its problem details.</t>

     <t>Problem details can be embedded in other formats by either
     encapsulating one of the existing serializations (JSON or XML) into that
     format, or by translating the model of a Problem Detail (as specified in
     <xref target="problem-json"/>) into the format's conventions.</t>

     <t>For example, in HTML, a problem could be embedded by encapsulating
     JSON in a script tag:</t>

     <figure><artwork type="example"><![CDATA[
       <script type="application/problem+json">
         {
          "type": "https://example.com/probs/out-of-credit",
          "title": "You do not have enough credit.",
          "detail": "Your current balance is 30, but that costs 50.",
          "instance": "/account/12345/msgs/abc",
          "balance": 30,
          "accounts": ["/account/12345",
                       "/account/67890"]
         }
       </script>
]]></artwork></figure>

     <t>or by inventing a mapping into RDFa <xref
     target="W3C.REC-rdfa-core-20130822"/>.</t>

     <t>This specification does not make specific recommendations regarding
     embedding Problem Details in other formats; the appropriate way to embed
     them depends both upon the format in use and application of that
     format.</t>
     
   </section>
	  
	</back>
	

</rfc>
