<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../xml2rfc/rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM '../bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>      
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-http-portal-00" category="info">
   <front>
      <title abbrev="HTTP Captive Portals">Considerations for Captive Portals in HTTP</title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
         <organization></organization>
         <address>       
            <email>mnot@mnot.net</email> 
            <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>       
         </address>
      </author>
      <date year="2010"/>
      <abstract>
         <t>"Captive portals" are a commonly-deployed means of obtaining
         access credentials and/or payment for a network. This memo discusses
         issues of their use for HTTP applications, and proposes one possible
         mitigation strategy.</t>
         <t>This memo should be discussed on the ietf-http-wg@w3.org mailing list,
            although it is not a work item of the HTTPbis WG.</t>
      </abstract>
   </front>

   <middle>

      <section title="Introduction">
      
         <t>It has become common for networks to require authentication,
         payment and/or acceptance of terms of service before granting access.
         Typically, this occurs when accessing "public" networks such as those
         in hotels, trains, conference centres and similar networks.</t>
      
         <t>While there are several potential means of providing credentials
         to a network, these are not yet universally supported, and in some
         instances the network administrator requires that information (e.g.,
         terms of service, login information) be displayed to end users.</t>
      
         <t>In such cases, it has become widespread practice to use a "captive
         portal" that diverts HTTP requests to the administrator's web page.
         Once the user has satisfied requirements (e.g., for payment,
         acceptance of terms), the diversion is ended and "normal" access to
         the network is allowed.</t>
      
         <t>Typically, this diversion is accomplished by one of several
         possible techniques; 
            <list style="symbols">
               <t>IP interception - all requests on port 80 are intercepted
               and send to to portal.</t>
               <t>HTTP redirects - all requests on port 80 are intercepted and
               an HTTP redirect to the portal's URL is returned.</t>
               <t>DNS interception - all DNS lookups return the portal's IP
               address.</t>
            </list> 
         </t>
      
         <t>In each case, the intent is that users connecting to the network
         will open a Web browser and see the portal.</t>
      
         <t>This memo examines the HTTP-related issues that these techniques
         raise, and proposes a potential mitigation strategy.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="HTTP Issues Encountered">

         <t>Since clients cannot differentiate between a portal's response and
         that of the HTTP server that they intended to communicate with, a
         number of issues arise.</t>
         
          <t>One example is the "favicon.ico" <eref
         target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Favicon"/> commonly used by
         browsers to identify the site being accessed. If the favicon for a
         given site is fetched from a captive portal instead of the intended
         site (e.g., because the user is unauthenticated), it will often
         "stick" in the browser's cache (most implementations cache favicons
         aggressively) beyond the portal session, so that it seems as if the
         portal's favicon has "taken over" the legitimate site.</t>
         
          <t>Another browser-based issue comes about when P3P <eref
         target="http://www.w3.org/TR/P3P/"/> is supported. Depending on how
         it is implemented, it's possible a browser might interpret a portal's
         response for the p3p.xml file as the server's, resulting in the
         privacy policy (or lack thereof) advertised by the portal being
         interpreted as applying to the intended site. Other Web-based
         protocols such as WebFinger <eref
         target="http://code.google.com/p/webfinger/wiki/WebFingerProtocol"/>,
         CORS <eref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/cors/"/> and OAuth <eref
         target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-v2"/> may also be
         vulnerable to such issues.</t>
         
          <t>Although HTTP is most widely used with Web browsers, a growing
         number of non-browsing applications use it as a substrate protocol.
         For example, WebDAV <eref
         target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4918"/> and CalDAV <eref
         target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4791.txt"/> both use HTTP as the
         basis (for network filesystem access and calendaring, respectively).
         Using these applications from behind a captive portal can result in
         spurious errors being presented to the user, and might result in
         content corruption, in extreme cases.</t>
         
          <t>Similarly, other non-browser applications using HTTP can be
         affected as well; e.g., widgets <eref
         target="http://www.w3.org/TR/widgets/"/>, software updates, and other
         specialised software such as Twitter clients and the iTunes Music
         Store.</t>
         
          <t>It should be noted that it's sometimes believed that using HTTP
         redirection to direct traffic to the portal addresses these issues.
         However, since many of these uses "follow" redirects, this is not a
         good solution.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Proposal">
      
         <t>The heart of the issues seen is that the client doesn't understand
         that a response from the portal does not represent the requested
         resource.</t>
            
         <t>As such, the response needs to indicate that it is
         non-authoritative.</t>
            
         <t>In HTTP, response status codes indicate the type of response, and
         therefore defining a new one is the most appropriate way to do this.
         Status codes are divided into general classes;
            <list>
               <t>1xx - Informational</t>
               <t>2xx - Successful</t>
               <t>3xx - Redirection</t>
               <t>4xx - Client errors</t>
               <t>5xx - Server errors</t>
            </list>
         </t>
         
         <t>Although it's common for captive portals to use redirection status
         codes, defining a new 3xx code for them isn't practical; current
         implementations won't recognise the new status code, and therefore
         won't follow it.</t>

         <t>Error status codes, on the other hand, have a nice property in
         that browsers will generally display the response content if they
         don't understand the status code. The one exception to this is
         Internet Explorer, which will display a "friendly" message if the
         response body is too small; however, this is easy enough to work
         around, by padding the response message as necessary.</t>
         
         <t>HTTP defines 4xx status codes as those where the error lies in the
         client; i.e., the client shouldn't retry the same request without
         changing something. This is arguably more appropriate than using a
         5xx error, where the error is said to lie in the server's area of
         responsibility, because clients might automatically retry a request
         upon seeing a 5xx error.</t>
         
         <t>In fact, there's already an existing status code with similar (but
         not quite suitable) semantics; 407 Proxy Authentication Required.
         What's needed is a new status code with the semantics of "Network
         Authentication Required."</t>

         <t>As such, this memo proposes (but does not yet define) using a new
         HTTP response status code in the 4xx range with the semantics
         "Network Authentication Required" to mitigate the risks of captive
         portals.</t>
      
         <t>Captive portals that deploy this status code will return it for
         all requests other than those to the actual portal resources (e.g.,
         images). Clients that are unaware of the specific semantics of the
         new status code will fall back to treating it as a generic 400 error,
         and browsers will display the portal page to users.</t>
         
         <t>Note that this would make the HTTP redirection technique described
         above obsolete; the portal page would be served directly with the new
         status code.</t>
            
      </section>
      
      <section title="What about Non-HTTP Applications and Techniques?">
         
         <t>This memo does not address non-HTTP applications, such as IMAP,
         POP, or even TLS-encapsulated HTTP. Since captive portals almost
         always target Web browsers (has anyone ever seen one that inserts an
         e-mail into your inbox asking you to authenticate?), this is
         appropriate.</t>
         
         <t>Instead, it is anticipated that well-behaved portals will block
         all non-HTTP ports (especially port 443) until the user has
         successfully authenticated.</t>
            
         <t>Overall, there may also be an interesting discussion to be had
         about improving network access methods to the point where a user
         interface can be presented for the same purposes, without resorting
         to intercepting HTTP traffic. However, since such a mechanism would
         by necessity require modifying the network stack and operating system
         of the client, this memo takes a more modest approach.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations">
         <t>This memo does not (yet) define any protocol elements, and
         therefore does not (yet) have any security considerations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations">
         <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
      </section>

   </middle>

   <back>

      <section title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>The author takes all responsibility for errors and omissions.</t>
      </section>
   </back>
</rfc>
