<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="full2026" docName="draft-nottingham-surrogates-01">

<front> 

<title abbrev="Surrogate Requirements">Requirements for Surrogates in the
HTTP</title>

<author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
<organization>Akamai Technologies</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Suite 703, 1400 Fashion Island Bvld</street>
<city>San Mateo</city> <region>CA</region> <code>94404</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<email>mnot@akamai.com</email>
<uri>http://www.akamai.com/</uri>
</address>
</author>

<date month="August" year="2000" />
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>surrogate</keyword>
<keyword>gateway</keyword>
<keyword>proxy</keyword>
<keyword>cache</keyword>
<keyword>HTTP</keyword>

<abstract> 

<t>This document states requirements for HTTP surrogates, also known as
reverse proxies and Web accelerators.</t>

<vspace blankLines="100"/></abstract> 

</front>



<middle>

<section title="Introduction"> 

<t>The WREC Taxonomy document <xref target="wrec_tax"/> defines a surrogate
as:</t>

<figure>
<artwork>
    A gateway co-located with an origin server, or at a different
    point in the network, delegated the authority to operate on
    behalf of, and typically working in close co-operation with,
    one or more origin servers. Responses are typically delivered
    from an internal cache.

    Surrogates may derive cache entries from the origin server or
    from another of the origin server's delegates. In some cases a
    surrogate may tunnel such requests.

    Where close co-operation between origin servers and surrogates
    exists, this enables modifications of some protocol
    requirements, including the Cache-Control directives in [1].
    Such modifications have yet to be fully specified.

    Devices commonly known as "reverse proxies" and "(origin)
    server accelerators" are both more properly defined as
    surrogates.
</artwork>
</figure>

<t>This document expands on this definition, expresses modified HTTP
requirements for surrogates (such as the Cache-Control directives
referenced), and clarifies the role of surrogates in the network.</t> 

<t>Other documents may express a framework for common intermediate functions
such as administration, authentication, reporting, and service extensions.
Such functions are out of scope in this document.</t>

<t>Additionally, some enhancements may provide optional, enhanced mechanisms
(such as improved coherence) unique to surrogates. This document is not
meant to preclude standardization of such enhancements.</t>


  <section title="Requirements">
  <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
  "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
  document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
  target="requirements">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

  <t>An implementation is not compliant if it fails to satisfy one or more
  of the MUST or REQUIRED level requirements. An implementation that
  satisfies all the MUST or REQUIRED level and all the SHOULD level
  requirements is said to be "unconditionally compliant"; one that satisfies
  all the MUST level requirements but not all the SHOULD level requirements is
  said to be "conditionally compliant".</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Terminology"> 
  <t>This document uses terms defined and explained in the <xref
  target="wrec_tax">WREC Taxonomy</xref>, and the <xref target="HTTP">HTTP/1.1
  specification</xref>. The reader is expected to be familiar with both.</t>

  </section>

</section>

<section title="Overview of Demand-Driven Surrogate Origin Servers">

  <section title="Uses and Characteristics">

	<t>Typically, surrogates can be characterized by their operation on
	behalf of origin servers, their appearance as an origin server from the
	client's point of view, and the use of the HTTP to transfer objects
	between the surrogate and the master origin server. As noted, they can
	and often do implement a cache.</t>

	<t>In normal operation, surrogates are deployed and maintained by (or on
	behalf of) the publisher of a Web site, rather than directly for end
	users (as a proxy would be). This is often done for a number of reasons,
	including (a non-exhaustive list):</t>

	<list style="symbols"> 
	
		<t>Reduction of load on the master origin server</t>
		
		<t>Reduction ("flattening") of network traffic to the master origin
		server</t>
		
		<t>Distribution of objects, in order to improve perceived latency by
		storing them closer to end users</t>
		
		<t>Increased security, by forcing clients to communicate through an
		intermediate</t>

		<t>Introduction of transcoding or other value-added services
		(possibly reducing semantic transparency)</t>

	</list>

	<t>Surrogate deployments may vary in several ways, including:</t>

	<list style="symbols">

		<t>Proximity - surrogates may be deployed close to the master origin
		server to reduce load on it, or near end users to reduce network
		traffic and improve perceived latency.</t>

		<t>Selection of surrogate objects - entire Web sites may be routed
		through surrogates, or a subset of a site's objects may be nominated
		for publication through them, depending on the effect desired, and
		the nature of the surrogate.</t>		
		
		<t>Number of surrogates - surrogates may be deployed in any number. 
		Localized surrogates may use any of a number of mechanisms to
		distribute requests between them, while distributed surrogates
		usually use wide-area DNS load balancing.</t>

		<t>Number of master origin servers - a surrogate may be configured
		to accept traffic for multiple master origin servers, identifying
		the appropriate master through examination of request
		characteristics (such as Host header or Request-URI).</t>
	
		<t>Directing traffic to the surrogate - any number of mechanisms may
		be used to distribute requests between multiple surrogates,
		including DNS or BGP manipulation, Layer 4, Layer 7 or "Content
		Aware" switching[13], and reference modification.</t>

	</list>
	
  </section title="Uses and Characteristics">

  <section title="General Operation">

	<section title="Configuration">

	<t>In order to accept and properly handle requests on behalf of a master
	origin server, a surrogate needs to be aware of the master's identity,
	and the profile of traffic that will be served on its behalf.</t>
	
	<t>Additionally, [close relationship, opportunities, out of scope]</t>
	
	</section title="Configuration">

	<section title="Request Handling">

    <t>A surrogate is configured to forward traffic to a master origin server,
    so that the hostname of the surrogate may be used in published URLs.</t>

    <t>A surrogate MAY be configured to forward traffic to multiple master
    origin servers by using the Host request header to differentiate
    requests.  In this scenario, requests without a Host header SHOULD be
    responded to with a 502 Gateway Error status code.</t>
   
    <t> Surrogates MUST accept <xref target="URI">Absolute-URI</xref> as well
    as Relative-URI requests and forward them to the master origin server, as
    configured. They MUST NOT forward Absolute-URI requests to origin servers
    that they have not been configured to serve.</t>

	</section title="Request Handling">

  </section title="General Operation">

</section title="Overview">


<section title="Specific Requirements">

  <t>Requirements for a surrogate are the same as those for a gateway or
  proxy in <xref target="HTTP">HTTP/1.1</xref>, except as noted.</t>

  <section title="Protocol Version Interpretation">

  <t>Implementations MUST satisfy the requirements of <xref
  target="http-version">RFC 2145</xref>, including those specific to
  proxies.</t>

  </section>

  <section title="Methods"> 
  
  <t>A surrogate MUST NOT accept CONNECT requests, or forward them to a
  master origin server.</t>
  
  <t>TRACE requests MAY be responded to as if max-forwards=0 were present,
  to keep the surrogate's relationship with the origin server private.</t>
  
  </section>

  <section title="Status Codes">

	<t>Surrogates SHOULD NOT change the semantics of 4xx and 5xx series
	status codes obtained from origin servers. However, these responses MAY
	be cached for a short period (sometimes known as 'negative
	caching').</t>

	<t>Surrogates SHOULD return a 502 Bad Gateway error when
	surrogate-specific directives are incomplete, contradict themselves or
	don't parse correctly.</t>
  
	<t>A 504 Gateway Timeout response SHOULD be sent under any of the
	following conditions:</t>

	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>DNS failure when resolving the origin server</t>
	  <t>no route to origin server</t>
 	  <t>refused connection to origin server</t>
 	  <t>connection timeout to origin server</t>
	</list>
 
	<t>However, a caching surrogate MAY be configured to use a cached
	resource, a different resource, or redirect to a different location
	under these conditions.</t>

  </section>

  <section title="Cache Correctness">

	<t>The RECOMMENDED mechanism for assuring object freshness on caching
	surrogates is use of Surrogate-Control request and response headers.</t>
	
	<t>Caching surrogates MAY be configured to fall back to HTTP freshness
	mechanisms (e.g., Expires and Cache-Control response headers), if
	surrogate-specific mechanisms are not used.</t>
	
	<t>Caching surrogates MAY also be configured to use a heuristic
	freshness algorithm, as in the HTTP, to ensure coherence if no other
	freshness information is available.</t>

  </section>

  <section title="End-to-End Headers">  

    <section title="Cache-Control Request Header">

	<t>Cache-Control headers in requests MUST NOT be honored by
	caching surrogates.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Cache-Control Response Header"> 
    
    <t>By default, Cache-Control headers in responses from a master origin
    server SHOULD NOT be honored by caching surrogates, and SHOULD be
    forwarded to clients.</t>
    
    <t>Caching surrogates SHOULD be able to be configured to honor
	Cache-Control response headers when surrogate-specific directives are
	not used.</t>
    
    </section>

	<section title="Host"> 
	
	<t>Surrogates MUST replace any Host header in requests with the identity
	of the appropriate master origin server before forwarding it.</t>
	
	</section>

	<section title="Pragma">
	
	<t>Caching surrogates SHOULD NOT honor Pragma request directives.</t>
	
	</section>

    <section title="Server">
	
	<t>Surrogates MAY set their own Server response header, replacing any
    present.</t>
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="Via">

    <t>Surrogates SHOULD append a Via header to requests, as outlined in
    <xref target="HTTP">RFC2616</xref>. Surrogates MAY append or
    strip Via response headers, depending on their configuration.</t>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section title="Surrogate-Control HTTP Headers">

	<t>Surrogate-specific HTTP headers allow specification of cache
	directives in requests or responses to the surrogate. Similar to
	Cache-Control headers, they allow separation of coherence from</t>

	<t>Surrogate-Specific headers MUST be consumed before forwarding a
	request or response.</t>

	<section title="Surrogate-Control Request Header">

	<t>Surrogate-Control request directives have similar semantics and
	effects as Cache-Control request headers. Defined directives are:
	</t>

	<t><list style="hanging">
	  <t hangText="no-cache"><vspace/>
		Has same meaning as a Cache-Control: max-age request directive to a 
		proxy.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="only-if-cached"><vspace/>
		Has same meaning as a Cache-Control: only-if-cached request directive 
		to a proxy.
	  </t>
	</list></t>

	<t>Surrogates MAY require some form of client authentication when
	honoring Surrogate-Control response directives.</t>

	</section>

    <section title="Surrogate-Control Response Header">

	<t>[targeting the device?]</t>

	<t>Surrogate-Control response directives have similar semantics and
	effects as Cache-Control response headers. Defined directives are:
	</t>
	
	<t><list style="hanging">
	  <t hangText="max-age"><vspace/>
		Has same meaning as a Cache-Control: max-age response directive to a
		proxy.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="no-cache"><vspace/>
		Has same meaning as a Cache-Control: no-cache response directive to a 
		proxy.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="must-revalidate"><vspace/>
	    Has same meaning as a Cache-Control: must-revalidate response
		directive to a proxy.
	  </t>
	</list></t>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section title="Surrogate-Generated Headers">

	<section title="Surrogate-Client Request Header">

	<t>Surrogates SHOULD be capable of adding a header that denotes the
	client which requested the object.</t>

    </section>
	
	<section title="Surrogate-For Response Header">
	<t>Surrogates MAY add a response header which denotes the name of the
	master origin server, if it is not obvious in the Request-URI, in order
	to enable third parties to identify the source of the content.</t>
	</section>
  
  </section>


</section>


<section title="Security Considerations">

  <t>[Because close relationship, higher security necessary]</t>

  <section title="Knowledge of Surrogate/Origin Relationship">
  <t>It may or may not be necessary to hide the relationship between
  surrogates and origin servers, depending on the nature of their use.</t>

  <t>Surrogates SHOULD allow configuration to accomplish this. 
  Specifically, this includes all HTTP headers that identify responses as
  coming from a surrogate, TRACE requests, and error responses and warnings
  that identify the surrogate.</t>
  
  </section>

</section>

</middle>




<back>
<references>

<reference anchor="wrec_tax">
<front>
  <title>Internet Web Replication and Caching Taxonomy</title>
  <author initials="I." surname="Cooper" fullname="Ian Cooper">
    <organization>Mirror Image</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="I." surname="Melve" fullname="Ingrid Melve">
    <organization>UNINETT</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="G." surname="Tomlinson" fullname="Gary Tomlinson">
    <organization abbrev="Novell">Novell Inc.</organization>
  </author>
  <date month="November" year="1999"/>
</front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="HTTP">
<front>
  <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP/1.1</title>
  <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding">
    <organization abbrev="UC Irvine">Information and Computer Science, 
    University of California, Irvine</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="J." surname="Gettys" fullname="James Gettys">
    <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="J. C." surname="Mogul" fullname="Jeffrey C. Mogul">
    <organization abbrev="Compaq">Western Research Laboratory, Compaq Computer 
    Corporation</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="H." surname="Frystyk" fullname="Henrik Frystyk Nielsen">
    <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
    <organization abbrev="Xerox">Xerox Corporation</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="P." surname="Leach" fullname="Paul J. Leach">
    <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft Corporation</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee">
    <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
  </author>
  <date month="June" year="1999"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2616"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="URI">
<front>
<title>Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee">
<organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>MIT Laboratory for Computer Science</street>
<street>545 Technology Square</street>
<city>Cambridge</city> <region>MA</region> <code>02139</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 617 253 5702</phone>
<facsimile>+1 617 258 8682</facsimile>
<email>timbl@w3.org</email>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="R.T." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding">
<organization abbrev="UCI">University of California, Irvine</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Department of Information and Computer Science</street>
<street>University of California, Irvine</street>
<city>Irvine</city> <region>CA</region> <code>92697-3425</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 949 824 7403</phone>
<facsimile>+1 949 824 1715</facsimile>
<email>fielding@ics.uci.edu</email>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
<organization>Xerox PARC</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>3333 Coyote Hill Road</street>
<city>Palo Alto</city> <region>CA</region> <code>94304</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 650 812 4365</phone>
<facsimile>+1 650 812 4333</facsimile>
<email>masinter@parc.xerox.com</email>
</address>
</author>
<date month="August" year="1998" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2396" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="requirements">
<front>
  <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
  <author initials="S." surname="Bradner">
  <organization></organization>
  </author>
  <date month="March" year="1997"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="http-version">
<front>
  <title>Use and Intepretation of HTTP Version Numbers</title>
  <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding">
    <organization abbrev="UC Irvine">Information and Computer Science, 
    University of California, Irvine</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="J." surname="Gettys" fullname="James Gettys">
    <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="J. C." surname="Mogul" fullname="Jeffrey C. Mogul">
    <organization abbrev="Compaq">Western Research Laboratory, Compaq Computer 
    Corporation</organization>
  </author>
  <author initials="H." surname="Frystyk" fullname="Henrik Frystyk Nielsen">
    <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
  </author>
  <date month="May" year="1997"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2145"/>
</reference>

</references>



<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>The author gratefully acknowledges the contributions of:
Ted Hardie,
John Dilley,
John Martin,
Peter Danzig,
and, 
Chuck Neerdaels.
</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
