<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../xml2rfc/rfc2629.dtd" [
   <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM '../bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc2616 SYSTEM '../bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY p1-messaging SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging-12.xml'>
   <!ENTITY p6-cache SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-httpbis-p6-cache-12.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-http-pipeline-02" category="info">

   <front>
      <title abbrev="HTTP Pipelining Enhancements">Making HTTP Pipelining Usable on the Open Web</title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
         <organization></organization>
         <address>       
            <email>mnot@mnot.net</email> 
            <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>
         </address>
      </author>
      <date year="2011"/>
      <abstract>
         <t>Pipelining was added to HTTP/1.1 as a means of improving the
         performance of persistent connections in common cases. While it is
         deployed in some limited circumstances, it is not widely used by
         clients on the open Internet. This memo suggests some measures
         designed to make it more possible for clients to reliably and safely
         use HTTP pipelining in these situations.</t>
      </abstract>
   </front>

   <middle>

      <section title="Introduction">

         <t>HTTP/1.1 <xref target="RFC2616"/> added pipelining -- that is, the
         ability to have more than one outstanding request on a connection at
         a particular time -- to improve performance when many requests need
         to be made (e.g., when an HTML page references several images).</t>

         <t>Although not usable in all circumstances (POST and other
         non-idempotent requests cannot be pipelined), for the common case of
         Web browsing, pipelining seems at first like a broadly useful
         improvement -- especially since the number of TCP connections
         browsers and servers can use for a given interaction is limited, and
         especially where there is noticeable latency present.</t>

         <t>Indeed, in constrained applications of HTTP such as Subversion,
         pipelining has been shown to improve end-user perceived latency
         considerably.</t>

         <t>However, pipelining is not broadly used on the Web today; while
         most (but not all) servers and intermediaries support pipelining (to
         varying degrees), only one major Web browser uses it in its default
         configuration, and that implementation is reported to use a number of
         proprietary heuristics to determine when it is safe to pipeline.</t>

         <t>This memo characterises issues currently encountered in the use of
         HTTP pipelining, and suggests mechanisms that are designed to make 
         its use more reliable and safe for browsers.</t>
         
         <t>Note that this memo does not suggest drastic changes to HTTP, nor
         does it require that intermediaries change to better support
         pipelining. Instead, it takes the position that removing the
         responsibility for making pipelining decisions from browsers, as well
         as reduce associated risks for browsers, we make it more likely that
         browsers will support it.</t>

         <t>This memo should be discussed on the ietf-http-wg@w3.org mailing
         list, although it is not a work item of the HTTPbis WG. Reviewers
         are encouraged to pay particular attention to items marked 
         FEEDBACK.</t>

      </section>
      
      <section title="Requirements">
         <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
         NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
         this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
         target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="HTTP Pipelining Issues">

         <t>Anecdotal evidence suggests there are a number of reasons why
            clients don't use HTTP pipelining by default. Briefly, they are:
            
            <list style="numbers">

               <t>Balking Servers - server implementations can stall pipelined 
               requests, or close their connection when the client attempts to 
               pipeline. This is one of the most commonly cited problems.</t>

               <t>Confused Servers - a few server implementations can respond 
               to pipelined requests in the wrong order. Even fewer might 
               corrupt the actual responses. Because this has security
               implications (consider multiple users behind such a proxy, or 
               multiple tabs in a browser), this is very concerning.</t>

               <t>Head-of-Line Blocking - Clients don't have enough 
               information about what is useful to pipeline. A given response 
               may take an inordinate amount of time to generate, and/or be 
               large enough to block subsequent responses. Clients who
               pipeline may face worse performance if they stack requests
               behind such an expensive request.</t>

            </list>
         </t>

         <t>Note that here, "servers" can also include proxies and other
         intermediaries, including so-called "transparent" proxies (also 
         known as intercepting proxies).</t>
         
         <t>The remainder of this memo proposes mechanisms that can be used
         to mitigate one or more of these problems; not all of them will
         survive discussion and implementation.</t>

      </section>


      <section title="Blacklisting Origin Servers">
        
        <t>To address balking and confused origin servers, a client
          SHOULD maintain a blacklist of origins that it does not attempt
          pipelining with.</t>
          
        <t>Such a blacklist MAY be populated by external information (e.g., 
          a list of known-bad servers maintained by the browser vendor), and
          when pipelining has been detected to fail to the origin.</t>

      </section>

      
      <section title="Discovering Faulty Proxies">
      
         <t>When a balking or confused server is a proxy, pipelining won't
         work for any requests sent through it. Therefore, clients SHOULD
         test the network for such proxies periodically.</t>

         <t>This can be done by sending pipelined requests to a
         known server, and examining the responses for errors.</t>
            
         <t>For example, if the ExampleBrowser implementation wishes to probe
         for faulty proxies, it can send a series of requests to
         "http://browser.example.com/pipeline-test/" and subresources. If the
         bodies of the resulting responses deviate from those it expects in
         any way, it is reasonable to assume that a faulty proxy is present,
         and pipelining SHOULD NOT be used through it.</t>
         
         <t>RECOMMENDED measures in such tests include:</t>
         
         <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>Sending a non-trivial number of pipelined requests (e.g., 10)</t>
           <t>Sending multiple pipelined requests in the same packet</t>
           <t>Inserting request bodies with various sizes</t>
           <t>Assuring that caching is disabled, so that requests are end-to-end</t>
           <t>Sending a variety of responses types that includes 100 and 304 responses</t>
           <t>Examining responses to assure that they all appear in the correct order</t>
           <t>Examining received requests and responses to assure that they aren't unduly modified</t>
         </list></t>
         
         <t>These tests SHOULD be performed by clients (both user agent and
           proxy) upon startup, as well as 
           periodically afterwards to assure that a new intercepting proxy 
           hasn't been interposed. They MAY be performed after a pipelining
           problem is detected, to determine whether the issue is proxy-
           related.</t>
         
         <t>See <eref target="https://github.com/mnot/pipeline-surveyor" /> 
         for an example implementation.</t>
      
      </section>


      <section title="Correlating Responses">
                   
         <t>HTTP relies on the context of the connection to associate a given
         request with its intended response. In HTTP/1.0, this was a
         reasonable assumption, since only one request could be outstanding at
         a given time, and each request had exactly one response.</t>
       
         <t>HTTP/1.1 made associating requests and responses in a given
         connection more complex (and therefore fault-prone). Not only does
         pipelining mean that multiple requests can be outstanding, but also
         the 1xx series of response status codes introduce the possibility of
         multiple response messages (syntactically) being associated with a
         single request.</t>

         <t>To improve the client's ability to correlate responses with their
         requests and identify confused origin and proxy servers (as well as
         serve other potential use cases), this memo introduces the
         "Assoc-Req" response header field.</t>
       
<figure><artwork>
Assoc-Req   = "Assoc-Req" ":" OWS Assoc-Req-v
Assoc-Req-v = Method SP absolute-URI
</artwork></figure>

         <t>The field-value of the Assoc-Req header field is the method and
         effective request URI of the request associated with the response
         that it appears in. The URI used MUST be generated using the
         algorithm for finding the Effective Request URI in <xref
         target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging"/>. The header field MUST NOT
         be generated by proxies.</t>
       
         <t>For example, given the following request over port 80:</t>
       
<figure><artwork>
GET /foo?it HTTP/1.1
Host: www.example.com
</artwork></figure>

         <t>the appropriate Assoc-Req header field would be:</t>
       
<figure><artwork>
Assoc-Req: GET http://www.example.com/foo?it
</artwork></figure>
       
         <t>Note that the Assoc-Req header field is not a perfectly reliable
         identifier for the request associated with a response; for example,
         it does not incorporate the selecting headers for content negotiation
         <xref target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-p6-cache"/>, nor does it
         differentiate request bodies, when present. However, for the purposes
         of making pipelining more reliable, it is sufficient.</t>
       
         <t>A client wishing to use the Assoc-Req response header field to aid
         in identifying problems in pipelining can compare its values to those
         of the request that it believes it to be associated with (based upon
         HTTP's message parsing rules, defined in <xref
         target="I-D.ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging"/>). If either the method or
         the URI differ, it indicates that there may be a pipelining-related
         issue, and the origin server (identified by its (host, port) tuple) 
         SHOULD be blacklisted.</t>
         
         <t>A client MAY choose to blacklist any origin server that does not 
           send the Assoc-Req header.</t>

         <t>FEEDBACK: Omitting the URI scheme and authority (i.e., just making
           it the path and query components) would make the header easier to
           generate and avoid some false positives (e.g., when a "reverse 
           proxy" or other URI rewriter is present), but may fail to identify
           cases where two requests are confused (consider requests for 
           "http://example.com/style.css" and 
           "https://foo.example.net/style.css").</t>

      </section>
      
      <section title="Hinting Pipelinable Content">
         
         <t>It's necessary to assist clients in determining what 
         requests are suitable for pipelining, so that the sole responsibility
         for deciding what and when to pipeline isn't theirs. This can be
         done through origin server hinting.</t>
         
         <t>Such hints indicates URLs that, when dereferenced, will
         likely not incur significant latency on the server in generating the
         response, nor significant latency on the network in transferring the
         response.</t>
         
         <t>What is "significant" is determined by the server. Clients will
         use these hints to determine what request(s) it is safe to pipeline
         something else after.</t>
            
         <t>For example, if "http://example.com/a" is hinted, a client can be
         more confident pipelining another request (e.g., to
         "http://example.com/b") on the same connection afterwards.</t>
         
         <t>There are several possible ways that content could be hinted, 
           including:
            <list style="symbols"> 

               <t>The "quick" link relation type can 
               appear on individual HTML elements such as "img", "script" and
               "link" to indicate that the link they contain has low overhead.
               </t>
               
               <t>
               A similar link relation could also be used in the HTTP link 
               header to indicate "quick" links within the response in a 
               format-neutral way.</t>
         
               <t>
               A server can indicate that all its resources are suitable
               for pipelining by returning a successful response status code
               (2xx) to requests for the path "/.well-known/pipeline". In the
               future, a format available at this location could give more
               fine-grained information.</t>
               
               <t>
               Client-side APIs (e.g., XmlHttpRequest) can allow callers to 
               indicate how connections are to be used, including aspects
               related to pipelining. Defining this will require further 
               work.</t>
         
            </list>
         </t>
         
         <t>FEEDBACK: thoughts on the suitability of these hinting mechanisms is 
           encouraged, so that the list can eventually be narrowed down.</t>

         <t>A user agent MAY have a policy of only pipelining to hinted resources.</t>
           
      </section>
      
      <section title="Indicating Blocking Responses">
        
        <t>An alternate way to avoid head-of-line blocking is for the origin
          server to aggressively indicate when a request would block.</t>
          
        <t>This can be done by using a new HTTP status code, 430 WOULD BLOCK.</t>
        
        <t>The meaning of "would block" is defined by the server; e.g., it 
          may return this code when the response is known to be over a certain
          size, or when the code to generate the response is known to take
          a long time to execute.</t>
          
        <t>When a client (user agent or intermediary) receives a 430 WOULD
          BLOCK, it SHOULD resubmit the associated request on a new or idle
          connection.</t>
          
        <t>An origin server MUST NOT send a 430 WOULD BLOCK status code to clients
          that do not include a "PWB: 1" (mnemonic: Pipelining Would Block) request
          header. User Agents that support the status code SHOULD send this header, and
          intermediaries that are willing to handle its processing MAY append it to 
          requests that do not already include it.</t>
        
        <t>A cache MUST NOT store a 430 WOULD BLOCK response, and origin servers
          SHOULD mark them as explicitly uncacheable (e.g., with Cache-Control: no-store). 
        </t>
        
        <t>FEEDBACK: This is a relatively new idea; thoughts? In some ways it's
          easier to deploy, but it does add a certain amount of latency to requests that
          block. Theoretically, a Location header could be added to redirect the client
          to a place where the generated response will be waiting (if the blocking is
          caused by server-side think time), but this may be impractical to implement.</t>
        
      </section>
      
      
      <section title="Handling Pipelining Problems">

         <t>Upon encountering an indication of pipelining problems with a
         particular response (e.g., an incorrect Assoc-Req field-value, a
         pipelined response that stalls), user agents SHOULD discard the
         response in question, all subsequent responses on the same
         connection, and close the connection. Unsatisfied requests can be
         resubmitted, without pipelining, and the implementation can choose
         not to use pipelining to the same server in the future (see 
         "Blacklisting Origin Servers").</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations">
         <t>TBD</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations">
         <t>TBD</t>
      </section>

   </middle>

   <back>
      <references title="Normative References">
         &rfc2119; &p1-messaging;
      </references>

      <references title="Informative References">
         &rfc2616; &p6-cache;
      </references>
      
      <section title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>Thanks to 
             Ilya Grigorik, 
             Anirban Kundu,
             Patrick McManus and
             Julian Reschke.
         The author takes all responsibility for errors and
         omissions.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Frequently Asked Questions">

         <t>Isn't full multiplexing better?</t>

         <t>While "full" multiplexing is theoretically better, pipelining --
         once usable -- is adequate for almost all common Web browsing cases.
         Since the browser needs to download HTML first, it has an opportunity
         to receive hints about subsequent requests and pipeline them
         appropriately. Likewise, by far the most common case for multiplexing
         on the Web is when a large number of images and other page assets
         need to be fetched with GET; a perfect use of pipelining, provided
         that the client has enough information to avoid head-of-line
         blocking.</t>
         
         <t>Why not have the client generate a unique request identifier?</t>
         
         <t>While in some ways this would be easier than the approach that the
            Assoc-Req header takes, it would be more difficult to deploy,
            because existing caching proxies wouldn't be able to serve
            the correct identifier when using a cached response.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Changes">
        <t>draft -00 to draft -01:</t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Add guidelines for blacklisting</t>
          <t>Remove advice on signature checking (for now)</t>
          <t>Clarified problem statement</t>
          <t>Rearranged</t>
          <t>Added 430 WOULD BLOCK</t>
        </list></t>

        <t>draft -01 to draft -02:</t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Added client-side API hinting stub.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
   </back>

</rfc>
