<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
   <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rfc5226 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rfc5234 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rfc5246 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rfc6265 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6265.xml'>
   <!ENTITY rfc6454 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6454.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-http-browser-hints-05" category="info">

   <front>
      <title>HTTP Origin and Hop Hints</title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
         <organization></organization>
         <address>
            <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>
            <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>
         </address>
      </author>
      <date year="2013"/>
      <abstract>

         <t>Over time, HTTP clients -- especially Web browsers -- have adapted
         how they use the protocol based upon common server configurations and
         behaviours. While this is necessary in the common case, it can be
         detrimental for performance and interoperability.</t>

         <t>This document establishes a mechanism whereby both origin servers
         and intermediaries can make hints available to clients about their
         preferences and capabilities, without imposing undue overhead on
         their interactions or requiring support for them.</t>

         <t>This is intended to allow clients to safely optimise connections
         to servers.</t>

      </abstract>

      <note title="Note to Readers">
          <t>Feedback for this draft should take place on the
          apps-discuss@ietf.org mailing list <eref
          target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/apps-discuss"/>. </t>
      </note>
   </front>

   <middle>

      <section title="Introduction">

        <t>HTTP <xref target="HTTP-p1"/> clients -- especially browsers --
        typically use hardcoded values or heuristics to determine how they use
        TCP, based on common-case server behaviours and limitations.</t>

        <t>For example, they often send voluminous request headers (e.g., in
        User-Agent and Allow) because they fear that changing those headers'
        values will break some sites that depend upon specific values.</t>

        <t>These conservative behaviours are good for interoperability, but
        potentially bad for performance in certain circumstances.</t>

        <t>This document specifies a mechanism whereby a HTTP server can
        advertise hints for browsers and other clients, so that
        communication with them can be optimised.</t>

        <t>It does so by defining two headers; "OH" (Origin Hints) for
        end-to-end hints from the Origin Server, and "HH" (Hop Hints) for
        hop-by-hop hints from the upstream server (origin or proxy). A
        selection of hints are also defined in this document, and a registry
        is defined to allow future such hints.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Notational Conventions">

        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
        this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

        <t>This document uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) notation
        of <xref target="RFC5234"/>, and explicitly includes the following
        rules from it: ALPHA, DIGIT. Additionally, it uses the list rule
        extension defined in <xref target="HTTP-p1"/>, Appendix B.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Origin Hints" anchor="origin">

        <t>Origin Hints are applicable to all future requests to the origin
        <xref target="RFC6454"/> associated with the response, until they are
        overridden. They are carried in the "OH" header field's value.</t>
        
        <figure><artwork>
OH = #hint
</artwork></figure>

        <t>A hint is considered overridden when an OH header field is seen
        from the same origin that does not contain the hint, or contains a
        different value for the hint.</t>

        <t>Practically speaking, this means that clients MAY cache origin hint
        values indefinitely, updating them when new OH header fields are seen
        from an origin.</t>

        <t>For example, an origin may send an OH header on every response, in
        which case the latest one seen would be the value used, or it could
        send one sporadically (e.g., upon connection), in which case the
        origin hints in effect would be the last one seen by the client.</t>

        <t>Practically speaking, origins that wish to have their hints
        available to clients as soon as possible will send them on every
        response; those that wish to limit the sizes of responses might use
        some other strategy, knowing that clients will eventually cache their
        hints.</t>

      <t>For example:</t>

      <figure><artwork>
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html
OH: a,b=6,c
Content-Length: 1234
Cache-Control: max-age=60

...
</artwork></figure>

      <t>Here, the origin hints "a", "b", and "c" are indicated; the "b" hint
      has a value of "6". If a subsequent message from the same origin
      to the same client were:</t>

      <figure><artwork>
HTTP/1.1 303 See Other
Content-Type: text/html
OH: a,b=2
Content-Length: 1234
Cache-Control: max-age=60

...
</artwork></figure>

      <t>The client would now consider "a" to still be true, whereas the
        value of "b" would be 2, and "c" would be false.</t>

      <t>Origin hints SHOULD NOT be generated by proxy servers.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Hop Hints" anchor="hop">

      <t>Hop Hints are applicable to all future requests on the TCP
      connection they occur upon, until they are overridden. The are carried
      in the "HH" header field's value.</t>

        <figure><artwork>
HH = #hint
</artwork></figure>

      <t>A hint is considered overridden when an HH header field is seen on
      the same connection that does not contain the hint, or contains a
      different value for the hint.</t>

      <t>Typically, a server (whether origin or proxy) will send the HH header
      field on the first response, omitting it from subsequent responses
      unless it wishes to change a value.</t>

      <t>When it occurs in a message, the HH header field MUST be listed in
      the Connection header's field-value.</t>

      <t>For example:</t>

      <figure><artwork>
HTTP/1.1 404 Not Found
Content-Type: text/plain
HH: x,ya
Content-Length: 5678
Connection: HH
Cache-Control: max-age=60

...
</artwork></figure>

      <t>Here, the hop hints "x" and "ya" are indicated.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Hint Syntax" anchor="syntax">

      <t>Both origin hints and hop hints share a common syntax, consisting of
      a string of alphanumeric characters. This form is designed to be compact
      without sacrificing readability.</t>

      <t>Every hint has a case-sensitive hint identifier.</t>

      <figure><artwork>
hint = 1*ALPHA [ "=" 1*DIGIT ]
</artwork></figure>

      <t>Hints are allowed to have a numeric argument. However, wherever
      possible, they are encouraged to be defined as flags (i.e., as a
      hint identifier only), so that the hints don't consume too much
      space in responses.</t>

      <t>Hints can be defined as one of two types:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Boolean - indicated by the presence of the hint identifier. If
          the hint identifier is absent in the last message containing the
          relevant hint header field, it is considered false.</t>
          <t>Numeric - value indicated by the digits after "=", up to the
          first non-digit character.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Note that HTTP/1.1 allows headers with comma-separated values to be
        conveyed using multiple instances of the same header; as a result,
        the hints of a given type (origin or hop) are collected from all
        instances of that header on the message in question before being 
        considered complete.</t>
        
    </section>

    <section title="Pre-defined Hints" anchor="hints">

      <section title="Small Request Headers">

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Hint Name: s</t>
            <t>Hint Type: origin</t>
            <t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that clients
            can omit the Accept and Accept-Charset request headers when
            communicating with the origin, and that they can use a
						shortened version of the User-Agent header.</t>
            <t>Value Type: boolean</t>
            <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>This hint can help reduce request sizes.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Relative Referers">

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Hint Name: r</t>
            <t>Hint Type: origin</t>
            <t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that the origin
 							 prefers a relative URI in the Referer request header.</t>
            <t>Value Type: boolean</t>
            <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>This hint can help reduce request sizes.</t>

      </section>

			<section title="Omitting Cookies">

        <t>
					<list style="symbols">
            <t>Hint Name: c</t>
            <t>Hint Type: origin</t>
						<t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that all cookies
            <xref target="RFC6265"/> can be omitted in requests to the
            origin.</t>
						<t>Value Type: boolean</t>
						<t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
					</list>
				</t>

        <t>This hint can help reduce request sizes.</t>

			</section>

      <section title="Sharing Connections">

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Hint Name: sc</t>
            <t>Hint Type: hop</t>
            <t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that the server
            allows clients to reuse persistent connections keyed by IP
            address, rather than by hostname. Note that all origins that are
            sharing the connection MUST declare this hint for it to be
            used, and if a transport-layer certificate is in use
            (e.g., for TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/>), it MUST be valid
            for all origins.</t>
            <t>Value Type: boolean</t>
            <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
            <t>Specification: [this document]</t>
            <t>Notes: Although it is a Hop Hint, this MUST NOT be set by
              servers other than origins.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>In other words, if both www.example.com and foo.example.org
        resolve to the address 192.0.2.5, and indicate this hint, then
        clients can send a request to www.example.com and then a request to
        foo.example.org on the same TCP connection to that address.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Pipeline Depth">

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Hint Name: p</t>
            <t>Hint Type: hop</t>
            <t>Description: When present, this hint indicates the maximum
            number of pipelined requests per connection that the server would
            like clients to use.</t>
            <t>Value Type: numeric</t>
            <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        </section>

      </section>

      <section title="Security Considerations">
         <t>By their nature, hints are both optional and advisory; clients
           ought to exercise judgement when applying them, as an attacker
           might use a naive implementation to trick the client into 
           generating abnormal traffic. For example, the "p" hint should not
           be the only input into determining how deep to pipeline requests.
           </t>
           
          <t>Hints are also only as secure as the channel they are
            transmitted upon; if HTTP is used in the clear, then hints might
            be observed (which typically is not a great risk), and modified
            (which could be, for a naive client implementation).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations">

       <section title="The OH HTTP Response Header Field">

         <t>This document defines the "OH" HTTP header field, and registers
           it in the Permanent Message Headers registry.</t>

         <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>Header field name: OH</t>
           <t>Applicable protocol: HTTP</t>
           <t>Status: Informational</t>
           <t>Author/Change controller: Mark Nottingham, mnot@mnot.net</t>
           <t>Specification document(s): [this document]</t>
           <t>Related information: for Origin Hints</t>
         </list></t>

       </section>

       <section title="The HH HTTP Response Header Field">

         <t>This document defines the "HH" HTTP header field, and registers
           it in the Permanent Message Headers registry.</t>

         <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>Header field name: HH</t>
           <t>Applicable protocol: HTTP</t>
           <t>Status: Informational</t>
           <t>Author/Change controller: Mark Nottingham, mnot@mnot.net</t>
           <t>Specification document(s): [this document]</t>
           <t>Related information: for Hop Hints</t>
         </list></t>

       </section>


       <section title="The HTTP Hints Registry" anchor="registry">

         <t>This document establishes the HTTP Hints Registry.</t>

         <t>New hints are registered using Expert Review (see
           <xref target="RFC5226"/>), by sending e-mail to <eref
           target="mailto:iana@iana.org"/> (or using other mechanisms, as
           established by IANA).</t>
           
         <t>New hints are expected to be implemented in at least one client in
         common use. The Expert MAY use their judgement in determining what
         "common" is, and when something is considered to be implemented.</t>

         <t>New hints MUST be optional; they cannot place requirements upon
         implementations.</t>

         <t>Specifically, new hints MUST NOT make communication non-conformant
         with HTTP itself; i.e., this is not a mechanism for changing the HTTP
         protocol in incompatible ways. For example, if a hint indicates that
         browsers can compress request headers using GZIP, intermediaries that
         are interposed are likely to fail.</t>

         <t>Registration requests MUST use the following template:</t>

         <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Hint Name: [name of hint]</t>
              <t>Hint Type: ["origin" or "hop"]</t>
              <t>Description: [description of hint]</t>
              <t>Value Type: ["boolean" or "numeric"] </t>
  	          <t>Contact: [e-mail address(es)]</t>
  	          <t>Specification: [optional; reference or URI to more info]</t>
  	          <t>Notes: [optional]</t>
            </list>
          </t>

         <t>The initial contents of the registry are defined in <xref
         target="hints"/>.</t>

       </section>

     </section>

   </middle>

   <back>
      <references title="Normative References">
        &rfc2119; 
        &rfc5234; 
        &rfc6454;

        <reference anchor="HTTP-p1">
          <front>
            <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP/1.1): Message Syntax and Routing</title>
            <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding" role="editor">
              <organization abbrev="Adobe">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
              <address><email>fielding@gbiv.com</email></address>
            </author>
            <author initials="J. F." surname="Reschke" fullname="Julian F. Reschke" role="editor">
              <organization abbrev="greenbytes">greenbytes GmbH</organization>
              <address><email>julian.reschke@greenbytes.de</email></address>
            </author>
            <date month="Feb" year="2013"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging-21;"/>
        </reference>

      </references>

      <references title="Informative References">
         &rfc5226;
         &rfc5246;
         &rfc6265;
      </references>

      <section title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>Thanks to
           Mike Belshe,
           Artur Bergman,
           William Chan,
           Jason Duell,
           Poul-Henning Kamp,
           Anirban Kundu,
           Patrick McManus,
           Ryan Sleevi,
           Steve Souders, and
			     Martin Thompson
           for their suggestions and feedback.
          </t>
         <t>The author takes all responsibility for errors and
         omissions.</t>
      </section>

   </back>

</rfc>
