<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
   <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc2616 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc4627 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4627.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5226 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5246 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc5785 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5785.xml'>  
   <!ENTITY rfc6265 SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6265.xml'>  
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-nottingham-http-browser-hints-04" category="info">

   <front>
      <title>HTTP Browser Hints</title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="Mark Nottingham">
         <organization></organization>
         <address>       
            <email>mnot@mnot.net</email> 
            <uri>http://www.mnot.net/</uri>
         </address>
      </author>
      <date year="2012"/>
      <abstract>

         <t>Over time, Web browsers have adapted how they use HTTP based upon
         common server configurations and behaviours. While this is necessary
         in the common case, it can be detrimental for performance and
         interoperability.</t>

         <t>This document establishes a mechanism whereby origin servers can make
         available hints for browsers about their preferences and
         capabilities, without imposing overhead on their interactions or
         requiring support for them.</t>

         <t>This is intended to allow browsers to safely optimise connections
         to servers.</t>

      </abstract>
      
      <note title="Note to Readers">
          <t>Feedback for this draft should take place on the
          apps-discuss@ietf.org mailing list <eref
          target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/apps-discuss"/>. </t>
      </note>
   </front>

   <middle>

      <section title="Introduction">

        <t>HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/> clients -- especially browsers --
        typically use hardcoded values or heuristics to determine how many TCP
        connections to use to a server, based on common-case server behaviours
        and limitations.</t>

        <t>Likewise, they often send voluminous request headers (e.g., in
        User-Agent and Allow) because they fear that changing those headers'
        values will break some sites that depend upon specific values.</t>

        <t>These are just two examples of common, conservative behaviour by
          browsers that is good for interoperability, but potentially bad
          for performance in certain circumstances.</t>

        <t>This document specifies a mechanism whereby a HTTP server can
        advertise hints for browsers (and other clients), so that
        communication with them can be optimised.</t>

        <t>It does so by defining a file format for such Browser Hints <xref
        target="format"/>, and defining how clients can discover it for a
        given Web site <xref target="discover"/>. Finally, an extensible
        vocabulary of hints is defined <xref target="hints"/>.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Requirements">
         <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
         NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
         this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
         target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="A file format for Browser Hints" anchor="format">

        <t>Browser hints are conveyed in a JSON <xref target="RFC4627"/>
        formatted file, containing a single object whose member's names are
        browser hints, as defined by the registry <xref
        target="registry"/>.</t>

        <t>For example;</t>
        
        <figure><artwork>
{
"max-conns": 5,
"small-hdrs": true
}
        </artwork></figure>

        <t>By their nature, all browser hints are optional; i.e., browsers are
        free to ignore them.</t>

				<section title="The 'prefixlist' Value Type">
					
					<t>Each browser hint is defined to have a JSON-derived value type;
          e.g., 'string' or 'array'. This section defines a special value
          type, 'prefixlist' that is an array containing one or more arrays,
          each containing a path prefix followed by either 'true' or 'false'
          to indicate whether the hint applies to that path.</t>

					<t>Prefixlists are evaluated in order, with the first
          case-sensitive, character-by-character prefix match for a given
          URI's path determining whether the hint applies.</t>

					<t>For example, given the following hint document:</t>
					
        	<figure><artwork>
{
  "omit-cookies": [
    ["/images/users/", false],
    ["/images/", true]
  ]
}
</artwork></figure>

					<t>We can tell that "omit-cookies" applies to resources under the
						"/images/" path (such as "/images/123.jpg"), except for those 
						under "/images/users/" (such as "/images/users/bob.jpg").</t>

					<t>If a value specified to be a prefixlist is either 'true' or
						'false' that indicates that the hint applies to the whole site,
						or does not apply to the whole site, respectively.</t>
						
					<t>For example,</t>

        	<figure><artwork>
{
  "omit-cookies": true
}
</artwork></figure>

					<t>Indicates that the "omit-cookies" hint applies to the entire
						site.</t>
					
					<t>Prefixlists can only be used when the browser hint's registration
						nominates their use.</t>
					
				</section>

      </section>

      <section title="Discovering Browser Hints for a Web site" anchor="discover">

        <t>The hints relevant to a given site can be determined by fetching
        the URI path "/.well-known/browser-hints" for that site.</t>

        <t>Typically, clients (especially browsers) will not block other 
          requests to a site while fetching the browser hints (because 
          they're optional); instead, it will usually be done concurrently
          with other requests, or on idle connections for future use.</t>

        <t>In this specification, "site" is scoped by the URI scheme and
        authority. As such, all of the following are considered to be
        different sites, and therefore have different browser hints:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>http://foo.com/</t>
          <t>https://foo.com/</t>
          <t>http://foo.com:8000/</t>
          <t>http://www.foo.com/</t>
        </list></t>

        <t>Clients SHOULD follow HTTP 3xx redirects when retrieving
        hints.</t>

        <t>A successful response is valid for its associated site for as long
        as it can be cached in HTTP.</t>

        <t>If the response has a 200 status code but no explicit freshness
        (e.g., a Cache-Control: max-age or Expires: header), clients SHOULD
        cache the response heuristically for a generous fixed period (e.g., 14
        days).</t>

				<t>If the response has a 404 status code but no explicit freshness,
					clients SHOULD cache the response heuristically for a generous
					fixed period (e.g., 14 days).</t>

        <section title="Notifying Clients with the BH Response Header Field">

          <t>It is anticipated that Browser Hints will be used by some, but 
            not all, Web sites. Because clients might be reluctant to 
            optimistically request the hints well-known URI, this document
            defines a new HTTP response header field, BH, to indicate that
            hints are available on a site.</t>
            
          <t>For example,</t>

          <figure><artwork>
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html
Content-Length: 324
BH: 1
</artwork></figure>

          <t>The presence of the BH header field in a response indicates that
            the origin associated with the effective request URI has a 
            Browser Hints resource available at the well-known URI.</t>
            
          <t>The header field value MAY be "0" or "1".</t>

          <t>Origin servers that wish to indicate to clients that Browser
            Hints are available SHOULD include a BH header in all responses
            with a value of "1".
          </t>
          
          <t>Proxy servers that wish to suppress the use of certain Browser
            Hints MAY set (or reset) the BH header's value to "0".
          </t>
            
        </section>
        
        <section title="Interaction with HTTP Proxies">
          
          <t>Browser Hints are intended to optimise the connection between a
          client and the origin server. However, HTTP allows proxies to be
          interposed between browsers and origin servers, meaning that
          careless use of some hints -- especially those that are
          connection-oriented -- might not be applicable, and might even be
          harmful to the proxy.</t>
          
          <t>To mitigate these risks, some hints identify additional
            requirements for clients consuming browser hints when there
            is evidence of a proxy in use.</t>
            
          <t>A proxy is considered to be in use if:</t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>A proxy is known to be present by the client (e.g., through
              its explicit configuration), or</t>
            <t>The BH response header field has a value of "0".</t>
          </list></t>
          
          <t>Note that the presence of the Via header is not considered, 
            because it can also be generated by intermediaries working
            on behalf of the origin server ("reverse proxies").</t>
          
          <t>Proxies MAY modify the value of the BH header field to be
            "0", or insert a BH header field with the value "0" if it is
            not present. Proxies MUST NOT modify a response so that the
            BH header field is "1" where it was previously not.</t>
          
        </section>

      </section>
      
      <section title="Pre-defined Browser Hints" anchor="hints">
        
        <section title="max-conns">

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Browser Hint Name: max-conns</t>
              <t>Description: When present, this hint indicates the maximum
              number of concurrent persistent connections that the site 
              would like clients to use.</t>
              <t>Value Type: number</t>
              <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
            </list>
          </t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="pconn-ip">

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Browser Hint Name: pconn-ip</t>
              <t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that the site
              allows clients to reuse persistent connections keyed by IP
              address, rather than by hostname. Note that all sites that are 
              sharing the connection MUST declare this hint for it to be
              used, and if a transport-layer certificate is in use 
              (e.g., for TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/>), it MUST be valid 
              for all sites.</t>
              <t>Value Type: true | false</t>
              <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
              <t>Specification: [this document]</t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>In other words, if both www.example.com and foo.example.org resolve
            to the address 192.0.2.5, and indicate this hint, then clients
            can send a request to www.example.com and then a request to 
            foo.example.org on the same TCP connection to that address.</t>
            
          <t>If any of the sites grouped together for the purposes of
            pconn-ip declare a max-conns hint, the max-conns value for that 
            address is considered to be the maximum of the declared 
            max-conn hints present.</t>

        </section>
        
				<section title="ip-balance">

					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Browser Hint Name: ip-balance</t>
							<t>Description: When present, this hint indicates a preferred
								policy for clients to handle a DNS lookup that return multiple
								IPv4 addresses for the site.</t>
							<t>Value Type: string</t>
							<t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					
					<t>Defined values include:</t>
					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>round-robin - Use each IP address in succession, using the
								next address each time a new connection is opened.</t>
							<t>random - Use a random IP address from the list for each new 
								connection.</t>
							<t>failover - Use the first IP address, falling back to the
								following address upon failure, and so forth.</t>
							<t>fastest - Attempt to connect to all IP addresses, using the 
								fastest for this and subsequent connections.</t>
						</list>
					</t>

				</section>

				<section title="connect-timeout">

					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Browser Hint Name: connect-timeout</t>
							<t>Description: When present, this hint indicates how long
								the site wishes browsers to wait for a connection to be
								established, in seconds, before considering that connection
								unresponsive.
								</t>
							<t>Value Type: integer</t>
							<t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
						</list>
					</t>

				</section>

				<section title="read-timeout">

					<t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Browser Hint Name: read-timeout</t>
							<t>Description: When present, this hint indicates how long
								the site wishes browsers to wait before considering a 
								connection unresponsive, when data is outstanding (either
								a response or part thereof), in seconds.
								</t>
							<t>Value Type: integer</t>
							<t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
						</list>
					</t>

          <t>Note that requests on timed-out connections can be retried, 
            subject to the constraints of HTTP.</t>

				</section>

        <section title="max-pipeline-depth">

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Browser Hint Name: max-pipeline-depth</t>
              <t>Description: When present, this hint indicates the maximum
              number of pipelined requests per connection that the site would
              like clients to use.</t>
              <t>Value Type: number</t>
              <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
            </list>
          </t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="small-hdrs">

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Browser Hint Name: small-hdrs</t>
              <t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that clients
              can omit the Accept and Accept-Charset request headers when
              communicating with the resource, and that they can use a 
							shortened version of the User-Agent header.</t>
              <t>Value Type: prefixlist</t>
              <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
            </list>
          </t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="relative-referer">

          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>Browser Hint Name: relative-referer</t>
              <t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that servers
	 							 prefer a relative URI in the Referer request header.</t>
              <t>Value Type: true | false</t>
              <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
            </list>
          </t>

        </section>
        
				<section title="chunk-req-bodies">
					
          <t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Browser Hint Name: chunk-req-bodies</t>
							<t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that the server
              can successfully process a request with a chunk-encoded body;
              i.e., that it should not return a 411 Length Required status.
              Note that clients may still require a 411 response status, even
              in when this hint is present. When false, the server may or may
              not require a Content-Length on requests with bodies.</t>
							<t>Value Type: true | false</t>
							<t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
						</list>
					</t>

				</section>

				<section title="omit-cookies">

          <t>
						<list style="symbols">
							<t>Browser Hint Name: omit-cookies</t>
							<t>Description: When true, this hint indicates that cookies <xref
		          target="RFC6265"/> can be omitted in requests.</t>
							<t>Value Type: prefixlist</t>
							<t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
						</list>
  				</t>

				</section>
				
				<section title="cookie-whitelist">
				
				<t>
				      <list style="symbols">
				         <t>Browser Hint Name: cookie-whitelist</t>
				         <t>Description: When present, indicates that the 
				            browser can omit any cookie <xref target="RFC6265"/> whose cookie-name is not a member of the value array.</t>
				         <t>Value Type: array</t>
				         <t>Contact: mnot@mnot.net</t>
				      </list>
				</t>

				</section>
      </section>
                  
      <section title="Security Considerations">
         <t>TBD</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations">
      
       <section title="The 'browser-hints' Well-Known URI">
      
         <t>This document defines the "browser-hints" Well-Known URI 
         <xref target="RFC5785"/>.</t>

         <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>URI suffix: browser-hints</t>
            <t>Change controller: mnot@mnot.net</t>
            <t>Specification document(s): [this document]</t>
            <t>Related information:</t> 
         </list></t>  

       </section>
      
       <section title="The BH HTTP Response Header Field">
         
         <t>This document defines the "BH" HTTP header field, and registers
           it in the Permanent Message Headers registry.</t>
           
         <t><list style="symbols">
           <t>Header field name: BH</t>
           <t>Applicable protocol: HTTP</t>
           <t>Status: Informational</t>
           <t>Author/Change controller: Mark Nottingham, mnot@mnot.net</t>
           <t>Specification document(s): [this document]</t>
           <t>Related information: </t>
         </list></t>
         
       </section>
      
       <section title="The HTTP Browser Hints Registry" anchor="registry">
      
       <t>This document establishes the HTTP Browser Hints Registry.</t>
       
       <t>New hints are registered First Come First Served (see 
         <xref target="RFC5226"/>), by sending e-mail to <eref 
         target="mailto:iana@iana.org"/> (or using other mechanisms, as
         established by IANA).</t>
         
       <t>Registration requests MUST use the following template:</t>
       
       <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Browser Hint Name: [name of hint]</t>
            <t>Description: [description of hint]</t>
            <t>Value Type: [JSON value type] </t>
	          <t>Contact: [e-mail address(es)]</t>
	          <t>Specification: [optional; reference or URI to more info]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      
       <t>New hints MUST be optional; they cannot place requirements upon
       implementations.</t>
       
       <t>Likewise, new hints MUST be relevant to browser use
       cases; other non-browsing hints and metadata would make the hints
       response undesirably large. However, note that non-browser clients
       MAY use them.</t>
       
       <t>Finally, new hints MUST NOT make communication non-conformant with
         HTTP itself; i.e., this is not a mechanism for changing the HTTP
         protocol in incompatible ways. For example, if a hint indicates
         that browsers can compress request headers using GZIP, intermediaries
         that are interposed are likely to fail.</t>
      
       <t>The initial contents of the registry are defined in
         <xref target="hints"/>.</t>
      
       </section>

     </section>

   </middle>

   <back>
      <references title="Normative References">
         &rfc2119; &rfc2616; &rfc4627;
      </references>

      <references title="Informative References">
         &rfc5226; &rfc5246; &rfc5785; &rfc6265;
      </references>
      
      <section title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>Thanks to 
           Mike Belshe,
           Artur Bergman,
           Jason Duell,
           Poul-Henning Kamp,
           Anirban Kundu,
           Patrick McManus,
           Steve Souders, and
					 Martin Thompson
           for their suggestions and feedback.           
          </t>
         <t>The author takes all responsibility for errors and
         omissions.</t>
      </section>
      
   </back>

</rfc>
